<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Queene Elizabeths looking-glasse of grace and glory Wherein may be seen the fortune of the faithfull: that is to say, the wrastling, victory, and reward, or the combat, conquest and crowne of Gods children. All cleerely represented according to Scripture, &amp; illustrated by diuers notable examples of Gods seruants both men and vvomen: and likewise enterlaced with many memorable alligories &amp; morallties: both pleasant and profitable to be read. By I.M. Master of Arts.</title>
            <author>Maxwell, James, b. 1581.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 218 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 120 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07317</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17705</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112547</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847795</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847795</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12856</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07317)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12856)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1387:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Queene Elizabeths looking-glasse of grace and glory Wherein may be seen the fortune of the faithfull: that is to say, the wrastling, victory, and reward, or the combat, conquest and crowne of Gods children. All cleerely represented according to Scripture, &amp; illustrated by diuers notable examples of Gods seruants both men and vvomen: and likewise enterlaced with many memorable alligories &amp; morallties: both pleasant and profitable to be read. By I.M. Master of Arts.</title>
                  <author>Maxwell, James, b. 1581.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 215, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. Alde, for Ed. White dwelling nere the little north-dore of Paules, at the signe of the Gun,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Iames Maxwell.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The looking-glasse of grace and glory.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12856:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12856:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>QVEENE</hi> ELIZABETHS Looking-glaſſe of Grace and Glory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WHEREIN MAY BE ſeen the fortune of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: that is to ſay, the wraſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, victory, and reward, or the combat, conqueſt and Crow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of GODS children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All cleerely repreſented according to Scripture, &amp; illuſtrated by diuers notable examples of Gods ſeruants both men and vvomen: And like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe enterlaced with mans memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble alligories &amp; morallties: both pleaſant and profitable to be read.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By I. M. Maſter of Arts.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12856:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12856:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO</hi> THE GREATEST HONOVR OF THE ME<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MORIE OF THE MOST ILLVSTRIOVS LADY OF SAMOTHEA, <hi>MARJE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N her lifetime Queene-heire of Scotland, Queene-dowa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of France, and by naturall deſcent Princeſſe apparent of England, France, and Ireland;</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A BRANCHE</head>
               <p>Sprung from the Imperiall and Royall ſtocke of CHARLES the great, once the
<pb facs="tcp:12856:3"/>moſt Auguſtious Emperour of Romaines &amp; Germaines, and King of France moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>GREAT-GRAND-CHILDE</head>
               <p>Of the moſt prudent and puiſſant Prince HENRY the ſeuenth, King of England, France, and Ireland, by his eldeſt Daughter borne in the bleſſed Bed of the happy Vnion of the two Roſes, the moſt illuſtrious Queene MARGARET wife to the moſt vertuous &amp; praiſe-worthy Prince IAMES the fourth King of Scots.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>DAVGHTER AND ONELY HEIRE</head>
               <p>Of the moſt noble, worthy &amp; mighty Brita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Prince IAMES the fift King of Scotland, and of the moſt excellent and prudent Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe his wife. Queene MARIE de Lorrayne, Dutcheſſe of Longouille, and daughter of the right magnificent Prince, CLAVDE Duke of Guiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:12856:3"/>
               <head>WIFE</head>
               <p>In firſt mariage, to the moſt Chriſtian King of France, FRANCIS the ſecond; and in ſecond mariage by Gods eſpeciall proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, diſappointing all the policies and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes of the Deuill, and euill men tending to the contrary, wife to the right generous and comely Prince her highnes neareſt &amp; deareſt cooſin, as being deſcended likewiſe from the loynes of HENRY the ſeuenth by his el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Daughter MARGARET Queene of Scotland, by her Daughter in ſecond mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, the right illuſtrious Princeſſe MARGA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RET DOVGLAS Counteſſe of Angus, &amp; Lennox, mother to the ſaid Prince HENRY Lord Darley, Earle of Roſſe, Duke of Alba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, Knight of the moſt renowned order of S. MICHAEL, and King of Scotland.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>MOTHER</head>
               <p>By the foreſaid moſt generous Prince, her Maieſties right entierly beloued husband, of the moſt Auguſtious Prince, our moſt grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soueraigne IAMES the CONCORDER, ſupreme Lord of Samothea, and the firſt
<pb facs="tcp:12856:4"/>Chriſtian Monarch and Vniter of this Ile;</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>GRAND-MOTHER</head>
               <p>Of thee three graces of great Britaine; the moſt hopefull flower of Princes, HENRY the MAGNANIMOVS Prince of Cambria and of Cumbri, the moſt ſweete tender Prince, CHARLES Duke of Yorke and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banie, and the moſt gracefull Princeſſe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame ELIZABETH Infanta of Albion;</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE FLOWER</head>
               <p>Once of the whole women of her age, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with an admirable fortitude, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnificent bountie of minde, adorned with an incomparable pulchritude and beauty of Body; decored with the moſt heroicall and princely properties, and honored moſt, of all the Ladies of the earth, with the many often profered mariages of the greateſt Kings, and nobleſt Princes of Chriſtendome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>TO THE EVERLIVING MEMORIE</head>
               <p>(I ſay) of a matchleſſe MARIE, once on
<pb facs="tcp:12856:4"/>earth full of <hi>Grace,</hi> and now in heauen full of <hi>Glorie:</hi> and euen the <hi>peace-making mother</hi> of Albions greateſt <hi>grace</hi> and vnited <hi>Glorie.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>The Sonnes ſonne of her highnes faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſeruant,</hi> WILLIAM MAXWELL <hi>Sonne to the Lairde of kirkonnell, and in his life-time Man at Armes to the moſt Chriſtian King, doth in moſt humble manner deuote &amp; dedicate the</hi> LOOKING-GLASSE OF GRACE &amp; GLORIE. IAMES MAXWELL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12856:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO</hi> THE MOST ILLVSTRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OVS LADY, AND RIGHT Graceful Princeſſe, the eldeſt &amp; now only Daughter of our moſt gracious and Auguſtious Soueraigne, IAMES the CONCORDER, and of the moſt noble, excellent &amp; worthy Princeſſe, Queene ANNE his wife, Madame ELISABETH Infanta of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bion, all happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Make bolde to preſent vnto your grace a <hi>Looking-glaſſe,</hi> in the which (if it ſhall pleaſe your grace to make vſe of it) ye ſhall ſee cleerly repreſented the <hi>fortune of the faithfull</hi> both heer &amp; hence; to wit, the <hi>Grace</hi> of Gods <hi>Seruants</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12856:5"/>on <hi>Earth,</hi> and the <hi>Glorie</hi> of his elect <hi>children</hi> in <hi>heauen.</hi> It will ſhewe your excellence how excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent a thing it is, for <hi>men</hi> and <hi>women</hi> to <hi>ſerue God</hi> by <hi>fighting</hi> againſt <hi>ſinne, Sathan,</hi> the <hi>world</hi> and the <hi>fleſh,</hi> and euen to be entred into his ſeruice in their <hi>tender yeeres.</hi> It likewiſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeth open the greatnes of the <hi>rewarde</hi> that God hath layed vp for all his <hi>ſincere</hi> and <hi>perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Seruants.</hi> For it pointeth out the right and ſtreighte way that leadeth from the <hi>Garden</hi> of <hi>grace</hi> (wherin the flowers of all Chriſtian vertues are to be found) vnto the <hi>Gallerie</hi> of <hi>Glorie:</hi> for into this there is none entrie, but by the other; euen as of olde, there was no paſſage into the <hi>Temple</hi> of <hi>honour</hi> but through the <hi>Temple</hi> of <hi>vertue,</hi> both builded by the moſt vertuous and honored Emperour <hi>Marcus Marcellus.</hi> In a word, it layeth open vnto the eye, ſuch deſirable things, as the very ſignification of your graces owne Chriſten name may ſerue to put you in minde of: for <hi>ELIZABETH</hi> ſignifieth aſmuch as the <hi>fulneſſe of God;</hi> And the <hi>fulneſſe of God</hi> is none other thing ells, but <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>glorie,</hi> wherof God is full aboue mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but <hi>men</hi> and <hi>women</hi> in a meaſure. To the ſame purpoſe may likewiſe ſerue the ſignification of the name of <hi>ANNA;</hi> which both importeth aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as <hi>grace</hi> or <hi>gratious</hi> and <hi>taking reſt,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:12856:6"/>is ſuch a name, as I aſſure my ſelfe, your grace can neuer forget, as being the name of our moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Queene your graces owne deare <hi>mother</hi> by <hi>generation,</hi> &amp; likewiſe of a moſt vertuous Lady very neare and deare vnto your grace, I meane the Lady <hi>ANNE HARINGTON</hi> your graces moſt worthy <hi>Gouerneſſe,</hi> and euen your <hi>mother</hi> by <hi>Education.</hi> And becauſe that this <hi>bookiſh loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king-glaſſe</hi> preſenteth vnto the eye by reading, and vnto the eare by hearing, the moſt excellent obiects that either eye can ſee, or eare can heare or yet can enter into the heart of man, therefore, haue I made choiſe of two of the moſt excellent Princeſſes, that either eye hath ſeene, or eare hath heard tell of theſe many ages paſt; the one our moſt gratious <hi>Soueraignes</hi> moſt worthy <hi>mother,</hi> and eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your graces moſt noble Grandmother <hi>Queene MARIE</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> the other the moſt renouned <hi>Godmother</hi> of both, <hi>Queene ELIZABETH</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> both of them once on <hi>Earth</hi> ful of <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce,</hi> and now in <hi>heauen</hi> full of <hi>glorie:</hi> And as I haue in a manner Chriſtened it by the name of the the one, euen of a <hi>much-lauded ELIZABETH,</hi> ſo haue I offered it as it were at the ſhrine of the other, I meane of a <hi>matchleſſe MARIE.</hi> The which thing I haue done of ſet purpoſe to doe therby both their names ſome piece of honour, ſo much at
<pb facs="tcp:12856:6"/>leſt as lyeth within the ſmall compaſſe of a meane Schollers ability to performe, as alſo therby to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate and declare vnto all our Britaines, how much I doe diſlike and deteſt the humorous and ſlanderous diſpoſition of ſuch paſſionate perſones of whatſoeuer qualitie or condition, countrie or reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as dare be ſo bold as by word or writte to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace and diffame either of them. And vnto both of them I thought it my duty to performe this Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian duty, but chiefly as being a Scottiſhman born (though likewiſe deſcended from the ancient En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh bloode) vnto my dreade Soueraignes moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mother, and your graces moſt gratious Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother, as ſhe who was not onely the Soueraigne Lady of our Scottiſh people, but alſo the moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy miſtris of mine owne Good ſire, who had the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to ſerue her highnes in France from her lower yeers. Vnto the memory of whoſe moſt noble name, I haue not onely vowed this ſmall part of mine En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Eſſayes, but alſo a parte of my Latine la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours written for the furthering of peace and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde amongs diuided Chriſtianes: towards the which how great a good will I doe beare, may part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare by the 7. chapter of this Booke. To paſſe ouer a defence of her fame which ſome yeeres agoe being in France I began to be about againſt the wicked inuectiues of certaine leud libellers and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers:
<pb facs="tcp:12856:7"/>wiſhing with all mine heart that I may ſee with mine eyes, or rather help with mine hands one day to make a publike bonefire of all ſuch fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand bookes, leaud libels &amp; ſpitefull pamphlets, as haue beene at any time hertofore publiſhed in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, latine or any other language, in poeſie or in proſe to the vnreaſonable and treaſonable reuiling &amp; reproching, blaming and diffaming, of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaide moſt worthy Princeſſe the bleſſed mother of Britaines peace, whoſe noble name in the deſpite of all ſuch detractors, ſhall be euer had of all honeſt hearted perſones in a reſpectfull remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance. That which reſteth. <hi>moſt gracefull Lady,</hi> this <hi>bookiſh Looking-glaſſe,</hi> wherin ye ſhall ſee nothing but ſound diuinity, and religious directions and enducements to primitiue deuotion and pietie, doth offer it ſelfe vnto your graces viewe, and beggeth your gratious acceptance both for the twofold moſt excellent matters ſake therein hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, euen <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Glorie,</hi> &amp; for the two moſt excellent Princeſſes ſake, whoſe <hi>gracious</hi> &amp; <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious</hi> names in the forefront it doth beare. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde it therefore with your fauour able viſage, &amp; garde it with your princely patronage, ſo ſhall it be ſecured vnder your highnes ſhadowe, and I encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to attempt yet more for the honour of your moſt gracefull Grandmothers name, and likewiſe
<pb facs="tcp:12856:7"/>of your graces owne. And ſo wiſhing vnto your grace, the <hi>beſt things</hi> which can be had on <hi>earth,</hi> euen <hi>Grace</hi> with <hi>God</hi> and <hi>man,</hi> and after a long and happie life, the <hi>beſt things</hi> which can be had in <hi>heauen,</hi> euen <hi>Glorie</hi> with <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Angels;</hi> I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your graces ſubmiſſe ſeruant right deuoted to all hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble duties, IAMES MAXWELL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:12856:8"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12856:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> Contents of this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>I.</label>
OF the Chriſtians beginning to ſerue God and to fight againſt ſinne and Sathan in the time of youth. pag. 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8. 9. 10. 11. 12. 13. 14. 15. 16. 17. 18. 19.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>II.</label>
A pleaſant allegorie &amp; moralitie vpon the encounter of yong Dauid with the Lyon, and of Sathans inceſſant compaſſing of the earth, to aſſaile Chriſts ſheepe. pa. 19. 20. 21. 22.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>III.</label>
Of Chriſt our good Shepheards carefull and powerfull protecting of his ſheepe from the deſtroying violence of the deuouring Lyon, pag. 22. 23.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>IIII</label>
A comfortable morall vpon King Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadnezars chooſing of yong children to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d before him, and his allotting of a portion of his owne meate and drink for their foode,
<pb facs="tcp:12856:9"/>together, with another delectable morall vpon the new wine, and new veſſels mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the Goſpell. pa. 11. 12. 13. 14. 204.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>V.</label>
Of the policies and practiſes of the fleſh, and in what manner the Chriſtian muſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer and diſappoint the ſame: pag. 24 25. 26. 27. 28. 29. 30. 31. 32. 33. 34. 35. 36. 37. 40.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>VI.</label>
A notable allegorie and morality vpon the hiſtories of Sampſon and Dalilah, Dauid and Abſalom, Sara and Hagar, the harlot and the fooliſh yong man, mentioned in the Prouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes: pag. 25. 26. 27. 28. 29. 30. 31. 37. 38. 39. 176. 177.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>VII</label>
Of the good Chriſtians vanquiſhing of the vanities of the worlde, &amp; the allurements therof: pag. 41. 42. 43, 44. 45 46. 47.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>VIII</label>
A delectable Allegorie &amp; moralitie vpon the hiſtories of Ehud and Eglon, of Iael and Siſera, of Ioſeph and Putiphars wife, and of the two women mentioned in Salomons Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement, pag. 46. 47. 48, 49. 50. 51. 52.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>X.</label>
Of Sathans guilefull enticing, and forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aſſailing of the Chriſtian ſoule, and how w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> muſt fight againſt his violent inuaſions, &amp; fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rauculent perſuaſions: p. 54. 55. 56. 57. 58. 62. 66. 67. 68. 69. 70. 73.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12856:9"/>
                  <label>X.</label>
A notable allegorie &amp; moralitie vpon the encounter of yong Dauid and Goliath, vpon the Bridegromes ſweete and perſuaſiue ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vnto the Spouſe in the Canticles, as alſo vpon Sathans tempting of the firſt woman, &amp; of our Sauiour Chhriſt: pa. 33. 55. 56. 57. 58. 59. 60. 61. 62. 63. 64. 65. 66. 69. 70. 71. 72.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>XI.</label>
Of the ſimplicity, ſincerity, and ſingleneſſe of heart that ought to be vſed of Chriſtians in ſeruing of God, pag. 76. 77. 78. 79. 80. 81. 82. 83. 84. 25.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>XII.</label>
Of the rigteouſnes, Equitie, and charitie that ſhould be in Chriſtianes: pag. 86. 87. 88. 89. 90. 91. 92. 93. 94. 95. 96. 97. 98. 99. 100. 101.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>XIII</label>
Of the earneſt ſtudy of peace, vnitie and concorde that ought to be amongs Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s both in church and common weale: pa 102. 103. 104. 105. 106. 107. 108. 109. 110. 111. 112. 143. 114. 115. 116.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>XIV</label>
Of the nature, efficacy, force and effects of iuſtifying faith in Chriſtians, pag. 117. 118. 119. 120. 121. 122. 123. 124. 125. 126. 127. 128. 129. 130.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>XV.</label>
Of the vnſpeakeable and happy hope of Chriſtians: p. 131. 132. 133. 134. 135. 136. 137. 138. 139.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12856:10"/>
                  <label>XVI.</label>
Of the excellency of Gods worde, &amp; how that Chriſtians ought to reade &amp; heare the ſame reuerently, affect it feruently, beleeue it conſtantly, &amp; practiſe it diligently in their life and conuerſation: pa. 140. 141. 142. 147. 148. 149. 150. 151. 152. 153. 154. 155. 156. 157. 158. 159.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>XVII.</label>
Of the manner how the Chriſtian muſt draw the ſword of Gods worde againſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than in all Sortes of tentations, with a morall vpon the encounter of Iudith and Olofernes: pag. 141. 142. 143. 144. 145. 146.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>XVIII</label>
Of faſting, and of the great efficacy ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and how that Gods children in all ages, both men and women, haue giuen them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues much vnto the exerciſe therof: pag. 160. 161. 162. 163. 164. 165. 166. 171. 173.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>XIX.</label>
A pleaſant allegorie and moralitie vpon the hiſtorie of Eſter, Mordecaie and Haman: pag. 53. 168. 169. 170.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>XX.</label>
Of the admirable vertue of prayer, and of many notable examples of the wonderfull effects thereof: pag, 173. 174. 175. 176. 177. 178. 179. 180.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>XXI.</label>
A comfortable allegorie &amp; morality vpon the praying of Moſes againſt Amaleck, of Sampſon praying for the reſtoring of his
<pb facs="tcp:12856:10"/>ſtrength againſt the Philiſtims; of Samuel Praying againſt the ſame Philiſtims; of Dauid praying againſt Achitophell: with diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; pag. 175. 176. 177, 178.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>XXII.</label>
Of the Chriſtianes continuing and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering in Gods ſeruice, &amp; in fighting againſt ſinne and Sathan, aye vntill the victorie be obtained: pag. 182. 183. 184. 185. 186. 187. 188. 189.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>XXIII</label>
A delectable allegorie and moralitie vpon the victorie of Abraham againſt Chedar-Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; of Debora againſt Siſera; of Dauid againſt Goliah, and of Ezekiah againſt Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacherib, pa. 190. 191. 192. 193.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>XXIV</label>
Of Gods ample and honorable rewarding of all ſuch as fight againſt ſinne valiantly, and continue conſtantly in his ſeruice vnto the end: pag. 194. 195. 196. 197. 198. 199. 200. 201. 202. 203. 204.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>XXV.</label>
A delectable allegorie and moralitie vpon the remuneration and exaltation of Ioſeph, Othniel, Dauid, Daniel, and Mordecaie, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at the hands of Pharao, Caleb, Saul, Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhazzar, and Ahaſueroſh, and of the greatnes of the glorie that ſhall be heaped vpon the heads of Gods good Seruants. pa. 196. 199. 200. 201. 202. 206. 267. 208. 209. 210. 211. 212.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:12856:11"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <head type="sub">Such eſcapes as haue beene committed in the preſſe, the gentle Reader ſhall find corrected heere in this Page.</head>
            <p>PAg. 23. lin. 2 for they, read. 1) p. 34 lin. 4. for labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth read lauer) p. 46. lin. 21. for aſſemble read re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble) p. 52. lin. 1. after) ſelfe, adde perfite) p. 59 lin. 9. for and, read end) p 69 lin. 21, for whom, read who) p. 84. lin. 1. for faith read truth) p. 108 lin. 18, for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions were, read contentious men) p. 109. li 16. for nicenes, read nicetics) p. 173. lin. 1. for force, read face.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:12856:11"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12856:12"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12856:12"/>
            <head>The looking-glaſſe of grace and glory.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 1.</hi> That the Chriſtian is called to hee Chriſts Seruant &amp; Souldier from the Cradle and in the very ſpring time of youth.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ans life is a warrefare, and a time of temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; triall:<note place="margin">2. Corr. 10 4.</note> for no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is he layed into the Cradle, to grow and waxe according to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but almoſt as ſoone is hee called into the Campe, to bee <hi>Christs Souldier,</hi> and to beare ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:12856:13"/>
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> was but a young Boy,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 16.11.12.13. &amp; 17.33.39.42.49.50.</note> when he went out againſt <hi>Goliah,</hi> and ouercame him: and all Gods beloued ones (for <hi>Dauid</hi> ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>beloued</hi>) muſt goe out againſt the ſpirituall <hi>Goliah</hi> the great Captaine of ſpiritual captiuitie, (for <hi>Goliah</hi> ſignifieth <hi>captiuity</hi>) they muſt I ſay goe out againſt him when as yet they are young.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> was no ſooner annoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the hand of <hi>Samuel,</hi> but he began to be valiant, <hi>for the Spirit of the Lord came vpon Dauid from that day forward:</hi> and weare no ſooner made <hi>Chriſtians</hi> by the annoynting of Baptiſme, (for as <hi>Chriſt</hi> is as much as <hi>the annointed,</hi> ſo <hi>Chriſtian</hi> is as much as <hi>one that is annointed</hi>) but as ſoone our names are rolled vp among Gods warriours.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 16.13. &amp; 17.34.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Samuel</hi> had no ſooner powred
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12856:13"/>out his horne of holy oyle vpon <hi>Dauids</hi> head, but as ſoone hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to encounter with a Lyon which came to aſſaile and ſlay the ſheepe which he kept in the field, and ouercame him, and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him as he did alſo a Beare: &amp; the appointed of God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 45.7. Heb. 1.9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Corr. 1.21 1. Iohn 2.20.27.</note> (for <hi>Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> ſignifieth ſo much) I meane Gods Miniſters, his Prieſts, and Prophets, or rather the holy Ghoſt, haue no ſooner annointed vs with the oyle of gladnes, but as ſoone we muſt begin to fight vnder our Sauiours bloody en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, &amp; croſſie Banner,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 17 40</note> prefigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by <hi>Dauids</hi> ſtaffe, againſt the roaring and deuowring Lyon the Deuill: we muſt I ſay begin to ſerue God euen when as yet we are young.</p>
               <p>Thus we read of <hi>Samuel</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, how that he was conſecrated
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12856:14"/>vnto the Lord, being yet a yong childe, euen as ſoone as he was wained, as <hi>Sampſon</hi> and <hi>Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt</hi> were ſet a part to Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice from the wombe.<note place="margin">Iudges. 13.5.7. Luke. 1.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Samuel</hi> (as hath bene already ſaid) ſignifieth as much as the appoynted of God; and the good Chriſtian, who is appoynted of God vnto life and glory, ſhould as ſoone as he is wained from the breaſt, or at leaſt as ſoone as he commeth to the yeares of diſcretion, begin to learne how to ſerue God, and how to eſchue ſinne, and how to fight againſt the Deuill, the world &amp; the fleſh, according to the tenor of the vow which was made in his name, when as hee was baptiſed. And truly as Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents offer vp their Children for a liuing ſacrifice vnto God, when as they make them to be baptiſed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12856:14"/>ſo ought they take great care, that as ſoone as they come to knowledge, they may both learn and put in practiſe, the whole Chriſtian duties that doe belong vnto that holy ordinance &amp; vow. Likewiſe <hi>Eſter</hi> was trained vp in the feare and knowledge of God from her youth: and as many as are of Gods ſecret and hidden ones (for <hi>Eſter</hi> ſignifieth ſecret or hidden) muſt from their youth be inſtructed and trained vp in Gods feare;<note place="margin">Eſter 14.5.</note> for the man or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that feareth God feruently, ſhall not need to feare the Deuils hoſtility. Alſo of <hi>Obadiah</hi> King <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habs</hi> Steward, it is ſaid that he fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red God greatly from his youth,<note place="margin">1. King. 18.3.12.</note> by whoſe godly example al Gods Seruants (for <hi>Obadiah</hi> ſignifieth as much as Gods ſeruant) are taught to begin Gods ſeruice in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12856:15"/>their young yeares, and not to delay it vntill old age. The ſame thing did likewiſe <hi>Daniel, Hanani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah, Michael, Azariah, Tobiah,</hi> and <hi>Timothie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 1.4.5 6.8.12.15.17. Toh 1.10. &amp; 2.13. 2. Tim. 3 15.</note> who is recorded to haue knowne the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of a childe. <hi>Daniel</hi> is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much by interpretation as the iudgement of God, and <hi>Hananiah</hi> the grace and vertue of God, and <hi>Azariah</hi> the helpe of God, and <hi>Tobiah</hi> the goodnes of God, and <hi>Timothie</hi> the honor or an hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of God: and as many as deſire to taſte of Gods goodnes, to haue his helpe in time of need, &amp; to finde mercy and fauour at his hands, chiefly in the day of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they muſt imitate theſe young mens example and begin to proue <hi>Timothies,</hi> that is hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of God, when as yet they are young.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:12856:15"/>And therefore <hi>Salomon</hi> exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth all young folkes to thinke earneſtly on Gods ſeruice in their youth, and not to defer or delay this maine duty,<note place="margin">Eccle. 12.1</note> 
                  <hi>Remember now thy Creator in the dayes of thy youth, whiles the euil dayes come not, nor the yeares approach wherein thou ſhalt ſaywe haue no pleaſure in them.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay: Thou that art a young man or woman, if euer thou meaneſt to remember thy duty towards God, remember it now whilſt thou art young, old-age is forgetfull, and youth is moſt able in memory, and moſt apt for remembrance, therefore either remember now or els ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: for if thou forget God, when thou art young, when thy memory is at the beſt, it ſhall be hard for thee to remember him when thou art old, when
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12856:16"/>thy memory ſhal be at the worſt. Remember him therefore now, and delay it not till heereafter: to day, and defer not til to morrow; this yere, and put it not off til the next; in thy youth, and tary not till thou be olde. The preſent time is the ſureſt time, for what woteſt thou if thou ſhalt liue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till old age? and youth is the beſt time as being the flower of mans time: and what knoweſt thou if God will accept of the ſeruice of thy withered old age, if thou haſt refuſed him the ſeruice of thy flouriſhing young yeares? God giueth vs our whole time, be it ſhort or be it long: is it not good reaſon then that we yeelde him the ſeruice of our whole time, but chiefely of the chiefe and beſt part of our time? farre be it from vs then to doe God ſuch a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12856:16"/>grieuous wrong as to reſerue for him therotten dregges of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crepit and old dayes. No maſter will be content that the ſeruant whome he hyred for the whole day, ſhould enter to his ſeruice at the gloming of the day, or at the going downe of the Sunne: And ſhall we think that the great Maſter of mankinde, can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that his hired ſeruant ſhould enter to his ſeruice in the euening he being hyred in the morning? mans life is as a day, a ſhort life as a winters day,<note place="margin">Mathew 20.1.2.</note> a long life as a ſommers day, but be the day of a mans life ſhort or be it long, be it faire or be it foule, it becommeth alwaies the good ſeruant to riſe early, and to fall to his worke ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly, to labour dilligently and to continue conſtantly, vntill the end of the day. As <hi>Elkanah</hi> with
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12856:17"/>his wiues <hi>Anna</hi> and <hi>Peninna,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 1.2 19.</note> roſe vp early to worſhip God, ſo as many as haue the zeale of God (for <hi>Elkanah</hi> ſignifieth the zeale of God) they will ſerue God ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, euen in the morning of their young yeres. And in ſo doing the Chriſtian man ſhall proue an <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kanah</hi> in deed, that is, a man indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Gods zeale, and the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian woman ſhal proue an <hi>Anna,</hi> that is, a gratious woman, and a <hi>Peninna</hi> that is, a precious ſtone in the ſpirituall building of Chriſts Church.</p>
               <p>God is the firſt aſwell as the laſt;<note place="margin">Reuct. 1.11 ſay 44.6.</note> the alpha and the beginning, as well as the omega and the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; and therefore he claimeth our firſt yeares as well as the laſt, and the beginning of our life as well as the ending thereof. Our young dayes are our beſt dayes,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12856:17"/>&amp; our young yeares are our moſt pleaſant yeares, for ſo <hi>Salomon</hi> doth ſignifie, when he calleth the daies of our olde age our euill daies,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12, 1</note> and ſaith that in the yeares thereof man hath no pleaſure; And therefore in our beſt dayes we muſt doe the beſt thing that man can doe, which is to ſerue God: and in our moſt pleaſant yeres we muſt be about the moſt pleaſant ſtudy of the pleaſing of God.</p>
               <p>As King <hi>Nebuchanezzar</hi> made choyſe of young children, faire and wel fauoured to ſtand before him,<note place="margin">Dan. 1.3.4.5.</note> and did commune with them familiarly, to whome hee did likewiſe aſſigne a portion of his owne meat, and of the ſame wine which he himſelfe dranke, for their nouriſhment, So the King of Kings, maketh choyſe of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12856:18"/>ſuch perſons as in their young yeares, when as yet they were tender, haue beautified their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man by the meanes of Gods ſeruice; for the faireſt and beſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured thing in the world is a ſoule that feareth God, and figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth againſt ſinne. And it is euen ſuch that our great King dooth chooſe for his minions and chief fauorites, to talke and commune with them as the children of his loue and delight. And to them he alloweth a portion of the meate of God, off his own Table; for he giueth them to eat of the hidden Manna and of the tree of life, which is in the mids of the Paradiſe of God,<note place="margin">Reuela. 2.7.17. Mat. 26.29 Ioh. 15.1. Cantie. 2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp; 8.2 Reuel. 14 1.2 3.4 5.</note> and he giueth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to drink of the new wine, out of the celeſtiall wine ſeller, ſuch as the Vine which is aboue doth yeeld, which maketh them ſing a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12856:18"/>new ſong before Gods ſeat, euen a ſong of exultation, and Iubilati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And as they doe now follow the Lamb whither ſoeuer he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in heauen, ſo being on earth among men, they were as the firſt fruits vnto God; that is, they were ſuch as in their very firſt yeares gaue themſelues to Gods ſeruice by the ſtudy of ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of newnes and holynes of life.<note place="margin">Reuel. 21.5</note> He that maketh all thinges new, maketh alſo a new wine for all ſuch as ſhall be new creatures. Wherefore, to the end we may then drinke of that new ſpiced wine,<note place="margin">Cantie. 8.2</note> of the pomegranate of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice, let vs now endeauoure to put on the new man,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.23 24</note> which after God is created in righteouſnes, and true holynes, according as the Apoſtle exhorteth,<note place="margin">2 Cor 5.17</note> 
                  <hi>If any man be in Christ, let him be a new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12856:19"/>olde things are paſſed away, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold all things are become new.</hi> No man putteth new wine into olde veſſels ſaith our Sauiour;<note place="margin">Mat. 9.17.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt both be made new veſſels by newnes of life, before we can receaue that new wyne of glory in Gods kingdome: and alſo before we be old veſſels, in yeares, we muſt labour to receiue into the new veſſels of our young hearts the new wine of Gods re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing grace, by following his ſeruice in our young yeares. For it is very likely that God will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer put the new wine of a new life into ſuch an olde veſſell as had once refuſed to receaue it, when as it was new; I meane, that it is not likely that God will euer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue ſuch an old man or woman into his ſeruice, as had refuſed it being called thereunto when as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12856:19"/>they were young.<note place="margin">Hebr. 16.17 12.</note> As <hi>Eſau</hi> when he would haueinherited the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing was reiected, and found no place to repentance, though he ſought the bleſſing with teares: ſo thoſe kinde of perſons when they would with all their heart be receaued into Gods ſeruice, they ſhall be reiected, neither ſhall they finde any place to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance or attendance, though they ſhould ſeeke Gods ſeruice with teares.</p>
               <p>Thus we ſee then how it ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs in hand to be entred into Gods ſeruice, when as yet wee are young &amp; euen little children: and therfore our Sauiour was wont alwaies to make much of little children, to the end they might be more and more encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged in the way of Gods feare: he inuited litle children to come
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12856:20"/>vnto hìm, and he bleſſed them, &amp; kiſſed them, when they came, and held them in his armes: <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer little children to come vnto mee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 19.13 14 15. Marke 10.13.14.15 16</note> 
                  <hi>and forbid them not, for of ſuch is the kingdome of God,</hi> ſaid our ſweete Sauiour to his diſciples.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, 8 1.2.</note> and as the Pſalmiſt ſheweth how that God ſometimes doth confound his foes by the mouth of ſublings and babes;<note place="margin">Mat 11.25</note> ſo doth our Sauiour thank the Father for reuealing &amp; opening the myſteries of his kingdome vnto Babes; yea he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendeth vnto his diſciples, the imitation of ſuch little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren as had begunne to ſpell out the right way of Gods ſeruice. <hi>Verily I ſay vnto you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math 18.1 2 3.4 5.6.10.</note> 
                  <hi>except ye be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted and become as little children, ye ſhall not enter into the Kingdome of heauen: Whoſoeuer therefore ſhall humble himſeiſe as this little childe,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12856:20"/>the ſame is the greateſt in the kingdome of heauen: And whoſoeuer ſhall receaue ſuch a little childe in my name receaueth me: ſee that ye deſpiſe not one of theſe little ones, for I ſay vnto you, that in heauen their Angells al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies behold the face of my father, which is in heauen.</hi> Our Sauiour had a chiefe care of wel-enclined young children, and ſuch as had any ſeeds or beginnings of grace in the ſpringtime of their youth,<note place="margin">Mat. 19.16 20. Marke 10.17.20.21</note> he loued them moſt dearly. Thus hee loued the young man that came to aſke him, touching the way how to be ſaued, who ſaid, that he had obſerued the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements from his youth, And by way of humaine affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he loued moſt of all his diſciples Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> who was the youngeſt of them al,<note place="margin">Ioh 13.23. &amp; 19.26</note> ſo that he is called <hi>the diſciple whome Ieſus loued,</hi> for there
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12856:21"/>is nothing that the Lord taketh ſo great delight in as to ſee a man or woman beging in their young yeares to ſerue God and to fight againſt Sathan, ſinne, the world, and the fleſh. And as our Sauiour did alwaies encourage young children in the way of Gods feare ſo his beloued diſciple St. <hi>Iohn</hi> whome he loued moſt, becauſe he was the youngeſt of them all, and for that he was ſo forward in godlines in ſo young yeares; he doth after his louing Lords ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample incourage little children and young men in the ſame way. <hi>Little children I write vnto you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Iohu 2.1.12.13.14.18.28.</note> 
                  <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe your ſinnes are forgiuen you for his names ſake. I write vnto youyoung men becauſe ye haue ouercome the wicked. I write vnto you Bahes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ye haue knowne the father; I haue written vnto you young men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12856:21"/>ye are ſtrong and the worde of God abideth in you, and ye haue ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the wicked. And now little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren abide in him, that when he ſhall appeare we may be bold &amp; not be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med before him at his comming.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus we ſee then that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans muſt begin to fight and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſinne, and Sathan in their very youth. The Lyon that you<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g <hi>Dauid</hi> encountred and ouercame was but a young one, and had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaded but one ſheepe: but the Lyon that the young Chriſtian muſt encounter and quell, is an old one, &amp; would faine ſwallow vp all Chriſts ſheepe; <hi>your aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary the deuil</hi> (ſaith the great Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Saint <hi>Peter</hi>)<note place="margin">1, Pet. 5.8.</note> 
                  <hi>as a roaring Lyon walketh about ſeeking whome he may deuour.</hi> He is alwaies hungry and bloodthirſtie,<note place="margin">Iohn 8.44.</note> 
                  <hi>for he bath beene a murtherer from the beginning,</hi> ſaith
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12856:22"/>bleſſed Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> and therefore is he alwaies roaring &amp; roauing abroadafter his pray. His throate is as an open Sepulchre, yea it is wide as hell, and therefore vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiable and cannot be filled with thouſands of ſheepe: and yet he walketh along continually, and runneth about mceſſantly, to catch (if he can) ſome one ſilly wandring ſheepe, to abate ſome part of his hungry and vnſatiable appetite. And it is I ſay for this end, that he doth bothwalk along the earth, and run round about the earth, without beeing any whit wearied or taking any reſt, And therefore Sathan being aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked on a time of the Lorde whence he came? anſwered,<note place="margin">Iob. 1.7</note> 
                  <hi>from compaſſing the earth to and fro, and from walking in it.</hi> He is a <hi>walker,</hi> and therefore he walketh with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12856:22"/>the wicked, and with them hee doth reſt, whenſoeuer he taketh any reſt: euen with and on al ſuch as walke in the waies of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. He is likewiſe a <hi>Compaſſer,</hi> for hee compaſſeth the godly round about, ſeeking to circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent them, to deceaue them, &amp; deſtroy them, but findeth no reſt to the ſole of his foote; therin re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebling <hi>Noahs</hi> doue, but yet more his blacke rauen. For as the rauen did nothing els but flitter to and fro vntill the waters were dryed vp vpon the earth, ſo doth this reſtles rauen, no other thing els but flitter and flee to and fro, and round about, vntill at what time there be no more ſinful ſoules to deſtroy vpon earth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sathan</hi> compaſſeth the earth, and the whole earth, becauſe he would conſume the whole earth,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12856:23"/>and ſwallow vp all <hi>Chriſts ſheepe,</hi> on earth. But he ſhall miſſe of his ayme: for <hi>the Shepheard of Iſrael, that leadeth Ioſeph like ſheepe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 80.1. &amp; 121.3.4.</note> 
                  <hi>euen he that keepeth Iſrael doth neither ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber nor ſleepe.</hi> The olde Lyon may well come with <hi>Dauids</hi> young Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and his Beare to the flock, to take a ſheepe out of the fold; But as <hi>Dauid</hi> reſcued his ſheepe, and tooke it out of the young Lyons mouth,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.25.</note> and ſlew him that came to flay, the like ſhall our great Shepheard doe. The good Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard that calleth his own Sheep by name, and leadeth them out and goeth before them, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth his life for them, and dooth not leaue them when the Wolfe or the Lyon cometh, he ſhall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen defend his ſheep, and reſcue them, and ſaue them from the olde Lyons iawes. <hi>My ſheepe</hi> (ſaith
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:12856:23"/>he) <hi>heare my voyce, &amp; I know them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 10.2.3 4.11.14.27.28.29.</note> 
                  <hi>and they follow me, and they giue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them eternall life, and they ſhal ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer periſh, neither ſhal any pluck them out of mine hand. My father which gaue them me is greater then all, and none is able to take them out of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our good Shepheard hath not onely giuen his life for his ſheep, but he giueth likewiſe eternal life to his ſheepe. So that the roaring and deuowring Lyon may well compaſſe them, but he ſhall not catch them; and though he catch them, yet ſhall he not be able to quel them or kil them; he may well ſcatter them with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, but he ſhall not be able to conſume them with deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">Heb 2.14.</note> yea he himfelfe ſhall in the end be deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>All Chriſtians then are called
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:12856:24"/>from the very firſt houre of their ſpirituall birth, to be Soldiers &amp; warriours againſt the <hi>Deuill,</hi> the <hi>world,</hi> and the <hi>fleſh.</hi> The <hi>fleſh</hi> is our enemy within vs, like an homebred foe; the <hi>world</hi> is our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy without vs, like a forraine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oe; and the <hi>deuill</hi> is our foe in both faſhions, within vs, without vs, yea and round about vs. Theſe be the three enemies which wee haue to encounter, and theſe be the aduerſaries we muſt ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP 2. Of the chriſtians figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againſt the fleſh and <hi>the luſts thereof.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> practiſed and allured <hi>Dalilah</hi> to deceaue
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12856:24"/>
                  <hi>Sampſon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">ludge 16</note> promiſing her ſo many ſhekels of ſiluer for a reward; ſo the ſpiritual Philiſtims, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curers of mans double decay and deſtruction, euen both of body and of ſoule, (for <hi>Philiſtim</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth a double decay) they will practiſe the conſuming <hi>Dalilah</hi> of our fleſh, (for <hi>Dalilah</hi> ſignifyeth a conſumer) to deceaue vs, to the end we may be vanquiſhed and ouercome in moſt wretched ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
               <p>And the <hi>Dalilah</hi> of our fleſh, wil not faile to betray vs vnto the Princes of the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Princes that rule in the aire,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.2. &amp; 6.12</note> for the hire of ſome fleſhly pleaſure or profite, except that we be aware. She will make vs ſleepe on her knees, that is to ſay, ſhe will lull vs, and rocke vs a ſleepe in the cradle, of ſecurity,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12856:25"/>and in the meane time ſhe will ſhaue off the ſeauen lockes of our head; that is, ſhe will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaue vs of the ſeauen gifts of Gods ſpirit,<note place="margin">Reuel. 3.1. &amp; 4 5.</note> as of faith, charity, righteouſnes, humility, patience, temperance, and dilligence; and ſo in end, make vs looſe our whole ſpirituall ſtrength. So that it ſhall be an eaſie thing for the Philiſtims of our affections, to put out our eyes, euen the eyes of our vnderſtanding, and for the Princes of the Philiſtims, I mean the principalities and powers that rule in the ayre, to binde vs <hi>Sampſon</hi> like with fetters, ſo that we cannot walke in the waies of righteouſnes and holynes as we ought. And therefore whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the <hi>Dalilah</hi> of our fleſh begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to entangle vs, wee muſt learne of <hi>Sampſon</hi> to beguile her,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:12856:25"/>and to practiſe the wiſdome of the ſerpent in the olde Serpents behalfe.<note place="margin">Mat. 10.16</note> We muſt I ſay deceaue this deceitfull fleſh of ours, at that time that ſhe ſeeketh moſt to deceaue vs; and this we muſt doe not onely once, twiſe, thrice as <hi>Sampſon</hi> did, but alwaies by perſeuering vnto the end. And therefore though <hi>Dalilah</hi>-like, our fleſh ſhould be importunate vpon vs with her faire perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to enſnare vs, yet muſt wee beware to tell her our whole heart with <hi>Sampſon,</hi> otherwiſe we ſhall not faile to be both ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen &amp; ſhamed with <hi>Sampſon.</hi> Yea the eyes of our vnderſtanding ſhall be put out as were <hi>Sampſons</hi> two bodily eyes, and the feete of our ſpirituall faculties ſhall be fettered with the fetters of fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly luſts, and we ſhall be made to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:12856:26"/>grinde in the priſon houſe of a grieued ſpirit: for where the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God is not, there is capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity, as <hi>where the ſpirit of the Lord is,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Corr. 3.17. 2. Sam 15. &amp; 18</note> 
                  <hi>there is liberty</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>fleſh Abſalon</hi>-like, will vſe many policies and practiſes to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire to the ſoueraignty ouer the ſoule. She will vſe great craft to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the affections, to entiſe them to diſlike of the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſpirit: ſhe will ſhew her ſelfe more forward to pleaſe the affections, then the reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble part of the ſoule can doe, ſhe will as it were put forth her hand to the affections and kiſſe them, and make much of them, to the end that ſhee may ſteale away their obedience from the ſpirit: No, ſhe will not faile to rebell againſt the ſpirit (<hi>for the fleſh</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>luſteth againſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:12856:26"/>the ſpirit</hi>) euen as <hi>Abſaion</hi> did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt K. <hi>Dauid</hi> his Father, who ſtole away the peoples hearts fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, and roſe vp rebelliouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him.</p>
               <p>And though it fall out often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, that the <hi>Abſalo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> of our fleſh prevaile over the <hi>Dauid</hi> of our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rit, and make a great ſlaughter of his ſubjects; that is, of good mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, &amp; holy reſolutions: yet in end, the <hi>Abſalom</hi> of our fleſh ſhall get the foyle. For when our fleſh <hi>Abſalom</hi>-like, ſhall be in a maner mounted vpon the Mule of ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualitie, it ſhall be left hanging as it were by the haire of an hard, &amp; heavie heart, vpon the Oake of Gods anger, and it ſhall be ſmote with the three darts of three-fold affliction, in goods, in body, and in minde, till it be mortified and ſlaine by the terror of the tenne
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:12856:27"/>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundments, as <hi>Abſalom</hi> was killed by <hi>Ioabs</hi> tenne ſeruants, and ſo be caſt as it were, into the pitte of repentance, for all by-paſt miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanours.</p>
               <p>The fleſh wil play with the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, as the Harlot in the Proverbs doth with the fooliſh yong man.<note place="margin">Prouer. 7.</note> She wil be alwaies abroad to ſpy our opportunities, ſhe will be ſtill lying in waite at euery cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, hunting after occaſions and adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tages for her, wher-through ſhe may catch the ſpirit and kiſſe him, and with an impudent face allure him to yeild vnto her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires.</p>
               <p>The fleſh will decke her ſelfe with all coſtlye Ornaments; ſhe will perfume and paynt her ſelfe with the moſt artificial ointme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, and will then ſay vnto the Soule, come, let vs take our pleaſure in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:12856:27"/>daliance, let vs delight our eyes with ſenſuall ſhewes and ſightes, our eares with amorous &amp; licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ſounds, our ſmell with the moſt exquiſite &amp; ſweet ſauours, our taſte with the moſt delicious drinkes, and daintieſt meates; let vs take our fill of loue, of ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall pleaſures and paſſe-times, as long as the morning of our life ſhall laſt, let vs eat and drink, ſport and play, ſing &amp; dance, for to morrow we ſhall dye. Thus the fleſh with her flattering lips wil entiſe the ſoule, &amp; the fooliſh and vnſanctified ſoule will not ſticke to yeeld vnto her, and to follow her ſtraight waies, as an oxe that goeth to the ſlaughter, and as a foole to the ſtockes for correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, til adart ſtrike through his liuer, euen the dart of a rele<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting remorſe. But the wiſe &amp; the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:12856:28"/>ſanctified ſoule will be loath to decline to her wayes, or to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or walke in her paths; for it knoweth well that ſhe hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed many to fal downe wounded, and that troupes of ſtrong men haue bene ſlaine by her; for her houſe is the way vnto the graue, which goeth down to the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of death. The fleſh wil ſpeak to the Soule, as the ſpouſe in the Canticles doth to the Bride, <hi>Open vnto me my Siſter, my loue, my doue, my vnde filed, for mine head is full of dew,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant 5.2.3</note> 
                  <hi>and my lockes with the drops of the night.</hi> But for al this her ſweet alluring ſpeech, and perſwaſiue talke, the Chriſtian Soule muſt not by yeelding vnto the fleſh, riſe to let her in: and therefore the ſoule muſt returne her this anſwere, or the like: ſoft, <hi>Fleſh,</hi> for I am not thy Siſter, but thy
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:12856:28"/>Soueraigne, and thou art not my Siſter but my Seruant; It dooth not befit the Miſtris to riſe &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the dore to her maind, neither muſt the maid preſume to expect any ſuch ſeruice at her Miſtris hands. It is thy part to obey, and not to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund, to attend vpon my pleaſure, and not to play the part of a miſtris, or yet of a mate in my behalfe: or els let the ſoule returne her the firſt anſwere of the ſpouſe, <hi>I haue put off my coate, how ſhall I put it on? I haue waſhed my feete, how ſhall I defile them?</hi> that is to ſay,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 22.23.24. Colloſſ. 3.9.10. Galla. 3.26 27 Mat. 22.11 12. Tit, 3.5.6. Reuel. 19.8</note> I haue caſt off old <hi>Adams</hi> ſkinne coate of originall corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by baptiſme, and haue put on the new fine linnen coate, of the white robe of Chriſts righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, the which is not onely imputed vnto me by the father, but alſo imparted vnto me by his
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:12856:29"/>ſpirit:<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.26 27. Act 22.16. Tit. 3.5. 1. Pet. 3.21 1. Co. 6.11 Iohn 3.5.</note> farre be it from me to put my new coate off, or mine olde coate on againe. I haue waſhed my feet in the lauer of rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration with the fount-water of the fountaine of God; farre be it from me to defile them againe, by yielding vnto any ſenſual ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion or ſinfull temptation.<note place="margin">Can. 5 4.5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The alluring fleſh will alſo i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate the Bridegrome, and put in her hand as it were by the hole of the doore to open it her ſelfe, with her owne fingers; but the ſoule for all that muſt not bee in heart affectioned towards her, to yeeld vnto her, or to ſuffer her to come in: yea rather the fleſh is to be chaſtiſed with faſting, hardnes and with abſtinence from ſuch things as doe moſt pamper and pleaſe it, for her malapert pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption: for as the ſoule muſt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:12856:29"/>not debaſe herſelfe ſo farre as to open the doore of her ſanctified heart to her fleſhly hand-maide, that ſhe may enter in; ſo muſt not the handmaide be ſo preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous as to put in her hand by the hole of the dore as it were to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolte it, that ſhe may thruſt her ſelf in, for both it becommeth the handmaide to ſtay till her mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris call for her, and not to come into her cloſet or cabinet before ſhe be called, and to ſtay no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger there then her miſtris doth enioyne her to ſtay. In one word, the Soule muſt not riſe to let the fleſh in by aſſenting vnto any ſenſuall Tentation; &amp; if it chance that ſhe hath riſen by affe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting, yet muſt ſhe not put her hands to the drawing of the bar to let her in by a corporall acting of the euill whereunto ſhe hath aſſented:
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12856:30"/>for if ſhe doe, ſhe ſhall be ſure that her heart ſhall ſmart for it, yea her hands ſhall drop downe the ſharpe myrrhe of a mourne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full wringing, proceeding from a ſorrowfull heart, for putting of her fingers to the drawing of the barre, and to the opening of the doore; that is, for putting of her hands to the acting of the cuill, as is ſaid. But if that the ſoule chance to haue let in the ſenſuall ſuggeſtion of the fleſh both by aſſent and action, then in the next place muſt the chriſtian ſouldier endeauour, that at leaſt it goe not forth at the gates of the Citie of his ſoule by publicke or noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious perpetrtion. For a priuate or ſecret treſpaſſe weakneth the ſoule of the treſpaſſer; whereas a publicke &amp; open offence, doth both weaken the partie that com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitteth
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:12856:30"/>it, and wounde others that either ſee it, or heare tell of it. And therefore we muſt labour to ſmother ſinne in the ſhell of cogitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and delectation, before that it come to be borne or brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght forth by action; or if it hath already beene acted, we muſt keepe it captiue in the baſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of a penitent breaſt, till it be quite killed with contrition, &amp; ſlaine with the ſword of a godly ſorrow, and afterwards caſt out like a dead carkaſe by confeſſion.</p>
               <p>The fleſh, as ſhe will come ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times like an alluring deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Dalilah,</hi> to entice the Sampſon of the regenerate ſpirit to yeeld vnto her ſuggeſtions, ſo will ſhe come at other times like a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainfull <hi>Hagar,</hi> diſpightfully to vpbraide and flout the <hi>Sara</hi> of the chriſtian ſoule,<note place="margin">Gen. 16.4.5, 6.9.</note> for not giuing
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:12856:31"/>place vnto her pleaſant perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. <hi>Hagar</hi> deſpiſed and mocked her miſtris <hi>Sara</hi> for her barrennes, and the ſinfull fleſh will flout and vpbraide the reaſonable regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ſoule for her holineſſe, and her barrennes in ſenſual and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate delights. <hi>Sara</hi> being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſd of her handmayd <hi>Hagar,</hi> complained vnto her husband <hi>Abraham,</hi> the father of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, of her vndutifulnes: and the regenerate ſoule muſt complaine vnto her ſpouſe Chriſt Ieſus and vnto his miniſters her Paſtour and ſpiritual father, whome God hath appointed to heare the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual complaintes of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; who will enioyne the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſoule to deale roughly with his rebelling fleſh, as <hi>Sara</hi> did with her mocking handmaide <hi>Hagar,</hi> ay til ſhe humble her ſelfe vnder
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:12856:31"/>her Miſtris handes, as the Angel commanded <hi>Hagar</hi> to doe in <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras</hi> behalfe.</p>
               <p>Thus the ſoule will with hold from her fleſh <hi>Dauidlike</hi> the ſilke and the ſattin,<note place="margin">Pſal. 35.13 &amp; 69.10.11.</note> and couer her with ſackclothe; and alſo <hi>Daniel-like</hi> ſhe will depriue her fleſh of the vſe of dainty cheere, of the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant breade, of the nouriſhing fleſh,<note place="margin">Dani. 10.2.3.</note> and of the cheriſhing wine, till ſhe be beaten downe and brought into ſubiection, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> faith he did,<note place="margin">1. Cor 9.27. Gen. 21.14</note> in the behalfe of his own Body. And as <hi>Abraham</hi> gaue vnto <hi>Hagar Saras</hi> handmaid bread and water, and ſent her away; ſo the chriſtians ſpirituall father or paſtor to whome he doth adreſſe him ſelfe to find conſolation and comfort to his diſtreſſed and troubled conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for ſin, he wil enioyn him to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:12856:32"/>giue no other food to his diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fleſh, but bread &amp; water, till at what time ſhe haue humbled her ſelfe ſufficiently vnder her miſtris hands. And by this meanes, the chriſtian, according to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles exhortation, ſhall by litle and litle crucifie and kill the fleſh with the affections and the luſtes thereof;<note place="margin">Gala. 5.16 24.25</note> he ſhall learne dayly to walke in the ſpirit, and ſhall not walke any more after the fleſh, nor ſauour the things ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, nor yet fullfill the deſires thereof;<note place="margin">Rom. 8.1.5.13.17.</note> &amp; conſequently, he ſhall not come into condemnation. For there is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Ieſus (ſayth the Apoſtle) which walke not after the fleſh, but after the ſpirit: for as many as are led by the ſpirit of God, they are the Sons of God, and conſequently
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:12856:32"/>heires of God, and heires annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 3. Of the chriſtians figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againſt the world and <hi>the allurements of the ſame.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS the Chriſtian muſt fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the allurements of the fleſh, wich is our enemy within vs, ſo muſt hee likewiſe againſt the vanities of the world, which is our enemy without vs.<note place="margin">1. Iohn 2.15.16.17</note> 
                  <hi>Loue not the world</hi> ſaith bleſſed <hi>St. Iohn neither the thinges that are in the world. If any man loue the world, the loue of the father is not in him, for all that is in the world (as the luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eyes, and the pride of life) is not of the father, but is of the worlde, and the worlde paſſeth away,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:12856:33"/>and the luſt thereof, but he that fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the will of God, abideth for euer.</hi> As the luſt of the fleſh is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate deſire of the pleaſures of the fleſh, and of ſuch things as the fleſh doth naturally delight in, the branches whereof are, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſnes, luxurie, intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, lechery, drunkennes, glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony, exceſſe, and ſuperfluity, with ſuch other fleſhly debord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: So the luſt of the world is the inordinate and immoderat deſire of worldly things; as of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, which is couetouſnes; and of greatnes, which is ambition.</p>
               <p>The Chriſtian muſt ſtriue ſtoutly againſt the immoderate loue of the world,<note place="margin">Coll. 3.1.2</note> by <hi>ſetting his affection on things which are aboue, and not on thinges which are on the Earth</hi> as the Apoſtle doth exhort <hi>The world lyeth in wickednes,</hi> and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:12856:33"/>therefore it is the part onely of wicked perſons,<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 5.19</note> to ſet their harts on the world. The world is deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of the knowledge of God, and therfore as many as doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to knowe God,<note place="margin">Iohn 1.9.10. &amp; 17.25.</note> and to be knowne of him, muſt in a maner miſken the world. <hi>I pray not for the world</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour) and therfore if we wold be partakers of Chriſts interceſſion &amp; prayers, towards the father,<note place="margin">Iohn 17.9.</note> we muſt not be of the world, though we liue in the world. <hi>If ye were of the world</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour to his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants) <hi>the worlde would loue his owne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 7.7. &amp; 15.18.1. Ioh. 3.14</note> 
                  <hi>but becauſe ye are not of the world, but I haue choſen you out of the world, therfore the world hateth you.</hi> So that ſo many as are choſen of God out of the worlde, they are hated of the worlde, and they themſelues hate the world; ſo far
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:12856:34"/>are they from the loue of the world. And not onely doth the world hate Gods children, and all mortified Chriſtians, but it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen hateth God and Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.19</note> 
                  <hi>If the world hate you</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour) <hi>ye knowe that it hated me before you.</hi> And truly if the world doth hate not onely true and good Chriſtians, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Chriſt himſelf, what reaſon haue we to loue it? yea rather ought we not to hate it with a perfit hatred? and the Apoſtle af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming, that <hi>whoſoeuer will bee a friend of the world,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iame 4.4.</note> 
                  <hi>maketh himſelfe the enemy of God:</hi> he teacheth Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to renounce the amitie and friendſhip of the world, as they doe tender the amitie and friendſhip of God; for as <hi>the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the fleſh is enmity againſt God,</hi> ſo is the friendſhip and loue of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:12856:34"/>the world,<note place="margin">Luk 16.13</note> the enmity and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of God: and as we cannot ſerue God and Mammon, ſo we can not be both Gods friends &amp; the worldes; but if we be the worldes freinds, we muſt be Gods foes &amp; contrariwiſe: for as God cannot away with a diuided heart or with a deuided ſeruice, ſo can he not like of an halfed freindſhip. The whole heart is to him due; he hath made the whole heart, and he would ſaue the whole heart, and therefore he both deſerueth and deſireth to be ſerued and loued with the whole heart: &amp; conſequently the worlde muſt haue no ſhare in the heart, nor yet in the ſeruice: loue &amp; frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dſhip of the heart. As <hi>Eliah</hi> ſaid once vnto the ſuperſtitious and Idolatrous people, <hi>how long halt ye betweene two opinions?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. King. 18 22.</note> 
                  <hi>If the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:12856:35"/>Lord be God, follow him, but if Baal be he, then goe after him:</hi> ſo may the good Chriſtian ſay vnto all worldly minded men, how long will ye halt betweene two ſeruices, and two freendſhips? if the Lord be your maſter and onely true and conſtant freend, then ſerue and loue him alone with your whole heart, for he cannot away with halfes in this kinde. But if mammon be your maſter and the worlde your tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtieſt friend, then ſerue mammon and loue the world, for no man can ſerue or loue two maiſters ſayth our maiſter Chriſt Such wordlie chriſtians as will needes diuide the heart, the ſeruice, loue and friendſhip thereof, betweene God and mammon doe reſemble that vnnatural harlot mentioned in <hi>Salomons</hi> iudgement who
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:12856:35"/>would haue had the liuing childe to be diuided in twaine,<note place="margin">1. King 3.26.</note> where as the perfite chriſtian is like vnto the naturall mother, who choſe rather to looſe her childe ſo he might liue, then that he ſhould he diuided in twaine or into halfes and ſo die: or they are like the luke-warme Laodiceans to whom the ſpirit doth thus ſpeake,<note place="margin">Reue. 3.14.15.16.</note> 
                  <hi>I knowe thy wortkes that thou art neither cold nor hot; I would thou wereſt colde or hote, therefore becauſe thou art lukewarme, and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther colde nor hote, it will come to paſſe that I ſhall ſpewe thee out of my mouth.</hi> In one worde, as the double hearted chriſtian can not harbour in Gods kingdome, ſo the lukewarm louer of God, ſhal be ſpewed out of Gods mouth.</p>
               <p>It is good then for vs to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the vnfaithfull freendſhip of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:12856:36"/>the world, and to leane to the firme freendſhip of God, for we may be ſure that the worlde will in end, both faile vs, and forſake vs. She will perhaps fawne on vs for a time, and bring vs a preſent with <hi>Ehud,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudg. 3.15 16.17.18.19.20.21.22.</note> that is, aduance vs vnto ſome good degree of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or wealth, but after that ſhe hat ſpied out a fit opportunity, ſo that ſhe may finde vs <hi>Eglon-like</hi> ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting alone, as it were in the ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer parlor of proſpertie, ſhe will be ſure to ſhewe her ſelfe ſuch a one as doth not a whit care for our kindnes: no, ſhe will not faile to doe her beſt to thruſt into our belly, or rather into our boſome, the two edged dagger of aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty &amp; anguiſhe, and ſo turne all our former plentie into pouerty, and felicity and excellency, into deie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and miſerie.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:12856:36"/>The worlde will ſay vnto the chriſtian, as <hi>Iaell</hi> ſaid once to <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſera, Turne in my Lord, turne in to me &amp; feare not:</hi> yea more,<note place="margin">Iudg, 4.18 19.20.21.</note> ſhe will not onely inuite him louingly to her houſe, but ſhe will likewiſe giue him to drink the ſweete milk of earthly pleaſures, and ſhe will promiſe him mony and wealth, which is ſweeter then milk, and couer him with the mantle of wordly might, but cre all be done, ſhe will make him by deere inough bothe her milke and her mantell, bothe her blanket and her bed. For ſhe ſhall not faile, <hi>Iael</hi>-like to take the prinne of pride and beate it into his head, or rather into his heart, whervpon preſently he ſhall fall.<note place="margin">Iob. 21.7. to 17.</note> For as the proſperity of the wicked maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proud (as the holy man <hi>Iob</hi> doth teache) ſo
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:12856:37"/>
                  <hi>pride goeth before deſtruction,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Proue. 16.18. &amp; 18.12. Iames 4.6.1. Pet. 5.5.</note> 
                  <hi>and an high mind before the fall,</hi> ſayth wiſe <hi>Salomon.</hi> And as God lifteth vp the humble and mccke, ſo he reſiſteth the proude and caſteth them vpon their backe.<note place="margin">Proue. 5.1.2.3.4.5.</note> The lips of the worlde like vnto <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> ſtrange woman, drop as an hony combe, and her mouth is more ſoft then oyle, flowing with ſmooth and ſweete allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: But the end of her is bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as wormwod, and ſharp as a two edged ſword, her feete goe downe to death, and her ſteps take holde on hell.</p>
               <p>When ſo euer then the world ſhall chance to tempt the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to loue her, as <hi>Potiphars</hi> wife did allure faire <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to lie with her;<note place="margin">G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n. 39.7.8.9.10.20.21.</note> the chriſtian muſt labour by all meanes to proue a <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede; that is, a perfite one: for
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:12856:37"/>
                  <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſignifieth perfite:) and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he muſt anſwer the world re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſingly as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> did <hi>Potiphars</hi> wife, and ſay, far be it from me to make ſuch a miſerable exchange, as to looſe the loue and freend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God for thine: no, world, though thou wouldſt giue thy ſelf wholy to me alone, yet will I not forgoe the loue of my God for all thy glory, though it were euen a thowſand folde greater then it is, and millions of times of longer laſting then it is. And though that the world will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps frowne on thee fearefully, for thy refuſall with <hi>Poliphars</hi> wife, and though ſhe goe about to diffame thee &amp; blame thee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſeruedly, and euen ſhut thee vp with <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in the priſon of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, and neceſſity: yet muſt the good Chriſtian endeauoure to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:12856:38"/>ſhewe him ſelfite in ſuffering pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently all kinde of affliction temporall, for that felicities ſake which is eternall as he that muſt count with the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.18.</note> 
                  <hi>that the afflictions of this preſent time are not worthy of the glorie which ſhalbe ſhewed vnto vs.</hi> And he that was with <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in the priſon, and made him to proſper, will like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be with the good Chriſtian that aymeth at perfection, in his penurie and pouertie, and in the mean time that his outward man is brought low, &amp; as it were bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with aduerſity, his inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhall growe and floriſh like a greene palme tree, and enioy all manner of inward comfort and ſpirituall proſperity. And he that brought <hi>Ioſeph</hi> out of priſon, and gaue him great glory,<note place="margin">Gen 41.40 41.42.43.</note> chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging his fetters of iron into gold
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:12856:38"/>chaynes,<note place="margin">Psalm 10.17.18.19.20.21.22</note> his poore priſon into a Princely palace, and making him of a diſpiſed priſoner, a potent prince, he will likewiſe in his owne time crowne the patient ſufferer of aduerſity, with the royall Diademe of might and of maieſty.</p>
               <p>The world <hi>Haman</hi>-like will ſeeke to be auenged on all ſuch Chriſtian <hi>Mordecaies</hi> as will not adore him &amp; do him reuerence:<note place="margin">Eſter 3.2.3 4.5.6. &amp; 6.3.10. &amp; 7.10.</note> but if the Chriſtian continue conſtantly in fighting againſt ſuch baſe idolatrie, the worlde <hi>Haman</hi>-like ſhall hang, and the Chriſtian wraſtler with <hi>Mordecai</hi> ſhall come to honour. In one word, ſo many as are borne of God, it ſtandeth them in hand to wraſtle againſt the world vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly, yea to conquer and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come it victoriouſly: I mean not
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:12856:39"/>
                  <hi>Coeſar</hi>-like, by ſubiugation or poſſeſſion, but <hi>Chriſt</hi>-like, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcation: <hi>for all that is borne of God</hi> (ſaith bleſſed St. <hi>Iohn</hi>) <hi>ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth the world,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.4.</note> 
                  <hi>and this is the victory that ouercommeth the world, euen our faith.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 4. Of the chriſtians figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againſt the Deuill, and <hi>his ſubtill perſwaſions, and violent invaſions.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe third enemy that the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian hath to encou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, is the ſtrongeſt and feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulleſt of all the three; for the two former, the <hi>world</hi> and the <hi>fleſh,</hi> are but the <hi>olde Lyons</hi> arm our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearers: the world as his chiefe page, and the fleſh as his hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:12856:39"/>This enemy commeth ſometimes like a Lyon to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure vs,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.8. Rcue 12 3 12.13.14.15.16.17.2. Cort. 11.14.</note> and ſometimes like a <hi>Serpent</hi> to circumvent vs, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times as a blacke <hi>Belial</hi> to peruert vs, and ſometimes as a lightſome Lucifer to beguile vs. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he will carry himſelfe as our greateſt friend, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times as our profeſſed foe. Wee knowe full well how he played his Serpents part in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of our Grandmother <hi>Eue:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 3.1.2.3.4.5.6.</note> he would needs ſhew himſelfe as one that did tender the perfit e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of our firſt parents; his wiſh forthem was, that they were as wiſe as God in knowing both good and euill. And therefore he told them that they ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as wiſe as God by the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of an apple. And yet in the meane time his intent was to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:12856:40"/>haue them made like, not vnto God in perfection, but vnto the Deuill in defection.</p>
               <p>Whenſoeuer then the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is tempted by Sathan the old Serpent, to eat the forbidden fruit of any vnlawfull action, to the end that he may become as it were a little God amongſt men, for worldly knowledge, for wealth, for honour, credit, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, hee muſt dilligently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware leaſt he liſten vnto the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents aduiſe, and let him aſſure himſelfe that the forbidden ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of diſobedience ſhall bee as bitter to the taſte of his ſoule, as it was to <hi>Adams</hi> and <hi>Eues.</hi> And when as he ſhall thinke to be like vnto God by eating of the forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den apple, he ſhall proue but a meere man, yea a naked and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable man, and he ſhall bee ſo
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:12856:40"/>vnlike vnto God, that he dare not be ſo bold as to abide the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, yea he ſhall bee faine with old father <hi>Adam,</hi> to fly from the face of God, if hee wiſt well where. And in that day that God ſhall make an enquiry touching ſuch mens diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the fig-leauie breeches of their light &amp; ſlight excuſes, ſhall not be able to hide their nakednes, or to couer their vncleanes from Gods cleere-ſeeing, ye all-ſeeing eyes. Let them flee whereſoeuer they wil, God ſhal find them out,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.8. Iſay 2.19. Hoſ. 10.8. Luke 23.30 K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ue. 15.16</note> &amp; though they ſhould hide the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the thickeſt trees of the obſcureſt woods, yea amidſt the deepeſt dennes of the earth, or amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the ragged rocks of the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taines, yet they ſhall not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape (for except they repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend before that day) they ſhall
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:12856:41"/>finde no denne or hole to hide them in at that day, till they bee thrown headlong into hel: euen hell ſhall be their hole to hide them in, and the Deuils dungeon ſhall be their denne.</p>
               <p>Sathan commeth ſometimes as one that knocketh at our dore, and ſo metimes as one that wold break open our dores, to get in v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs againſt our wil. He knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the dore of <hi>Euahs</hi> hart, to get in by flattery &amp; fraudulence, but he laboured to break vp the dore of <hi>Iobs</hi> hart by forceand violence:<note place="margin">Iob. 1.7.8.9.10.11.12. &amp; 2.4.5.6.7.8.9.</note> for his drift was to make him di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire of Gods fauour, and euen to make him ſo to raile againſt God, to blaſpheme him and dye.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Goliah</hi> the fearefull Philiſtim,<note place="margin">Sam. 17.4.8.10.36.</note> the Giant of Gath, railed vpon the people of God, and reuiled them in moſt outragious maner:
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:12856:41"/>And ſo will the great Captaine of ſpirituall captiuity, I meane the <hi>Deuill,</hi> (for <hi>Goliah</hi> ſignifieth captiuity) he wilſometimes raile vpon the Chriſtian, and reuile him, by laying open vnto the eies of his touched conſcience, his owne vileneſſe and vglines, to the and that he may driue him into deſpare.</p>
               <p>But the Chriſtian ſouldier muſt not be quelled or caſt downe in his courage, though he be both weake and young, and his aduerſarie both olde and ſtrong. <hi>Dauid</hi> was but a young boy and in naturall ſtrength farre inferiour to <hi>Goliah,</hi> for he was not able to goe in <hi>Sauls</hi> armour, though it were not ſo heauy as was <hi>Goliahs</hi> ſpeares head: and yet beng inwardly fortified by faith in God, he went out againſt him
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:12856:42"/>with his ſtaffe in his hand, and his ſling together with fiue ſmall ſtones in his ſkrippe, and ſaid vnto the vncircumciſed chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenger thus;<note place="margin">1. Sam. 17 40.45.49 50.</note> 
                  <hi>Thow commeſt to me with a ſworde and a ſpeare, and with a ſheild, but I come to thee in the name of the Lord of hoſtes, the God of the hoſt of Iſrael whom thou haſt rayled vpon.</hi> And in the like maner the Chriſtian muſt goe out againſt the ſpirituall <hi>Goliah</hi> in the name of <hi>Ieſus</hi> the ſonne of God, and the Lord of heauen and earth, being ſpiritually armed with the ſtaffe of his croſſe, the ſling of faith, and with a feruent meditation vpon our Sauiours ſuffering, and his fiue bloodie wounds, anſwering vnto <hi>Dauids</hi> fiue flintie ſtones, the which he muſt alwayes carrie about him in the skrippe of a cleanſed conſcience, and of a
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:12856:42"/>deuoute and dutifull remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance. <hi>Dauid</hi> ouercame the fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Philiſtim</hi> with his ſling and with a ſtone, wherewith he ſmote him mortally in the forehead, ſo that he fell preſently groue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to the ground: And the Chriſtian ſhall ouercome the ſpirituall <hi>Philiſtim</hi> with the ſling of an effectuall faith, which lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth holde vpon our ſauiour <hi>Chriſt,</hi> whom <hi>Iacob</hi> calleth <hi>the ſtone of Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 49.24 Dan. 2.34.35.</note> and <hi>Dantel the ſtone hewed out of the mountaine without hands:</hi> for he was formed in his holy mothers wombe of <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſanctified ſeede without hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine helpe,<note place="margin">Luke 1.26 to 35.</note> and cut out of this holy mountaine, dignified to be the ſpouſe and mother of God without mans hand, by the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfull working and ouerſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowing of the holy ghoſt, he euen
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:12856:43"/>tooke vpon him our nature in the virginall wombe of his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted and pure mother, to the end,<note place="margin">Heb. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.14.15.16.17 18.</note> 
                  <hi>that he might deſtroy through death him that had the power of death, that is the deuill; and that he might deliuer all them which for feare of death were all their lifetime ſubiect to bondage: for in that he ſuffered and was tempted, he is able to ſuccour them that are tempted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus then if our great aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary the Deuill, endeauoure to ſteale in vpon vs like a theefe, or to ſlide and ſlip into our boſome like a ſerpent, or if he knocke at our dore like a friend, then muſt we vſe great circumſpection, leaſt we be gulled: for in that caſe he will not faile to diſguiſe himſelf, in the likenes of an Angell of light,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.13.4.</note> and to borrow the ſugred lips &amp; ſweet tongue of the bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grome,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:12856:43"/>and euen ſpeake as allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly and ſweetly vnto the ſoule which he would ſlaye, as the bride-groome doth in the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles to his ſpouſe, or to the ſoule which he would ſaue:<note place="margin">Cant. 5.2.3</note> 
                  <hi>Open vnto me my Siſter, my loue, my doue, my vndefiled, for mine head is full of dew, and my lockes with the drops of the night.</hi> But the Chriſtian ſoule muſt beware of ryſing to let him in, &amp; muſt rather repell him with ſuch an anſwer as this; no ſubtill Sathan, thou ſhalt not come in,<note place="margin">Reuel. 3.7.</note> for <hi>he that is holy &amp; true, which hath the key of Dauid, which openeth and no man ſhutteth, and ſhutteth and no man openneth,</hi> euen he hath both opened and ſhut the dore of myne heart; it is now ſhut and thou canſt not come in, and my brother, my loue, and my ſpouſe is already lodged in the houſe of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:12856:44"/>myne heart, and is now lying in the bed of my breaſt, euen in his Brides boſome, and thou ſhalt not come in. Thou calleſt mee thy ſiſter, when as thou wouldſt make mee thy ſlaue; thy loue, when as thou wouldſt make mee forlorne; thy doue, when as thou wouldſt make me thy rauen, or thy dog; thy vndefiled, when as thou wouldſt defloure me, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file me; in one word, thou woldſt haue me to take thee for my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and my bridegrome, when as thou wouldeſt indeede be my burriour: thou wouldſt make me beleeue that thine head is full of dewe to refreſh mee, when as it is indeed ful of duſt &amp; of dirt to defile me, yea full of fire &amp; brimſtone to burne me, if thou ſhouldſt once get into my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome. Get thee gone ſubtill Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:12856:44"/>thou curſed night-crowe, that takeſt pleaſure thus to flie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in the night, and dareſt not be ſo bold in the day, for a darke time is fitteſt for the Prince of darknes, to be a ſtirring, and to be ſet on the entycing of ſimple ſoules, to the doing of the works of darkenes. I knowe well thy compaſſing &amp; thy paines taking out of what fountaine it dooth flowe; auoid therfore, for mine heart-dore is ſhut, and thou canſt not get in, and my ſoules ſweete heart is already lodged in mine heart and thou ſhalt not get in.</p>
               <p>But if our aduerſarie like a Lion ſeeke to breake open the doore of our heart, and in a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent manner, endeauoure to driue vs into deſpaire by reaſon of our grat wretchednes, wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:12856:45"/>and vnworthines, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he will not faile to hit vs in the teeth, to the end that we may diſtruſt of Gods mercie in our ſoules behalfe; then muſt the Chriſtian if euer at any time ells, ſtand out ſtoutly againſt him in the faith of Chriſt, and laying aſide <hi>Sauls</hi> armour, I meane, all opinion and conceit of his owne worthines, towardnes, and ſtrength, let him fling onely againſt <hi>Goliahs</hi> forehead the flin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſtone of Chriſts death, out of the ſling of an effectuall faith working by loue;<note place="margin">Gall. 5.6.</note> and no doubt, but the <hi>Philiſtim</hi> ſhall fall, and with <hi>Dauid</hi> hee ſhal winne the fielde: for the Chriſtian (to ſpeake with the Apoſtle) is able to doe all things through the helpe of Chriſt which ſtrengtheneth him.<note place="margin">Philli. 4.13</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:12856:45"/>So then when Sathan com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in his railing humour to reuile the Chriſtian for his vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and vnworthines, for his wretchednes and wickednes, for the finnes of his youth, or of his olde yeeres, for the multitude of his vnfanctified thoughts, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe and prophane ſpeeches, and vnlawfull actions, for his faults both of knowledge and of ignorance, both of omiſſion and commiſſion; and when as the Chriſtian ſhall ſee that they doe exceede the haire of his head for nomber and quantity, and the ſand of the ſea for greatnes and grauitie, yet for all this let him not be diſmayed or diſpairingly caſten downe; but let him confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently reply and ſay to Sathan in this manner; it is true, Sathan, that I am full of ſinne, and my
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:12856:46"/>tranſgreſſions, I grant, are both many and mighty; but Gods mercies are more. <hi>The Lord is full of compaſſion and mercy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 103.8 9.10.11.12.13.</note> 
                  <hi>ſlowe to anger, and of great kindes, he will not deale with me after my ſinnes, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde me according to mine iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. For as high as the heauen is aboue the earthe, ſo great is his mercie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them that feare him. As farre as the eaſt is from the weſt; ſo farre hath he remoued our ſinnes from vs. As a father hath compaſſion on his children, ſo hath the Lord compaſſion on then that feare him.</hi> I know Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, that I am a ſinner and an vgly one too, and thereof may I iuſtly blame thee; but I knowe likewiſe that Chriſt <hi>came not to call the righteous but the ſinners to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 9.13.</note> for ſo he ſayth him ſelfe. If there had not bene ſuch ſinful creatures as I am, Chriſt needed
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:12856:46"/>neuer to haue come into the worlde; <hi>For this is a true ſaying and by all meanes worthy to be embraced,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.15</note> 
                  <hi>that Chriſt Ieſus came into the worlde to ſaue ſinners, of whom I am the chiefe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if Sathan goe not ſo farre, but onely take occaſion of a mans afflicted or indigent eſtate to tempt him (as he did our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour) to diſtruſt of Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,<note place="margin">Mat. 4.2.2.3.</note> and to make as it were, bread of ſtones, that is, to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe wordly wealth by vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meanes; then let him repell the Tempter with ſome ſuch anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were as this; if our heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feedeth the fowles of the heauen, and cloatheth the lillies of the fielde,<note place="margin">Mat. 26 27 28.29.30</note> how much more will he feede and cloathe me whome am much dearer vnto him then they? And therfore how
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:12856:47"/>ſoeuer it be true, that I want di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers neceſſary or deſirable things, yet will I alwayes waite on God patiently,<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.3.4.7.25.34</note> and aſſure my ſelfe confidently that I ſhall not be forſaken for euer: no, <hi>though my father and my mother ſhould for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake mee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 27.10.</note> 
                  <hi>yet the Lord will gather me vp:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob. 13.15.</note> and <hi>though he ſhould euen ſlay me</hi> (let alone to pinch me in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſon of neceſſarie things) <hi>yet will I truſt in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe,<note place="margin">Math. 4.5.</note> if the Tempter goe about to ſet a man on the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of preſumption, by indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing or alluring him to preſume vpon Gods fauour and mercy in his behalfe, to the end that he may the more eafily win him to the working of any wickednes: then muſt he ſay vnto Sathan in this manner, farre be it fro me to make a baude of Gods mercy, to
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:12856:47"/>my miſerable nature, or to abuſe the riches of his grace to the committing of any grieuous treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe. And with all, let him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe his humble &amp; hearty peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vnto the Lord in this or the like forme; <hi>keepe thy ſeruant from preſumptuous ſinnes;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 19.13</note> 
                  <hi>let them not reigne ouer mee: ſo ſhall I be vpright and be made cleane from much wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes.</hi> Becauſe thy ſinne is forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen be not without feare (ſayth <hi>Siracides</hi>) to heape ſinne vpon ſinne. And ſay not,<note place="margin">Eccl. 5.5.6.</note> the mercy of God is great: he will forgiue my manifold ſinnes: for mercy and wrath come from him and his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation cometh downe vpon ſinners.</p>
               <p>But if the Tempter goe yet further, and entiſe a man to adore him, and to that effect promiſe to carry him vp into the high
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:12856:48"/>mountaine of wordly might, and to giue him his hearts deſire, euen abundance of treaſure, and of earthly honour, to giue him perhaps a kingdome, or els the ſmiling countenance of a king: then muſt the Chriſtian reſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay, <hi>auoide Sathan,</hi> for I will not worſhip thee for all the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the earth.<note place="margin">Mat. 16.26</note> 
                  <hi>For what ſhall it profite a man though he ſhould winne the whole worde, if he looſe his owne ſoule?</hi> or what ſhall a man giue for recompence of his ſoule what ſhall it profite a man to poſſeſſe all the kingdomes of the earth, if he be in the meane time depriued of the kingdome of heauen? finally what ſhall it auaile him to enioye the fauora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble contenance of an earthly king, if he be ſecluded from the fauour and contenance of the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:12856:48"/>immortall king,<note place="margin">Pſal. 6.11</note> in whoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is the fulneſſe of ioy, and at whoſe right hand there are pleaſures for euermore? To what ſinne then ſoeuer it be that <hi>Sathan</hi> tempteth the Chriſtian vnto, let him take heed neuer to yeelde, but to ſtriue ſtoutly,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.4. 1. Cot. 16.13. Ephe. 4.27.</note> and to wraſtle valiantly againſt the wicked one. <hi>Watch ye, ſtand faſt in the faith quite yow like men, and be ſtrong, neither giue place to the Deuil,</hi> ſayth <hi>S. Paul.</hi> Neither muſt the chriſtian be any whit deſmayd, when as he is tempted:<note place="margin">Mat. 4.1. Heb 2.18. Ma. 10.24.</note> for Chriſt our Captaine hath beene tempted aſwell as wee: And we knowe that the ſeruant is not aboue his maiſter, and that the Captaine is alwayes aboue his ſouldier. The Temptation of the Captaine doth not exempt the ſouldier, but rather aſſure him
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:12856:49"/>that in his Temtation he ſhal not be ouercome, but ſhall conquer and ouercome, euen as his Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ouercame.<note place="margin">Reue. 3.21</note> 
                  <hi>To him that ouercometh</hi> (ſayth the great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour Chriſt) <hi>will I grant to ſit with me in my throne, euen as Iouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came, and ſit with my father in his throne.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 5. Of the firſt piece of the Chriſtians ſpirituall armour, which is the girdle of verity, <hi>and of the meaning and vſe thereof.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ANd as <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Captaine hath caled vs to fight, ſo hath he furniſhed vs with armour, wherethrough we may aduanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geouſly fight: and as our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:12856:49"/>are ſpiritual and not carnal,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.11 12.13.14.15.16.17.</note> 
                  <hi>for we wreſtle not againſt fleſh and blood, but againſt Principailties and powers, and ſpirituall wickednes:</hi> So is our armour ſpirituall and not carnall. <hi>The weapons of our warre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 10.3.4.</note>) <hi>are not carnall but mighty through God, to cast downe holds, caſting downe the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginations and euery high thing that is exalted againſt the knowledge of God, and bringing into captiuity e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery thought, to the obedience of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is the armour of God, and not of man, though it be forged by the finger of Gods ſpirit for the vſe of man. The ſeuerall parts &amp; pieces of which armour being ſeauen in number, the holy Apoſtle doth thus ſet down 1. <hi>The Girdle of Veritie,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>ſtand therefore, and your
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:12856:50"/>loynes gird about with verity.</hi> 2. <hi>The breſtplate of righteuſnes</hi> in theſe, <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing on the breſt plate of righteouſnes:</hi> 3. <hi>The ſhooes of peace</hi> in theſe, <hi>and your feete ſhod with the preparation of the Goſpell of peace.</hi> 4. The <hi>ſhield of faith</hi> in theſe, <hi>aboue all take the ſhield of faith, wherewith ye may quench all the fiery dartes of the wcked.</hi> 5. The <hi>helmet of hope</hi> in theſe <hi>take the helmet of ſaluation.</hi> 6. The <hi>ſword of Gods word</hi> in theſe, <hi>take the ſword of the ſpirit which is the word of God.</hi> 7. And laſtly, the <hi>bowe and arrow of faſting and prayer,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>and pray alwaies with all maner prayer and ſupplication in the ſpirit, and watch therunto with al perſeuerance.</hi> Where in watching is alſo included faſting, becauſe a man is then moſt apt to watch, when as he faſteth.</p>
               <p>The Chriſtian muſt haue the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:12856:50"/>loynes of his ſoule gyrt about with verity, which is no other thing but ſinglines of heart, vprightnes, and ſincerity,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.12 Pſal. 78.72</note> being free from all diſſimulation and hipocriſie.<note place="margin">Ioſh. 24.14 1. Sam. 12 24 1. King. 2.4 5. Pſal. 51.6.</note> And therefore we reade how that <hi>Ioſhua</hi> and <hi>Samuel</hi> did exhorte the people to ſerue the Lord in vprightnes and truth with all their hearts; for God lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth truth in the inward affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſaith the Pſalmiſt: &amp; as he is a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, &amp; the eſſential truth, ſo muſt he be worſhipped in ſpirit &amp; in truth,<note place="margin">Iohn 4.24.</note> as the truth him ſelfe doth affirme. He muſt be worſhipped in ſubſtance and in deed, and not only in word or in ſhew which is helliſh hipocriſie, &amp; moſt dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable iniquity.<note place="margin">M t. 54.21</note> And therfore by our Sauiour, hel is called the por<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hypocrites, that is to ſay, of al ſuch as haue a ſhew of godlines
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:12856:51"/>but haue denyed the power ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.5</note> as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh. Wee muſt worſhip God not onely in word but alſo in worke, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the ſpeeches of our lips, but alſo in the actions of out liues, and not onely in our heads and intentions, but alſo in our hearts and affections: and yet more, not onely in the reſolutions of our hearts, but likewiſe in the executions of our hands,<note place="margin">Iam. 1.22.</note> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Be ye doers of the word, and not hearers onely, deceauing your owne ſelnes.</hi> God will not be content with the eare onely, nor with the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the eare, neither yet with the lips &amp; the religious talking of the tongue; no, the whole head,<note place="margin">Iame 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.22.</note> and the cogitations and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions thereof will not ſuffice; it is the heart or els nothing at al
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:12856:51"/>
                  <hi>Becauſe this people</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>come neere vnto me with their mouth and honour me with their lippes, but haue remoued their heart farre from me, and their feare toward me, was taught by the precept of men; therfore behold, I will againe doe a meruailous worke and a wonder,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſay. 29.13 14</note> 
                  <hi>for the wiſdome of their wiſe men ſhall periſh, and the vnderſtanding of their prudent men ſhall be hid.</hi> God is a Spirit and therefore he requireth chiefely the ſpirit, and the heart, for it is the chiefe part and the beſt part: <hi>My ſonne</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>giue me thine heart:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 23.26</note> he muſt haue the whole heart, &amp; not an halfe of it, for an halfed heart, or a diuided heart, is a double heart, and God can not away with it or with any kinde of diuiſion.<note place="margin">Pro. 23.26</note> 
                  <hi>Woe vnto them that haue a double heart,</hi> [ſaith <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racides] and to the wicked lipps, and
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:12856:52"/>to the faint hands, and to the ſinner that goeth two manner of waies. An heart that goeth two wayes ſhall not proſper, and he that is froward in heart, ſhall ſtumble therein.</hi> The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided heart is an vncircumciſed heart, &amp; God cannot harbour in ſuch a hart as is ſubiect to vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion &amp; diuiſion: &amp; therfore <hi>the Lord</hi> (ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi> to the people <hi>will circumciſe thine hart &amp; the hart of thy ſeede,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 30.6</note> 
                  <hi>that thou mayeſt loue the Lord thy God with all thine heart, and with all thy ſoule, that thou maiſt liue.</hi> whereby is ſignified vnto vs, that except the heart be circumciſed by the ſanctification and renoua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſpirit, that it can not be wholy and vndeuidedly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted vnto God,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.13</note> as it ſhould be. One man cannot ſerue two ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and one heart muſt not be parted betweene two ſuters, to
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:12856:52"/>wit, the world &amp; God. God hath made the whole hart &amp; therfore ſhould haue the whole heart; it is he that ſanctifieth and ſaueth the whole heart,<note place="margin">Deut. 1.13. &amp; 10.12. &amp; 11.1. 1. King. 2.4 5. Luk 10.27 Math. 6.21</note> &amp; therefore good reaſon that he be ſerued with the whole heart. The Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is aboue &amp; not belowe, and therfore his heart muſt be aboue &amp; not below, in heauen, &amp; not in earth; with God, &amp; not with man; in whole, &amp; not in halfe: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as the Apoſtle exhorteth me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to loue one another not in word or in tonge only,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.18 19.20</note> but in deed &amp; in truth, for thereby (ſaith he) wee know that we are of the truth; ſo muſt the chriſtian labour dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to worſhip God, loue &amp; feare him, not in tongue only, but alſo in truth, and as I ſaid before, not onely in worde, but likewiſe in worke, and not onely with the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:12856:53"/>heart,<note place="margin">Iſay 51.5.6 7.8.9.10.11.12.13.</note> but alſo with the hand. <hi>Is it ſuch a faſt that I haue choſen (ſayth the Lord) that a man ſhould afflict his ſoule for a day, and to bow downe his head, as a bull-ruſh and to lie downe in ſackloth and aſhes? wilt thou call this a faſting or an acceptable day vnto the Lord? Is not this the faſting that I haue choſen, to looſe the bands of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, to take off the heauie burdens, and to let the oppreſſed goe free, and that ye breake euery yoke? Is it not to deale thy bread vnto the hungrie, and that thou bring the poore that wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, vnto thine houſe? when thou ſeeſt the naked, that thou couer him, and hide not thy ſelfe from thine own fleſh? If thou take away from the middes of thee the yoke, the putting forth of the finger, and wicked ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, if thou powre out thy ſoule to the hungrie, and refreſh the troubled ſoule, then ſhall thy light ſpring out
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:12856:53"/>in the darknes, and thy darkenes ſhall be as the noone day. And the Lord ſhal guide thee continually, and ſatisfie thy ſoule in drought, and make fat thy bones, and thou ſhalt be like a watered garden, and like a ſpring of water, whoſe waters fayle not. If thou turne away thy foote from the Sabbath, from doing thy will on mine holy day, and cal the Sabbath a delight, to conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate it, as glorious to the Lorde, and ſhalt honour him, not doing thine owne wayes, nor ſeeking thine owne will, nor ſpeaking a vaine word, then ſhalt thou delight in the Lord, and I will cauſe thee to mount vpon the hie places of the earth, and feede thee with the heritage of Iacob thy father, for the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it.</hi> Out of which notable place of the Euangelicall Prophet, we are cleerly taught what it is to be a worſhipper of God in ſpirit
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:12856:54"/>and in faith, and what it is to be truly religious, and how that the ſoule and ſubſtance of religion conſiſteth in action.<note place="margin">Iam. 1.27.</note> To which purpoſe the Apoſtle <hi>S. Iames tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth that pure religion, and vndefiled before God euen the father, is this, to viſite the fatherles and widowes in their aduerſity, and to keepe him ſelfe vnſpotted of the worlde.</hi> And <hi>Siraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> doth likewiſe teach plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the feare and true worſhip of God, doth conſiſt not in an orall profeſſion, but in a reall execution of the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of the Lord.<note place="margin">Ecclu. 2.16 17.18.19.</note> 
                  <hi>They that feare the Lord (ſayth he) will not diſobey his word; and they that loue him will keepe his wayes. They that feare the Lord will ſeeke out the things that are pleaſant vnto him, and they that loue him ſhall be fulfilled with his law. They that feare the Lord
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:12856:54"/>will prepare their hearts, and humble their ſoules in his ſight: they that feare the Lord, keepe his commandements, and will be patient till he ſee them.</hi> Finally,<note place="margin">Pſal. 78.72</note> as <hi>Dauid</hi> fed the Iſraelites according to the ſimplicity of his heart;<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.12</note> and as <hi>S. Paul</hi> walked in the ſimplicity of his heart, and as <hi>Ezekiah</hi> walked before the Lord in truth and with a perfite heart;<note place="margin">2. King. 20 3.</note> ſo muſt the Chriſtian worſhip, honour, loue and feare God, in ſynceritie and ſimplicity of heart; and likewiſe loue his neighbour feruently and without faining, with a pure,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.22</note> ſincere and entire hart. And thus much is imported by the girding of the loynes with the girdle of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, or of truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:12856:55"/>
               <head>CAP. 6. Of the Breaſt-plate of Righteouſnes.</head>
               <p>ANd as the Chriſtian muſt haue his loynes girde with verity, ſincerity and ſimplicity, ſo muſt he beare on his breaſt, or rather in his breſt, the Breſt-plate of Righteouſnes, equity and charity. That is to ſay, the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> muſt be made his, not onely by gratious imputation, whereby he is of God accounted righteous in Chriſt and for Chriſt, but alſo by ſpirituall participation &amp; actuall imitation, whereby he is really made to be that which he is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted. For as the father for the Sonnes ſake doth pronounce and account the Chriſtian righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:12856:55"/>(as the holy Apoſtle doth in diuers places deliuer) and that by the meanes of his faith in Chriſt, which doth lay holde on his all ſufficient righteouſnes:<note place="margin">Rom. 3.22 24.25.26. &amp; 4.3.22.23 24. 1. Cor. 1.30 Gala. 2.16. Phillip. 3.4.</note> ſo the holy ghoſt doth worke righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes in our hearts, by the waſhing and renuing of the new birth according to the ſame Apoſtle.<note place="margin">Tit. 3.5.6 7 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Not by the workes of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>which we had done</hi> (to wit before the time of grace) <hi>but according to his mercy he ſaued vs, by the waſhing of the new birth, and the renewing of the holy Ghoſt, which he ſhedde on vs abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly through Ieſus Chriſt our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, that we being iuſtified (or made righteous) by his grace, ſhould be made heires according to the hope of eternall life. This is a true ſaying, and theſe things I would thou ſhouldſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that they which haue beleeued
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:12856:56"/>in God, might be carefull to ſhewe forth good workes: theſe things are good and profitable vnto men.</hi> By the which cleere teſtimonie, it is more then apparant, that beſides Chriſts imputed righteouſnes, there is alſo an infuſed or impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted righteouſnes ſhed abroad in our hearts, by the working of Gods renewing ſpirit; the which infuſed or inherent righteouſnes doth ſhewe it ſelfe forth in good workes,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.12 16.17.18</note> flowing there-fro. And therefore the ſame Apoſtle doth exhorte men to giue their mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers as weapous of righteouſnes vnto God, and that they ſhould make them ſelues the ſeruants of righteuſnes by actual obedience: for as many as are made free from ſinne (ſayth he) are made the ſeruants of righteouſnes, euen the workers and doers of
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:12856:56"/>righteous actions.<note place="margin">1. Joh. 2.29 &amp; 3.7.24.</note> 
                  <hi>For he that doth righteouſnes</hi> (ſayth bleſſed <hi>S. John) is righteous as he</hi> (to wit Chriſt) <hi>is righteous, &amp; he that doth righteouſly is borne of him, yea he that keepeth his commandements dwelleth in him, and he in him.</hi> And it is of this inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and actual righteouſnes that the Prophet. <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſpeaketh at large in the 18. chapter of his propheſy.<note place="margin">Ezek. 18.5 6.7.8.9.15 16.17.</note> 
                  <hi>But if a man be iuſt</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>and do that which is lawfull and right, and hath not eaten vpon the mountaines, neither hath lift vp his eyes to the Idols of the houſe of Iſrael, neither hath defiled his neighbours wife, neither hath lyen with a men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruous woman, neither hath opreſſed any, nor hath witholden the pledge, neither hath ſpoiled by violence, but hath giuen his bread to the hungrie, and hath couered the naked with a garment, neither hath withdrawen
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:12856:57"/>his hand from the afflicted, and hath not giuen forth vpon vſury, neither hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any increaſe, but hath with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawne his hand from iniquity, and hath executed true iudgement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene man and man, and hath wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in my ſtatutes, and hath kept my iudgements, to deale truly, he is iuſt, he ſhall ſurely liue ſaith the Lord God.</hi> Out of which place it is more then manifeſt, that the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes or iuſtice by which a mans ſoule liueth, muſt be inherent in the heart, and likewiſe muſt bee acted by the hand: as alſo that perfite righteouſnes, ſuch as God dooth require at mans hands, is not onely to giue euery man what is his, by ſtrict debt, which is <hi>equitie,</hi> but alſo to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part vnto the needy, a part of his owne goods, which is <hi>charitie.</hi> Likewiſe in the booke of <hi>Sarachs</hi>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:12856:57"/>wiſedome, theſe two, <hi>equity,</hi> and <hi>charity</hi> are deſcribed, as the parts of one, and the ſame inherent &amp; actuall righteouſnes.<note place="margin">Eccle. 4.1.2 3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.</note> My ſonne (ſaith the wiſeman) defraud not the poore of his liuing, and make not the needy eyes to waite long, make not an hungry ſoule ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull, neither vexe a man in his neceſſity. Trouble not the heart that is grieued, and deferre not the gift of the needy. Refuſe not the prayer of one that is in trouble, turne not away thy face from the poore. Turne not thine eyes aſide in anger from the poore, and giue him none occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſpeake euill of thee, for if he curſe thee in the bitternes of his ſoule, his prayer ſhal be heard of him that made him. Be cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous vnto the company of the poore, and humble thy ſoule vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:12856:58"/>the elder, and bow down thine head vnto a man of worſhip. Let it not grieue thee to bow downe thine eare vnto the pore, but pay thy debt, &amp; giue him a friendly anſwere. Deliuer him that fuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth wrong, from the hand of the oppreſſor, and be not faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted when thou iudgeſt. Bee as a father to the fatherles, and as an husband vnto their Mother, ſo ſhalt thou be as the ſonne of the moſt high; and he ſhall loue thee more then euen thy mother doth. Likewiſe the Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> doth paint out <hi>charity</hi> &amp; the works therof, as a part of righteouſnes: <hi>If thou powre out thy ſoule to the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, and refreſh the troubled ſoule, then ſhall thy light ſpring out in the darknes, and thy darknes ſhall be as the noone day.</hi> And in the ſame place he ſaith, that if a man deale
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:12856:58"/>his bread to the hungry, &amp; bring the poore that wander vnto his houſe, and couer the naked, not hyding himſelfe from his owne fleſh;<note place="margin">Iſay 58.7.8.9.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Then</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhall thy light breake forth as the morning, and thine health ſhall grow ſpeedily, and thy righteouſnes ſhall goe before thee, and the glory of the Lord ſhall em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace thee.</hi> Wherein wee maye learne that as righteouſnes is the life of Chriſtians, acording to <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiel,</hi> ſo is it the light of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans according to <hi>Iſay.</hi> To which purpoſe tendeth likewiſe the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation of our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before men,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5.16.</note> 
                  <hi>that they may ſee your good workes and glorifie your father which is in heauen.</hi> Moreouer that <hi>Charity</hi> or <hi>Loue</hi> is the perfection of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian righteouſnes, it doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare abundantly by the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:12856:59"/>of the holy Apoſtles.<note place="margin">Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 13.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Loue doth not euill to his neighbour</hi> (ſaith Saint Paul) <hi>therefore is loue the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of the law:</hi> and in the ſame chapter he exhorteth thus, <hi>Owe nothing to any man,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſe 8.</note> 
                  <hi>but to loue one another: for he that loueth another hath fulfilled the law.</hi> And writing to the Coloſſians, he calleth <hi>Loue the bond of perfectnes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Collo. 3.14</note> which is as much as the perfection of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian righteouſnes. And <hi>hee that keepeth his word</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn) in him is the loue of God perfite in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 John 2.5 &amp; 5.3.</note> 
                  <hi>for this is the loue of God, that we keepe his commaundements, and his commandements are not grieuous.</hi> Loue (ſaith the wiſeman) is the keeping of the lawes, &amp; the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the lawes is the aſſurance of immortallity,<note place="margin">Wiſd. 6.18 19.</note> and immortalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty maketh vs neere vnto God And therefore the Lord maketh
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:12856:59"/>alwaies a coniunct exhortation to loue and obedience:<note place="margin">Deut. 30.6 15.16.19.20.</note> behold (ſaith the Lord) I haue ſet before thee this day life and good, death and euill, in that I commaund thee this day to loue the Lord thy God, to walke in his waies, and to keepe his commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and his ordinances, and his lawes, that thou mayeſt liue and be multiplyed, and that the Lord thy God may bleſſe thee: And againe, I call heauen and earth to record this day againſt you, that I haue ſet before you life and death, bleſſing &amp; curſing, therefore chooſe life, that both thou and thy ſeed may liue, by <hi>lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing</hi> the Lord thy God, by <hi>obeying</hi> his voyce, and by cleauing vnto him, for he is thy life and the length of thy daies. Finally, our Sauiour expreſly affirmeth, that
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:12856:60"/>Loue is both the greateſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement,<note place="margin">Mat. 22.36 37.38.39.</note> and the next vnto the greateſt. The firſt, ſtanding &amp; conſiſting in the loue of God, &amp; the ſecond, in the loue of our neighbour.<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.8. &amp; 3.23. &amp; 2 Ioh. 5</note> And Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, that loue is both the olde commaundement of the Father, in the old Teſtament, &amp; the new commandement of the Sonne in the new Teſtament: and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently <hi>loue</hi> or <hi>charitie,</hi> is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation &amp; perfection aſwell of euangelicall as legall righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes.</p>
               <p>Thus then wee ſee how that <hi>loue</hi> or <hi>charitie</hi> is the chiefe part of the breaſt-plate of righteouſnes, and euen as it were that part of this ſpirituall armour-piece, that couereth and fenceth the heart, which thing the Apoſtle dooth yet more punctually inſinuate,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:12856:60"/>exhorting the Theſſalonians to the putting on of the Breaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Loue.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 5.8</note> And it is of this ſame inherent and actuall righteouſnes, that the ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaketh, writing to the Corinthians,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.7.</note> and calling it by the name of the <hi>armour of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 3.18. &amp; 5.16.</note> and likewiſe Saint <hi>Iames</hi> when as he ſaith that the fruit of righteouſnes is ſowne in peace of them that make peace, and that the prayer of the righteous man auaileth much.<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.29</note> And alſo St. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaying he that doth righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes is borne of God:<note place="margin">Reu. 22.11</note> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, he that is righteous, let him be righteous ſtill: and Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> when as he ſaith that wee look for new heauens, and a new earth, according to his promiſe,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.13</note> wherein dwelleth righteouſnes; and our Sauiour himſelfe, when
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:12856:61"/>as he telleth vs that he that recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth a righteus man in the name of a righteous man ſhal receaue a righteus mans reward:<note place="margin">Mat. 10.41</note> as alſo whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as he teacheth vs how that the righteouſnes of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ought to exceed farre the righteouſnes of the Scribes and Phariſes,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.20.</note> and withall pronounceth them bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that ſuffer perſecution for righteouſnes ſake:<note place="margin">Math. 5.10.</note> and <hi>Salomon</hi> doth almoſt euery where in his Prouerbs ſpeake of this kinde of righteouſnes, whereby the belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſoule is inherently &amp; actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally made righteous, by the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Gods ſanctifying ſpirit, as may appeare by theſe few te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies, ſelected out of many.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Righteouſnes deliuereth from death,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prouerb 10</note> 
                  <hi>the Lord will not famiſh the ſoule of the righteous, Bleſſings are vpon the head of the righteous, The
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:12856:61"/>memoriall of the iuſt ſhall be bleſſed: he that walketh vprightly walketh boldly, the mouth of a righteous man is a well ſpring of life, the labour of the righteous tendeth to life, the lips of the righteous do feed many, God will grant the deſire of the righteous, the righteous is as an euerlaſting fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, the patient abiding of the righteous ſhall be gladnes, the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſhall neuer be remoued.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The righteouſnes of the vpright ſhall direct his way,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prover. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>the righteouſnes of the iuſt ſhall deliuer them, the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous eſcapeth out of trouble. In the proſperity of the righteous the Citty reioyceth, by the bleſling of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous the Citty is exalted, he that ſoweth righteouſnes ſhall receaue a ſure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, righteouſnes leadeth to life, the deſire of the righteous is only good, the ſeede of the righteous ſhall eſcape, the righteous ſhall flouriſh as leafe, a
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:12856:62"/>righteous man hateth lying wordes: righteouſnes preſerueth the vpright of life,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prouer. 13</note> 
                  <hi>the light of the righteous reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth, vnto the righteous God will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence good,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prouer. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>The righteous eateth to the contentation of his minde, hee that walketh in his righteouſnes fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the Lord, the tabernacle of the righteous ſhall flouriſh, the righteous hath hope in his death, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conſidering then the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent condition of the righteous man,<note place="margin">Prou. 28.1.</note> what meruaile is it though he <hi>be bold as a Lyon,</hi> to ſpeake with the ſame <hi>Salomon?</hi> he is bold, and what is it that maketh him thus bold, but this ſelfe ſame inward armour &amp; ſpirituall breaſt-plate which he beareth within his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome? he is bold, and bold as a Lyon, yea the deuowring Lyon by his boldnes is turned into flight. In one worde, none muſt
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:12856:62"/>dwell in thoſe new heauens and new earth,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.13</note> wherein dwelleth righteouſnes (as the great Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaketh) but ſuch as in this olde earth haue had new hearts, and Chriſts infuſed righteouſnes dwelling in thoſe new hearts; for onely the righteous ſhall liue for euer:<note place="margin">Wiſd. 5.15 16</note> their reward is alſo with the Lord, and the moſt high hath care of them, therefore ſhal they receaue a glorious kingdome, &amp; a beautifull crowne of the Lords hands.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 7. Of the Shoes of peace.</head>
               <p>THe Chriſtian muſt haue on his feete the ſhooes of peace, that is to ſay, his wayes muſt bee
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:12856:63"/>wayes of peace, and ſuch as are worthy of him that hath bene called vnto the participation of Gods peace: for it becommeth Chriſtians to walke worthy of God,<note place="margin">Epheſ 4.1. Philli. 1.2 Coloſ. 1.10 1. Theſſa. 2.12.</note> and of the vocation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto we are called, (ſaith the Apoſtle) and it is fitting that our conuerſation be as it becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the Goſpell of Chriſt, which is th Goſpell of peace, and therefore the ſame Apoſtle doth often exhort the faithfull to the ſtudy of peace. <hi>Let vs followe then thoſe things,</hi> (ſaith he to the Romaines) <hi>which concerne peace:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 14.17 19.</note> The kingdome of God (ſaith the ſame Apoſtle) is righteouſnes &amp; peace; and therefore if we deſire to be poſſeſſors of the kingdome of God, we muſt be followers &amp; practiſers of righteouſnes and peace:<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.10 Rom 12.18</note> and againe, <hi>if it be poſſible</hi>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:12856:63"/>(ſaith he) <hi>as much as in you is, haue peace with all men:</hi> and writing to the Corinthians, <hi>be perfect,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Corr. 13 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>be of good comfort, be of one minde, liue in peace, and the God of loue and peace ſhall be with you.</hi> And writing to the Epheſians he exhorteth all Chriſtians in their perſons, to endeauour to keepe the vnitie of the ſpirit in the bond of peace,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.1.2 3.4.5.6.</note> as there is one body, one ſpirit, &amp; one hope of our vocation, one Lord, one ſaith, one baptiſme, one God and father of all, which is aboue all, and through all, and in vs all. And to the Philippians,<note place="margin">Phill. 1.27</note> that we continue in one ſpirit, and in one minde, fighting toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through the faith of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell. And to the Hebrewes,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.14</note> 
                  <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low peace</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>with all men, and holynes, without the which no man ſhall ſee God.</hi> God is the God of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:12856:64"/>peace, and therefore no man can goe vnto God, except he haue on his feete the ſhoes of peace. <hi>Let the peace of God</hi> (ſaith the ſame Apoſtle) <hi>rule in your hearts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Colloſſ. 3.15</note> 
                  <hi>to the which ye are called, in one body, and be ye amiable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Chriſtian, as he is at war, yea a continuall warre with the Deuill, the world, and the fleſh, ſo is he at peace with God:<note place="margin">Rom. 5.1.</note> 
                  <hi>For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing iuſtified by faith, we haue peace to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle: and as our God is the God of peace,<note place="margin">Rom. 15.33. 2. Cor. 13.11. 1. Theſſ. 5.23 Iſay 9.6. Ephc. 2.14 15.16.17</note> and Chriſt the Prince of peace, ſo is he both the maker and the preacher of our peace: <hi>For he is our peace</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>which hath made of both one, and hath bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the ſtop of the partition wall, and came and preached peace to you which were a farre off, and to them that
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:12856:64"/>were neere.</hi> And this ſame thing the Angells did preſignifie by their ſweet ſong of peace, which they ſung at his birth,<note place="margin">Luke 2.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Glory bee to God in the higheſt heauens, and peace in earth; and towards men goodwill.</hi> Giuing vs to vnderſtand, that Chriſt came into the world, to make peace both betweene God and men, and betweene man and man: who as he preached peace vnto men, ſo was it alwaies his cuſtome to wiſh peace vnto men, whenſoeuer hee came amongſt men; ſaying, <hi>Peace be vnto you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk 24.36 Ioh 20.21. luke 7.50. &amp; 8.48. &amp; 19.42.</note> and diſmiſſing them, to bid them <hi>Goe in peace;</hi> yea he wept ouer <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> becauſe it knew not thoſe thinges that belonged to her peace: And being to leaue the world, he left his peace for a le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacy vnto his ſeruants, ſaying, <hi>Peace I leaue with you, my peace I giue
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:12856:65"/>vnto you,</hi> to the end that in him we might haue peace, and that the peace of God might rule in our hearts,<note place="margin">Collo. 3.15</note> according to the Lords owne ſpeech, and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles exhortation.</p>
               <p>The whole company and ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of Chriſtians make but one army fighting together through the faith of the Goſpell, againſt the enemy thereof Sathan, and all his ſuppoſts. And if we be at peace and concord among our ſelues, we may be ſure to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come; but if we be at warre one with another, and if we be deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded one from another, in faith or in affection, we may be no leſſe ſure that Sathan and his army will be able to make among vs a great ſlaughter.<note place="margin">Mark 3.24 25</note> 
                  <hi>If a kingdome be deuided againſt it ſelfe</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour) <hi>that kingdome cannot
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:12856:65"/>ſtand; or if a houſe be diuided againſt it ſelfe, that houſe cannot continue;</hi> and in like maner if the army of Chriſtians be deuided againſt it ſelfe, it cannot preuaile: and therefore it is that we ſee the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of vnity, concord, &amp; peace, is ſo dilligently reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended to vs in holy ſcripture.<note place="margin">Rom. 12.16</note> 
                  <hi>Be of like affection one towards another,</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi>) and againe, <hi>I beſeech you brethren by the name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt that ye all ſpeake one thing, and that there be no diſſentions among you: but be ye knit together in one minde,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.10. 2. Cor. 13.11</note> 
                  <hi>and in one iudgement.</hi> And yet againe, <hi>If there be therefore any conſolation in Chriſt, if any comfort of loue, if a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny fellowſhip of the ſpirit, if any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion and mercy, fulfill my ioy, that ye be like minded, hauing the ſame loue, being of one accord, and of one iudgement.</hi> And as he prayeth and
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:12856:66"/>exhorteth chriſtians to be of one opinion and of one affection, ſo doth he pray vnto God to giue vs that we <hi>be like minded one towards a nother,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 15.5 6</note> 
                  <hi>according to Chriſt Ieſus, that with one mind &amp; with one mouth we may praiſe God, euen the father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Yea our Sauiour himſelfe in his laſt prayer,<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.20 21.22.23.</note> prayed that all beleeuers might be one, and be all made perfite in one. But alas! it is a pittifull thing to conſider how aduerſe the moſt part of men now a daies are, from this ſtudy of chriſtian vnion and peace. The Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> of olde complained of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions were of his time:<note place="margin">Iſay 59.8.</note> That they knew not the way of peace.<note place="margin">Pſal. 120.5 6</note> And King <hi>Dauid</hi> of the diſſentious men of his age, made the like complaint, <hi>I ſeeke peace, and when I ſpeake thereof, they are bent to war,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:12856:66"/>they make them ready to battell;</hi> and the ſame complaint may the peaceable minded men make now adayes with farre greater cauſe, in regard that Chriſtians are on all hands ſo much adicted to diſcord. But the greateſt pitty of all is to conſider how that Chriſtians can be ſo hard-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as to behold without pitty or compaſſion the miſticall body of Chriſt, in ſo pittifull a paſſion, as to ſee it ſtretched along vpon the croſſe of the croſſenes of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine conceites, bored through with the nailes of nicenes, crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the pricking thornes of ſubtil Sillogiſmes, &amp; Sophiſmes tranſpearced with the ſpeare of ſpightfull ſeperations, and expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vnto the ſcoffage and moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kage of both misbelieuing Iewes and vnbelieuing Gentiles. To ſee
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:12856:67"/>I ſay without ſorrow and ſubuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Body of the Church of Chriſt lying in the ſight of theſe two ſcoffers of Chriſtianity, like the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded man left of robbers,<note place="margin">Luke 10.30 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.32.33.34.35.</note> halfe dead, lying betweene <hi>Ieri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> and to behold both Prieſts and Leuites paſſing by without yeelding any ſuccour or reliefe. So that either ſome Samaritane, ſome Prince, or ſome priuate lay perſon belike muſt put to his hand to powre the oyle of mittigation into the diſſected bodies wounds; &amp; bind them vp, or els the charitable deed is like to lye vndone.</p>
               <p>It is the part therefore no doubt of all good Chriſtians, with the kingly Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> to deſire and wiſh peace, to ſeek it,<note place="margin">Pſal. 120.6. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>22 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.7 8.96</note> to ſpeake of it, and to pray for it. <hi>O pray for the peace of Ieruſalem,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:12856:67"/>they ſhall proſper that loue thee: peace be within thy walles, and plenteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes within thy palaces:</hi> and not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this, but euery one ought to ſee ke to doe her good, with the ſame Prophet, and to labour for her peace, by furthering and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancing the ſame, according to their ſeuerall abilities: yea who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer deſireth to be bleſſed, or to be accounted &amp; called one of the children of God, ought to endeauoure to be a peace-maker at leaſt in affection, if ſo be that his ability can not reach vnto ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and execution.<note place="margin">Math. 5.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſsed are the peace-makers</hi> (ſaith the Prince of peace) <hi>for they ſhall be called the Sonnes of God.</hi> And doubtles a moſt bleſſed and happy thing it were, if once princes and paſtors could be broght to ſacrifice their ſeueral abilities to the procuring
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:12856:68"/>and furthering of this holy peace that the ruines of Sion might be repaired, the breaches and deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of Gods houſe redreſſed, and this much deſired concord reſtored at laſt vnto Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. That ſuch Iewes &amp; Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles as are yet without being no longer ſcandaliſed by our diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and diſſections; but ſeeing peace and vnity flouriſhing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs, might be thereby indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to like the better of our reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and ſo in end might be hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led home vnto the ſociety of the Chriſtian profeſſion, That ſo all the Kings and kingdomes of the earth, may know &amp; acknowledge the Lord Ieſus,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.8.10 11. &amp; 67.7. &amp; 102.15.22 &amp; 86.9.</note> and feare and ſerue him: that his kingdome may encreaſe and flouriſh more and more, being freed from theſe dolefull diuiſions, that do
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:12856:68"/>thus weaken and blacken the ſame, and ſo vnited, may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended from ſea to ſea, euen from the riuer vnto the ends of the earth,<note place="margin">Pſal. 72.8.9.10.11.15.17.19. Iſay 45.22.</note> according to the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure of the diuine Oracles, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the plenitude and collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Gentiles, the beatitude and conuerſion of the Iewes, and the amplitude and extention of Chriſts kingdome, conſiſting of both Iewes and Gentiles, vnited vnder one ſoueraigne Lord, and ruled by one Chriſtian law.</p>
               <p>The which Oracles doe beare, that in the laſt dayes all nations ſhall flowe vnto the Church, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one to another: <hi>Come,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſay 2.2.3. Micah. 1.2.</note> 
                  <hi>let vs goe vp to the mountaine of the Lord, to the houſe of the God of Iacob, and he will teach vs his waies, and we will walke in his paths: Vp, let vs goe and pray before the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zach 8.21</note> 
                  <hi>and ſeeke the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:12856:69"/>Lord of hoſtes, we will goe alſo.</hi> So that then in this day (ô the thrice happy and deſireable day!) there ſhall be no contrariety or recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſancy amongs Chriſtians: for after long debate and much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, they ſhall breake their ſwords into mattockes,<note place="margin">Iſay 2.4. &amp; 11.9. &amp; 63.5. Micah 4.2.</note> and their ſpeares into Sythes; they ſhall not learne to fight any more, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall they any longer hurt or deſtroy one another in the mountaine of his holyneſſe. As if he ſhould ſay, Chriſtians ſhall burne their bookes of controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and turne their controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie ſhooles into ſchooles of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, their warring and wrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſhal vaniſh, their iarring and iangling ſhall take an end. <hi>For the mountaines</hi> (that is Chriſtian Princes) <hi>ſhall bring peace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 72.3.</note> 
                  <hi>and the hilles</hi> (that is heauenly and
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:12856:69"/>humble prieſts) <hi>ſhall bring righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes vnto the people.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 72.7. Iſay 11.9. Haba. 2.24 Iſay 66.12.</note> Then there ſhall be abundance of peace, and the earth ſhall be full of the knowledge of the Lord, as the ſea that ouerfloweth with water; yea he will extend peace ouer his church like a flood, and the glory of the Gentiles like a flowing ſtreame;<note place="margin">Zephan 3.9</note> finally <hi>He will turne to the people a pure langage that they may all call vpon the name of the Lord, to ſerue him with one conſent.</hi> Euen ſo, come Lord Ieſus, come Prince of peace, &amp; come quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by thy ſpirit of peace into the heads and hearts of all diuided chriſtians,<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.21 22.23.</note> 
                  <hi>That they may be made perfit in one,</hi> as the father &amp; thou art one. Inſpire vs all with the ſpirit of peace, that the common people in their houſes may pray for peace, Schollers in their
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:12856:70"/>ſchooles may write of peace, Preachers in the Church may preach for peace, and Kings and Princes in their kingdomes may worke for peace, and incourage peaceable ſpirits vnto the ſtudy of peace; ſo that at laſt as chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of peace; we may ſing vnto the praiſe of the God of peace, that moſt excellent ſong of peace <hi>Ecce quam bonum et quam iucundum fratres habitare in vnum.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 133.1</note>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>O how happy a thing it is,</l>
                  <l>and ioyfull for to ſee:</l>
                  <l>Chriſtians together faſt to hold,</l>
                  <l>the bond of vnitie.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 8. Of the ſhield of faith.</head>
               <p>BVt aboue all, the Chriſtian muſt take vnto him the <hi>Shield</hi>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:12856:70"/>of <hi>faith,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle: for it is of ſuch efficacy &amp; force, that it is able to quench all the fiery darts of the deuill, to vanquiſh the world, and to ouercome the wicked one. In the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture we may read, of the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold and wonderfull effects of faith: It is of greater force then the moſt ouerflowing floods;<note place="margin">Heb. 11.29 30.31.32 33.34.35</note> for by faith the red ſea was made as dry land for the belieuing <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> to paſſe through into the earthly <hi>Canaan.</hi> And in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner all Gods true Iſraelites, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the promiſe, ſhall paſſe ſafely through the red ſea of this reſtles and ruthles world, into the heauenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> where there is fulnes of reſt. Faith is ſtronger then the ſtrongeſt towne walles, for by faith the walles of <hi>Iericho</hi> fell downe after
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:12856:71" rendition="simple:additions"/>that they had bene compaſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſeauen dayes. And by the ſame faith, the walles of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall <hi>Iericho</hi> that is, of the citty of ſinne wherein the chriſtian ſoule dwelleth, though not as a Cittizen (for ſo it belongeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Citty of God, which is the Citty of righteouſnes) but rather as a captiue or priſoner: they ſhal in end fall, after that wee haue compaſſed the ſame by wraſtling and fighting againſt ſinne, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſeauen dayes or weekes as the world ſhall continue. <hi>Faith</hi> is ſtronger then kingdomes and kings, for diuers of Gods Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions, as <hi>Gedeon, Sampſon,</hi> and <hi>Dauid,</hi> through <hi>Faith</hi> haue ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued kingdomes, and turned to flight the armies of the aliants. And the ſame <hi>faith</hi> is ſtronger then the kingdome of ſinne and
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:12856:71"/>Sathan, for it ſubdueth the ſame, and ouercommeth both the kingdome and the king thereof. <hi>Faith</hi> is ſtronger then Lyons,<note place="margin">Dan. 3.23.24.25.26.27.28. &amp; 6.16.22 23. 1. King 17.17.18.19.20.21.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 2. King. 4 20.32.33.34.35.</note> for by <hi>faith Daniel</hi> ſtopped the Lyons iawes; and ſtronger then fire, for the three children through <hi>faith</hi> quenched the violence of the fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry furnace. Finally, it is ſtronger then death, for through <hi>faith, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias</hi> rayſed vp the widdow of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reptas</hi> ſonne, and <hi>Eliſha</hi> the <hi>Shuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi> ſonne. And by the ſame <hi>faith,</hi> the Chriſtian doth ſtop the mouth of the deuouring Lyon, and as it were doth quench the hot fornace of hell-fire: it is ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then death, yea then the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of death, for as it quencheth all the deuills fiery darts, ſo it vanquiſheth the wicked one, it conquereth the ſpirituall death of the ſoule, by aſſurance and
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:12856:72"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:12856:72"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:12856:73"/>ſanctification, and it ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the corporall death of the body, by a powerfull and a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious reſurrection:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.54.55.56.57</note> 
                  <hi>For when this corruptible hath put on incorruption, and this mortall hath put on immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ty, then ſhall be brought to paſſe the ſaying that is written</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>Death is ſwallowed vp into victory: O death, where is thy ſting? O graue where is thy victory?</hi> And this victory we obtaine by faith in Chriſt, as the ſame Apoſtle teacheth, <hi>But thankes be vnto God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>which hath giuen vs vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſe 13.14</note> for it is he that hath ſaid <hi>I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme thee from the power of the graue, I will deliuer thee from death; O death I will be thy death; O graue I will be thy deſtruction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is not then without great cauſe that the Godly haue beene
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:12856:73"/>alwaies wont ro pray vnto God, to encreaſe and confirme their <hi>faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark 9.23 24. &amp;c. 4.</note> for ſo we read did not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the belieuing father of him that was firſt poſſeſſed of Sathan, and afterward cured by our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, but euen the Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, <hi>Lord I belieue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 17.5.</note> 
                  <hi>helpe my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliefe,</hi> ſaid the one: <hi>Lord inereaſe our faith,</hi> ſaid the other. And therefore the Apoſtle St. <hi>Iude</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth Chriſtians to pray in the holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">Iude. V. 20.21.</note> to be edified and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed in the <hi>faith:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 13.5.</note> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> willeth euery man to proue himſelfe whether he be in the <hi>faith</hi> or no, as alſo to grow from <hi>faith</hi> to <hi>faith,</hi> and to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue grounded and ſtabliſhed in the <hi>faith:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 1.17. Collo. 1.2. Ephe. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.18.19. Philli. 1.29 Gall. 5.22. 1. Cor. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.5.9.11</note> For as God is the giuer of <hi>faith,</hi> and euen the worker and beginner of it in vs, ſo is he encreaſer, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:12856:74"/>and finiſher of our faith,<note place="margin">act. 15.9. Rom. 3.24 25. to 29. 2. Cor. 5.17 Coloſ. 1.12 1. Ioh. 2.3 Gall. 3.14.26. Ephe. 3.26 1. Pet. 1.2.5.9. &amp; 5.9. 1. Ioh. 3.4 Epheſ. 2.8.9. 2. Tim. 3.15. acts 26.18.</note> by the holy Ghoſt: By <hi>faith</hi> our harts are purified, we are regenerated and iuſtified, yea raiſed vp from ſinne: By <hi>faith</hi> we know God, we are bleſſed of God, and made his ſonnes, we haue peace with him and free acceſſe vnto him. By faith we are ſtrengthned in Gods grace, by it we reſiſt and ouercome both the world and the deuill, and in end we acquire the ſaluation of our ſoules, and inheritance among the Saints.</p>
               <p>But the Chriſtian muſt in the meane time conſider how that all theſe things and the like oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring in holy ſcripture are to be vnderſtood of ſuch a <hi>faith</hi> as doth liue and worke by loue and charity, and perſeuere and laſt by continuance and conſtancy. For firſt if <hi>faith</hi> haue not good
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:12856:74"/>workes annexed vnto it, it is but a dead <hi>faith</hi> as the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Iames</hi> doth teach,<note place="margin">Iame 2.17 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.21.</note> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently it is both vnprofitable and vnable to work any of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue named effects. And therfore not onely doth the ſame Apoſtle teach vs that <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith was made perfit by works: But alſo St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſheweth vs that the <hi>faith</hi> whereof he maketh ſo often mention in his Epiſtles is none other but that which worketh by loue.<note place="margin">Galla. 5.6</note> 
                  <hi>For in Ieſus Chriſt neither Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion auaileth any thing, neither vncircumciſion but faith which worketh by loue:</hi> and againe,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.2</note> 
                  <hi>If I had all faith</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſo that I could remooue mountaines and had not loue, I were nothing.</hi> Neither are we iuſtified by any other <hi>faith;</hi> for the iuſtifying <hi>faith</hi> of Chriſtians liueth by loue; and as
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:12856:75"/>for <hi>faith</hi> without <hi>loue,</hi> it is ſuch a <hi>faith</hi> as the Deuill and the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned may haue, for the Deuils al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo beleeue and tremble,<note place="margin">Iame 2.19.</note> (ſaith the Apoſtle) that is, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue through <hi>faith,</hi> and they tremble through feare, but they loue neither God nor man through hearty affection. The Chriſtians <hi>faith</hi> muſt not onely be in the head by light and illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, but alſo in the heart by aſſurance and ſanctification, and by loue and affection. It muſt not ſlitter in the braines, but it muſt neſtle in the breaſt. In one word, it muſt be like vnto <hi>Arons</hi> pretious oyntment, which being powred vpon his head,<note place="margin">Pſal. 133.2</note> ran downe vpon his beard, and from thence vnto his breaſt, and went downe on the border of his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. <hi>Faith</hi> I ſay, muſt diffuſe
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:12856:75"/>and ſhed it ſelfe abroade like vnto a pretious oyle; for it muſt go downe from the head vnto the heart, and from thence vnto the hands.</p>
               <p>Thus then we ſee how that the ſauing and iuſtifying <hi>faith</hi> of Chriſtians doth liue and worke by loue. And therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the <hi>Theſſalomans</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyneth <hi>loue</hi> with <hi>faith,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of them both but one breaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate.<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.8</note> 
                  <hi>Let vs which are of the day</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>be ſober, putting on the Breaſt-plate of ſaith and loue.</hi> And writing to <hi>Timothie,</hi> he maketh of them but one maine end of one great commandement.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.5</note> 
                  <hi>The end of the commandement</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is loue out of a pure heart, and of a good conſcience, and of faith vnfained.</hi> So dooth bleſſed Saint <hi>Iohn;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.23</note> 
                  <hi>This is his commandement</hi> (ſaith he)
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:12856:76"/>
                  <hi>that we beleeue in the name of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt and loue one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as he gaue commandement.</hi> And the great Apoſtle St. <hi>Peter</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyneth all Chriſtians to ioyne to <hi>faith</hi> vertue and loue,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.5.6 7.8.9.</note> to the end that it be not idle, nor wee vnfruitfull in the knowledge of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>And as the chriſtians faith muſt be a liuing faith by loue and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie: So muſt it likewiſe be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuering faith by continuance &amp; perpetuitie,<note place="margin">Mat. 24.13</note> for <hi>he that endureth to the end ſhall be ſaued,</hi> ſaith our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. And therefore he exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his diſciples and vs in them to peſeuer and abide in the faith <hi>Abide in one</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>&amp; I in you; as the branch cannot beare fruit of it ſelf except it abide in the vine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh 15.4.9</note> 
                  <hi>no more can ye except ye abide in me: as the father hath loued me ſo haue I loued you, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:12856:76"/>in my loue.</hi> And to the Iewes which belieued in him he ſaid,<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.31.</note> 
                  <hi>If ye continue in my words,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">acts 13.43</note> 
                  <hi>ye are verily my diſciples,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> exhorted the belieuing people <hi>to continue in the grace of God,</hi> and the ſame Apoſtle writing to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians, Watch ye</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſtand faſt in the faith, quite you like men,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 16 13.</note> 
                  <hi>and be ſtrong.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 3.12.13.14</note> And writing to the <hi>Hebrewes, Take heed</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren leaſt at any time there be in any of you an euill heart and vnfaithfull, to depart away from the liuing God: for we are made partakers of Chriſt, if we keepe ſure vnto the end, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning wherewith we are vpholden.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 4.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Let vs feare therfore leaſt at any time by for ſaking the promiſe of entring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his reſt, any of you ſhould ſeeme to be depriued: for it is impoſſible that they which were once lightened,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 6.4.5.6.11.</note> 
                  <hi>and haue taſted of the heauenly giſt, and
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:12856:77"/>were made partakers of the holy Ghoſt, and haue taſted of the good word of God, and of the powers of the world to come, if they ſhall fall away, ſhould be renewed againe by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, ſeeing they crucifie againe to them ſelues the ſonne of God, &amp; make a mock of him.</hi> For ſuch men as do with <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus</hi> put away a good conſcience,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.19.20.</note> and make ſhipwrack of their faith (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh) they treade vnder foote the ſonne of God, and counte the blood of the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament as an vnholy thing,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.29</note> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they were ſanctified, and in ſo doing, they doe deſpite and euen extinguiſh or quenche the ſpirit of grace And yet again the ſame Apoſtle doth dehorte Chriſtians from falling away, in theſe wordes,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.15</note> 
                  <hi>Take heede that no man fall away from the grace of God;</hi>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:12856:77"/>ſo he deterreth then from it in theſe. <hi>The iuſt ſhall liue by ſaith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10.38</note> 
                  <hi>but if any withdraue him ſelfe, my ſoule ſhall haue no pleaſure in him:</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the bleſſed Apoſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Pet 2.20 21.22. Iohn. 2.19. &amp; 5.16.</note> admoniſh vs of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable danger that doth follow vpon this back ſliding and this falling away of men from the grace and faith of Chriſt; for it is ſuch a ſinne, that he that commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it in the higheſt degree, that is to ſay, by falling away finally or totally from the grace of Chriſt and by grieuing the holy Ghoſt, he muſt not be prayed for;<note place="margin">Mat. 12.31 32. Mar. 3.29. Luke 12.10</note> yea our Sauour him ſelfe ſaith that it ſhall neuer be forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. And therefore he exhorteth the Chriſtian ſouldier thus by his Prophete, <hi>Beholde I come ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, holde that which thou haſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">&amp; 3.11.12</note> 
                  <hi>that no man take thy crowne.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reue. 2.25.26</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:12856:78"/>Finally there is no celeſtiall &amp; eternall rewarde promiſed but onely to him that by perſeuering in faith doth ouercome.<note place="margin">Rom. 2.7.11.17.26.27.28. &amp; 3.5.12.12</note> The which thing our Sauiour doth teache vs, by an eight-folde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition of a promiſe of rewarde to be rendered to him that ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth, vttered by Saint Iohn in his reuelation. And therefore as the Apoſtle exhorteth <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to fight the good fight of faith:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.12</note> ſo he admoniſheth him that he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuere in fighting, when as in the next words he biddeth him <hi>lay holde on eternall life.</hi> And ſpeaking of him ſelfe,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.7 8.</note> he ſaith, <hi>I haue fought a good fight and haue finiſhed my courſe: I haue kept the faith: hence forth is layde vp for me the crowne of righteouſnes which the Lord the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous iudge ſhall giue me at that day, and not to me onely but vnto them
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:12856:78"/>alſo that loue his appearing.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 9. Of the helmet of Hope</head>
               <p>ANd as the Chriſtian muſt be armed with the ſhielde of a liuing and perſeuering faith, ſo muſt he likewiſe haue his head armed with the helmet of hope, that is to ſay, he muſt expect pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently &amp; confidently for grace &amp; glory &amp; all good things at Gods hands, &amp; at his onely &amp; at none others els.<note place="margin">Pſal 9.10.</note> 
                  <hi>They that know thy name will truſt in thee, for thou Lord haſt not failed them that ſeeke thee. Yet my ſoule keepe thou ſilence vnto God, for mine hope is in him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal 62.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou art mine hope O Lord, and my portion in the land of the liuing.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 142.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> The holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet almoſt euery where calleth
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:12856:79"/>the Lord his <hi>hope,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.2 &amp; 131.1.2 3. &amp; 62.5. &amp; 65.5. &amp; 91.2. &amp; 142.5. Prou 30.5. Iſay 26.3.</note> his <hi>rocke,</hi> his <hi>fortreſſe,</hi> his <hi>ſtrength,</hi> his <hi>ſhield,</hi> and <hi>buckler,</hi> his <hi>refuge,</hi> and the <hi>horne of his ſaluation:</hi> yea not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his helpe and hope, but euen of all the ends of the earth, and of them that are farre off, in the ſea.<note place="margin">Pſal. 40.4. &amp; 146.5.</note> And he pronounceth him bleſſed whoſe hope is in the lord, and who maketh the Lord his truſt. The like doth the Prophete <hi>Ieremie, Bleſſed be the man</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that truſteth in the lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iere. 17 7 8</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; whoſe hope the Lord is, for he ſhal be as a tree that is planted by the water which ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth out her rootes by theriuer, &amp; ſhall not feele when the heate commeth, but her leafe ſhal be greene, &amp; ſhal not care for the yeere of drought, neither ſhall ceaſe from yeelding fruite.</hi> And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in his Lamentation, after much mourning and bitternes, he cheereth him ſelfe wmeto hat
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:12856:79"/>vp by reaſon of his ſure hope in God, and ſayeth,<note place="margin">Iame. 3.24.25.26.</note> 
                  <hi>the Lord is my portion ſayth my ſoule, therefore will I hope in him: the Lord is good vnto them that trust in him, and to the ſoule that ſeeketh him, it is good both to truſt, and to waite for the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the Lord. God is a ſhielde to thoſe that truſt in him</hi> ſayth <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 30.5 Iſay 26.3.</note> 
                  <hi>truſt in the Lord for euer (</hi>ſayth <hi>Iſaye) for in the Lord God is ſtrength for euermore.</hi> And <hi>S. Peter</hi> teacheth that God the father did ſend his ſonne into the world to redeeme vs with his pretious blood, as of a Lambe vndefiled, and without ſpot, and that he raiſed him from the dead and gaue him glory;<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.3.18.19.20.21</note> to the end <hi>that our faith and hope might be in God,</hi> who hath alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten vs againe according to his aboundant mercy (ſayth the ſame Apoſtle) vnto <hi>a liuely hope</hi> by
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:12856:80"/>the reſurrection of Ieſus Chriſt from the dead.<note place="margin">Rom. 5.5. &amp; 12.12.</note> And it is no other hope, but this liuely hope in God and in him alone which maketh not aſhamed, as the Apoſtle <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſpeaketh, and wherin he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth vs to reioyce.<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.16.</note> 
                  <hi>It is euen God the father which loued vs and hath giuen vs euerlaſting conſolation and good hope through grace,</hi> as the ſame Apoſtle ſpeaketh: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore good reaſon that our hope be in him who hath giuen vs the ſame; for all other hope which is not in God is a vaine and a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing or a perſhing hope.<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.13.14.15.</note> 
                  <hi>The hipocrites hope ſhall periſh</hi> (ſayth <hi>Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dad</hi> to <hi>Iob) his conſidence alſo ſhall be cut of, and his truſt ſhal be as the houſe of a Spider, he ſhall leane vpon his houſe, but it ſhall not ſtand, he ſhall holde him faſt by it, yet ſhall it not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure.</hi> Such as deſpiſe wiſedome
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:12856:80"/>and diſcipline (ſayth the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man) <hi>their hope is vaine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Wiſd. 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 13.</note> and their labours fooliſh, and their worke vnprofitable, and if they die haſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily they haue no hope, neither comfort in the day of try all. The hypocrites and vngodly mans hope reacheth no farther then vnto corruptible and tranſitorie things, and therefore it faileth them as ſoone as this tranſitorie life faileth them and flieth away from them. So that when as they haue moſt neede of hope, they haue no hope at all, but are made both hopeles and helples in one inſtant. The vngodly man ſhall be ſo far from reioycing in his hope as the godly man doth, that he ſhall be in end aſhamed of his hope:<note place="margin">Wiſd. 5.14 15.16.</note> 
                  <hi>For the hope of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly</hi> (ſaith the wiſeman) <hi>is like the duſt that is blowne away with the
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:12856:81"/>winde, and like a thin foame that is ſcattered abroad with the ſtorme, and as the ſmoake which is diſperſed with the winde, and as the remembrance of him paſſeth that tarrieth but for a day.</hi> But it fareth far otherwiſe with the godly man, whoſe hope is in God; <hi>For the righteous</hi> (that is ſuch as haue their hope in God and not in man, or in any tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory thing) <hi>ſhall liue for euer: their reward is alſo with the Lord, and the moſt hie hath care of them. Therefore ſhall they receiue a glorious kingdome and a beautifull crowne of the Lords hand: for with his right hand ſhall he couer them, and with his arme ſhal he defend them.</hi> And for this cauſe the Apoſtle compareth the hope of the godly to an Anker, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the ſtedfaſtnes thereof, which taketh hold of a better &amp; ſurer foundation then any tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:12856:81"/>or corruptible thing,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.18.19.</note> 
                  <hi>For it enterreth into that which is within the vayle,</hi> that is, it is founded and grounded vpon an immortal and incorruptible Crown: for <hi>If in this life only we hauchope in Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.19</note> 
                  <hi>we are of all men the moſt miſerable,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle; ſo that our hope muſt reach further then this life, or any thing whatſoeuer that is ſubiect to our ſenſe, or yet may be here in this world ſeene. <hi>We are ſaued by hope</hi> (ſaith the ſame Apoſtle) <hi>but hope that is ſeene is not hope;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.24 25.</note> 
                  <hi>for how can a man hope for that which he ſeeth? but if we hope for that we ſee not, we doe with patience abide for it.</hi> For there is one <hi>hope</hi> of our vocation, euen the <hi>hope</hi> of eternall life, of glory,<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.4. Collo. 1.27</note> and of an immortall inheritance. So ſaith the Apoſtle of the Gentils Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">T t. 3.7.</note> 
                  <hi>That we being iuſtified by his
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:12856:82"/>grace, ſhould be made heires according to the hope of eternall life.</hi> And ſo ſaith the grear feeder of the flock Saint <hi>Peter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed be God, euen the father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, which according to his abundant mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy hath bigotten vs againe vnto vs a liuely hope by the reſurrection of Ieſus Chriſt from the dead, to an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance immortall and vndefiled, and that fadeth not away, reſerued for you in heauen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as wee are often in holy Scripture exhorted to grow &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in faith; &amp; to be grounded &amp; ſtabliſhed in the faith,<note place="margin">Collo. 1.23</note> ſo are we likewiſe admoniſhed that we be not moued away from the <hi>hope</hi> of the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Heb 3.6. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 18.19 &amp; 105 23.</note> but that we <hi>hold faſt the confidence and the reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of hope vnto the end; let vs keepe the profeſsion of our hope</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>without wauering, for he is faith-full
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:12856:82"/>that promiſed.</hi> And the ſame Apoſtle as he praiſeth God for the effectuall faith, feruent loue, and patient hope of the <hi>Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Theſſ 1.2.3 4.</note> ſo he prayeth vnto God for the <hi>Romaines;</hi> that he would fill them in al ioy and peace in belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing,<note place="margin">Rom. 15.13.</note> that they may abound in hope through the power o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the holy Ghoſt: <hi>hope</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>maketh not aſhamed,</hi> yea <hi>we are ſaued by hope,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 5.5. &amp; 8.24. &amp; 12.12.</note> and therefore he exhorteth vs to reioyce in hope So then as many as would not be aſhamed in that great day, but euen re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce with ioy vnſpeakeable and glorious, let them now harbour in their hearts a ſtedfaſt and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faileable hope; for bleſſed is he and yet more bleſſed ſhall he be that hath not fallen, neither doth fall away at any time from his hope in the Lord, as ſpeaketh the
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:12856:83"/>wiſe <hi>Siracides.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 10. Of the Sword of Gods word.</head>
               <p>NO good Souldier goeth out at any time to the field, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſworde by his ſide or els in his hand: and the Chriſtian who is called to be a ſpirituall Souldier, muſt haue a ſword by his ſide, or rather in his hand likewiſe. And becauſe that his warrefare and his weapons are ſpirituall and not carnall,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 10 4.</note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt he take vnto him not any material ſword for this fight, but the ſword of the ſpirit, which is the word of God.<note place="margin">Heb. 4.12.</note> 
                  <hi>For the word of God is liuely</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>and mighty in operation, and ſharper then any two edged ſword, &amp; entreth through euen vnto the diuiding aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:12856:83"/>of the ſoule, and the ſpirit, and of the ioynts, and the marrow, and is a diſcerner of the thoughts, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the heart.</hi> And truly it had need to be a ſharp ſworde, that muſt be an inſtrument of the cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off of all ſinnefull and ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all affections from the ſoule, and of the ſlaying and killing of our concupiſcence, and inordinate deſires and fleſhly Iuſts. And it had need be a ſtrong ſword that muſt in <hi>Iudiths</hi> hand, that is in the hand of the praiſing and confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Chriſtian, (for <hi>Iudith</hi> ſigniſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth praiſing and confeſſing) cut off the head of ſo ſtrong a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine as is the ſpirituall <hi>Olofernes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudith 13.6.7.6.8 9.15.17.18.</note> (for <hi>Olofernus</hi> ſignifieth a ſtrong Captaine) the chiefe of our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall enemies. <hi>Iudith</hi> cut off <hi>Olo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernes</hi> head with his owne faw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 17.51.</note> and <hi>Dauid</hi> cut off <hi>Goliahs</hi>
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:12856:84"/>head with his owne ſword: but it fareth farre otherwiſe with the ſpirituall <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Iudith,</hi> that is with the Chriſtian Souldier, man or woman: for no ſex nor age is exempted from the ſpirituall warrefare. The Chriſtian ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er I ſay muſt vſe another kinde of ſword, for the cutting off ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>Olofernes</hi> and <hi>Goltahs</hi> head, then any ſuch as he can take from <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> himſelfe; yea his ſworde muſt be the ſworde of the ſpirit, that is ſuch a one as the ſpirit of God hath forged with his owne finger, and hath deliuered vnto vs by the miniſterial hand of his Prophets and Apoſtles. And it was this ſelfe ſame ſworde of Gods worde which our great Captaine Chriſt Ieſus vſed in
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:12856:84"/>his great fight againſt our great enemie, whome he repelleth once, twiſe, thriſe with an <hi>Ita ſcriptumeſt, it is written.</hi> Whereby all his ſouldiers, are taught vpon the like occaſion to vſe the ſame weapon that he did then. As for example; if Sathan entice the Chriſtian to pride, let him an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer him thus, in his heart, avoide proud <hi>Lucifer,</hi> for it is written that <hi>God reſiſteth the preud,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iame 4.6.</note> 
                  <hi>and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth grace vnto the humble.</hi> If to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſnes, let him ſay, auoyde couetous <hi>mammon,</hi> for it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>that the loue of money is the roote of all euill,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.10 Ephe. 5.5.</note> 
                  <hi>and that no couetous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone hath any inheritance in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God.</hi> If to vncleanes and lecherie, let him ſay,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.15 19 Epheſ. 5.5. Reuel. 21.27.</note> auoide vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane ſpirit, for it is written that <hi>our bodies are the members of Chriſt, and the Temple of the holy Ghoſt, and
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:12856:85"/>that no vncleane thing ſhal enter into Gods Citie.</hi> If to cruelty, let him ſay, avoyde manſlayer, for it is written,<note place="margin">Cen 4.10. &amp; 9.1.6</note> that <hi>the voice of blood crieth vnto God from the earth, and who ſo ſheddeth mans bloode, by man ſhall his blood be ſhed.</hi> If to hatred and enuie, let him ſay,<note place="margin">1. Ioh 3.15</note> auoyde man-hater for it is written that <hi>whoſoeuer hateth his brother is a man flayer, and ye know that no man-ſlayer hath eternall life abiding in him.</hi> If to idlenes and ſloth, let him ſay, avoyde ſuggeſter of ſloth and of allſinne,<note place="margin">2. Thess. 3.10. Eze. 16.42</note> for it is written, <hi>if there be any that will not worke, that he ſhould not eate,</hi> and that Idlenes was one of the ſinnes of <hi>Sodome</hi> If to luxurie, exceſſe, intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and ſuperfluity, let him ſay, auoyde licentious Sathan, for it is written, <hi>that we walke honeſtly as in the day,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 13.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 1. Cor. 6.9.10.</note> 
                  <hi>notin gluttonie, and drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kennes,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:12856:85"/>neither in chambering &amp; wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton neſſe.</hi> If to a continuing anger and wrath, let him ſay, auoide au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of ſtrife for it is written,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.26</note> 
                  <hi>let not the Sun go downe vpon your wrath.</hi> If to reuenge, let him ſay, avoyde reuengefull Sathan, for it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. <hi>Reſiſt not euil, reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence to no man euill for euill, auenge not your ſelues,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5.39. Rom. 12.17.19.</note> 
                  <hi>but giue place vnto wrath; for it is written, vengeance is mine, I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay, ſayth the Lord.</hi> If to curſed and euill ſpeaking, to fooliſh or filthy talking, let him ſay, avoyd Sathan, for it is written,<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.29.30. Collo. 3.8.</note> 
                  <hi>let no corrupt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication proceede out of your mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, let all bitternes and euill ſpeaking be put away from you, put away curſed and filthy ſpeaking out of your mouth.</hi> If to lying and deceiuing, let him ſay, auoid father of lies, for it is written,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.25. Colloſ. 3.9.</note> 
                  <hi>caſt off lying and ſpeake e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man truth vnto his neighbour,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:12856:86"/>for we are members one of another.</hi> If preſumption, let him ſay, auoide preſumptuous ſatha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,<note place="margin">Nom. 15.30.</note> 
                  <hi>The perſon that doth ought pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly, the ſame blaſphemeth the Lord, therefore ſhall he be cut of from among his people.</hi> If to deſperation, let him ſay, auoide ſoule-ſlayer,<note place="margin">Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>03.8 11.</note> for it is written that <hi>the Lord is full of compåſſion and mercy, ſlow to anger and of great kindnes, for as high as the heauen is aboue the earth, ſo great is his mercy toward them that feare him. Loe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob. 13.15</note> 
                  <hi>though he ſlay me yet will I truſt in him, and will reproue my wayes in his ſight.</hi> Finally, to whatſoeuer enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mious ſinne it be that ſathan doth tempt and entice the Chriſtian, let him anſwere, avoid ſinfull <hi>Sathan,</hi> for it is written,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.9.</note> that <hi>Tribulation and anguiſh ſhall be vpon the ſoule of euery man that doth euill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus we ſee how the Chriſtian
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:12856:86"/>muſt learne to make vſe of the worde of God againſt all kinde of Tentations &amp; inſtigations what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, and we ſee likewiſe the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent vertue &amp; efficacie of Gods worde. By the worde of God,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.23 Rom. 11.17 Deut. 4.2.6 &amp; 29.9. Iſay 8.6.19.20. Pſal. 119.105.</note> we are borne anew againe, and by the hearing of it faith is begotten in our hearts. The worde of God is our wiſedme, and teacheth vs what we muſt chooſe and what we muſt ſhume, what we ought to doe, and what we muſt leaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done. It is a lanterne vnto our feete, and a light vnto our pathes to direct our wayes and foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps according to godlines, righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, honeſty and peace. Gods worde is the worde of truth,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.13</note> for therby we are taught the right way and manner of Gods true worſhip. It is the worde of life,<note place="margin">Acts 5.20.</note> for by it we are led into the way
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:12856:87"/>that leadeth vnto life, and the word of reconciliation,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.19</note> for it ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth vs how that God in Chriſt hath reconciled the world to him ſelfe by the remiſſion of our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.7.8 9.10.11.</note> The worde or lawe of the Lord is perfite (ſayth the Pſalmiſt) conuerting the ſoule, the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Lord is ſure, and giueth wiſdome vnto the ſimple: the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of the Lord are right, and reioyce the heart: the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of the Lord is pure, and giuetht ligh vnto the eies: the feare of the Lord is cleane, and endureth for euer: the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lord are truth, they are righteous all together, and more to be deſired then golde, yea then much fine golde; ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alſo then hony, and the hony combe: more oeuer, by them is thy ſeruant made circumſpect, and in
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:12856:87"/>keeping of them there is gerat re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde. The word of God is milke to ſuch as are babes in Chriſt,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Heb. 5.12. Epheſ 6.17. Heb. 4.12.</note> and ſtrong meate to ſuch as are more ſtrong in Chriſt, yea it is a ſharp two edged ſword for all ſuch as are ſouldiers in Chriſt, wherwith they may kill ther owne concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcences, and make a ſlaughter of ſinne, and both conquer Sathan and onercome them owne ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues. Good reaſon then that Gods worde be read with all reuerence, and heard with great humilitie, &amp; affected with all feruency and practſed with greateſt diligence and induſtrie of all Chriſtian peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, according as we are exhorted in holy ſcripture.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.11 12</note> 
                  <hi>Be humble to heare the worde of God, that thou maieſt vnderſtand it &amp; make a true anſwere with wiſedome: be ſwift to heare good things, and let thy life be pure, and giue
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:12856:88"/>a patient anſwere ſayth Siracide.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſay 56.2</note> 
                  <hi>Tio him will I looke</hi> (ſayth the Lord by his Prophete <hi>I ſay</hi>) <hi>euen to him that is poore and of a contrite ſpirit, and trembleth at my wordes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mth. 13.9. Marke 4.9 Luke 8.8 Reucl. 2,7. 11.17.29.</note> 
                  <hi>Heare the word of the Lord, all ye that tremble at his worde</hi> ſayth the Prophete to the faithfull people. <hi>He that hath eares to heare let him heare</hi> ſayth our Sauiour, and againe, <hi>let him that hath an eare, heare what the Spirit ſaith vnto the churches.</hi> But the eare and the hearing thereof, is not inough; for Gods word muſt goe from the head and the eare into the heart.<note place="margin">Deut 6.6. &amp; 11.18 &amp; 32.46.</note> 
                  <hi>Theſe wordes,</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>which I command thee this day ſhall be in thine heart:</hi> and againe, <hi>therfore ſhall ye lay vp theſe my words in your heart and in your ſoule.</hi> Gods worde muſt not be leef ſwimming or flittering in the braines by knowledge and ſpeculation, but it
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:12856:88"/>muſt ſink donnewards into the breaſt, &amp; their ſetle it ſelfe by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe and affection: we muſt I ſay keepe the ſayings of Gods worde not in our heade but in our heart,<note place="margin">Luke 2.51. Collo. 3.16</note> as <hi>Marie</hi> the bleſſed mother of <hi>Ieſus</hi> did the ſayings of her ſonne. <hi>Let the worde of God dwell in you plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly</hi> (faith the holy Apoſtle) <hi>in all wiſedome, teaching and admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing your owne ſelues in Pſalmes and himmes, and ſpirituall ſongs ſinging with grace in your hearts to the Lord.</hi> The worde of God muſt dwell in our hearts in deede, by faith and affection, but it muſt likewiſe ſometimes come and ſtand as it were in the doore of the houſe, I meane in the mouth, by confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, inſtruction and admonition. And therefore the Lord conioyneth theſe two together, the heart and the mouth,<note place="margin">Deu. 30.14 Rom. 10.8.9.10.17.</note> 
                  <hi>The worde</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>is
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:12856:89"/>very neere vnto thee, euen in thy mouth and in thine heart.</hi> The ſame ſayeth likewiſe the Apoſtle, and addeth, <hi>This is the word of faith which we preache: for with the heart man belecueth vnto righteouſnes, and with the mouth man confeſſeth to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation:</hi> yea vnto the heart and the mouth he addeth likewiſe the eare, <hi>faith is by hearing</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>and hearing by the worde of God.</hi> And the Lord as he enioyneth his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to ſet ther hearts vnto his worde, and to lay his worde vp in their hearts by faith &amp; affection, ſo he commandeth them to talke of it tarying in the houſe,<note place="margin">Deut. 6.6. &amp; 32.46.47.</note> &amp; wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king by the way, at their lying do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wne and at their riſing vp, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction &amp; admonition; for they muſt euen teache and inſtruct their children therin: And to what end all this, the Lord him ſelfe
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:12856:89"/>doth ſignifie,<note place="margin">Deut. 30.14 &amp; 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.46.47.</note> 
                  <hi>the worde</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>is very neere vnto thee, euen in thy mouth and in thine heart for to do it,</hi> and againe, <hi>ſet your hearts vnto all the wordes which Iteſtifie againſt you this day, that ye may command them vnto your children that they may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue &amp; doe all the wordes of the lawe, for it is no vaine worde concerning you, but it is your life, and by this word ye ſhall prolong your dayes;</hi> ſo that the end of al is <hi>doing.</hi> We heare the worde with the eare, that we may vnderſtand and remember it with the minde; we vnderſtand it with the minde, that we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it and loue it with the heart, and talke of it with the tongue; &amp; the maine end of our hearing, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, remembring, belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, louing, talking and ſpeaking of Gods word, is our liuing and doing according to the ſame: for
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:12856:90"/>as to hearken vnto the worde of God is better then the fat of ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, ſo to obey his worde and his voice, is better then ſacrifice; and the doing of Gods worde is better then the hearing and ſpeaking of the ſame.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15 22. Luk 6.48.49.</note> 
                  <hi>For whoſoeuer commeth to me</hi> (ſayth our Sauiour) <hi>and heareth my wordes, and doeth the ſame, I will ſhewe you to whome he is like: he is like a man which builte an houſe, and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged deepe, and laide the foundation on a rocke: and when the waters aroſe, the flood beat vpon that houſe and could not ſhake it; for it was grounded vpon a rocke. But he that heareth and doth not, is like a man that builte an houſe vpon the earth without foundation, againſt which the floode did beate, and it fell by and by: and the fall of that houſe was great.</hi> So that the doer of the worde is as a wiſe builder that groundeth his houſe vpon the
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:12856:90"/>rocke, where as the bare hearer of the worde is as a fooliſh builder that buildeth vpon the ſand: for when the raine of Gods indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall fall downe vpon the wicked worlde at the day of iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement, and the floode of his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſhall ouerflow the ſinful earth, and the whirle winde of his wrath ſhall blowe from the foure cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and quarters of the earth, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſandie building of an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward profeſſion, together with the fooliſh builder, I meane, the bare hearer or talker of Gods worde, ſhall be beaten downe, neither of them ſhall ſtand, but both of them ſhall haue a great, yea an vnrecouerable fall; and onely the rockie building of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious life which conſiſteth moſt part in action, and in a godly, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber &amp; vpright conuerſation, ſhall
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:12856:91"/>vnſhakeably ſtand &amp; perpetually endure,<note place="margin">Pſal. 125.1.</note> euen as mount Sion which cannot be remoned but remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth for euer. The Lord complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth by his Prophet <hi>Iſaye</hi> of ſuch as come naere vnto him with their mouth,<note place="margin">Iſay 29.13 &amp; 58.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.</note> &amp; honour him with their lips, but haue remoued their heart farre from him. And he complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth of ſuch as would draw nere vnto him with the outward ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice; ſubmiſſion and humiliation of their bodies, &amp; of their hearts too, by afflicting their ſoule for a day, by bowing downe the heade, by lying downe in ſackloth, by fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and crying vnto the Lord, but yet bad remooued their hands too farre from him. And therfore be telleth them that he careth not for their whole religion when as it is not accompanied with action; and that the thing he doth
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:12856:91"/>moſt like of, which in them not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding was moſt lacking, is to put to their hands to the loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing off the bands of wickedens, to the taking of the heauie burdens, to the letting of the oppreſſed goe free, to the breaking off euery yoke, to the dealing of their bread to the hungrie, to the couering of the naked, and to the bringing of the poore that wander, vnto their houſe. And in another place he ſheweth the people of the Iewes,<note place="margin">Iſay 1.10.11.12.13.14.15.16.17.18.19.20.</note> that the chiefe ſeruice he did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire at their handes doth not ſtand in the multitude of their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, &amp; oblations, nor in their ſabbaths and ſolemne aſſemblies, neither yet in their often reſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vnto his courtes and their making of many prayers; but in their waſhing and cleanſing of them ſelues, in their taking away
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:12856:92"/>the euill of their workes from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his eyes, in ceaſing to doe euill, in learning to doe well, in ſeeking of iudgement, in relieuing the oppreſſed,<note place="margin">Zach. 7.9.10.</note> in iudging the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therles and defending the widow. And he telleth them that without ſuch godly actions &amp; executions as theſe, that their whole religion and outward profeſſion is in his eyes no better then an abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; that he maketh no recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their drawing neere vnto him, with their feete in treading in his courtes, with their eares, in hearing of his worde, with their tongues, in making many prayers, with their hearts, in ſorrowing and afflicting their ſoule; ſo long as they drawe not neere vnto him with their hands by holy, vpright and charitable actions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If ye knowe theſe things,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh 13.17</note> 
                  <hi>bleſſed are
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:12856:92"/>ye if ye doe them</hi> ſayth our Sauiour Wherebi we are let to vnderſtand that the bleſſednes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianes doth not ſtand in contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation, but in action: &amp; the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Iames</hi> doth exhort men to be doers of the worde, and teacheth how that it is but a vaine religion which doth not acquire the owne perfection by vertuous working and godly liuing. <hi>Receiue</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>with meekneſſe the word that is graffed in you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iame 1.21.22.23.24.25.26.27.</note> 
                  <hi>which is able to ſaue your ſoules; and be ye doers of the worde, and not hearers onely, deceiuing your owne ſelues: for if any heare the worde, and doe it not, he is like vnto a man that beholdeth his naturall face in a glaſſe. For when he hath conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him ſelfe, he goeth his way, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth immediately what maner of one he was. But who ſo looketh in the perfect law of libertie &amp; continueth
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:12856:93"/>therin, he not being a forgetfull hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, but a doer of the worke, ſhall be bleſſed in his deede. If any man among you ſeemeth religious, and refraineth not his tongue, but deceiueth his owne heart, this mans religion is vaine. Pure religion and vndefiled before God euen the father, is this, to viſite the fatherles, and widowes in their aduerſitie, and to keepe him ſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted of the worlde.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 11. Of the Bowe &amp; arrow of faſting and prayer.</head>
               <p>TO the aboue named partes or pieces of ſpirituall armour, the Chriſtian muſt ioyne yet ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther piece which is the ſeuenth &amp; the laſt, &amp; it is as it were the Bowe &amp; the Arrow of faſting and praer.
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:12856:93"/>For faſting is as it were the Chriſtians bowe, out of which he ſhooteth the Bolte or Arrowe of a pithy and effectuall pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer, able to penetrate or pierce thorow the higheſt heauens. <hi>Pray</hi> (ſayth the Apoſtle) <hi>with all maner prayer and ſupplication in the ſpirit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.18.</note> 
                  <hi>and watch thereunto with all perſeucrance</hi> where (as I ſaid aboue) in the exerciſe of watching, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting is included, for man is then moſt apt to watch when as he doth faſt. The ſame thing doth likewiſe appeare by the great A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles exhortation; <hi>be ſober</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>and watche,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.8</note> 
                  <hi>for your aduerſary the deuill as a roaring lyon walketh about ſeeking whom he may deuoure.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay; when the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill your aduerſarie ſeeketh moſt buſily to feaſte vpon you by your fall, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be ye fartheſt of from fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting;
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:12856:94"/>yea then more then at any other time els giue your ſelues to faſting and praying; for in ſo doing ye ſhall make your enemy to roare and to rampe in vaine, when as he ſhall by the meanes of your faſting and praying find no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to pray or to feaſt vpon. The holy Scripture ſheweth vs abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly how that the beſt and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt men and women haue giuen themſelues much to the exerciſe of faſting our Sauiour as foone as he was led aſide of the ſpirit into the wildernes to be tempted of the deuill,<note place="margin">Mat. 4.1.2.3.</note> began his long faſt or lentfaſt of fourty dayes and as many nights, to teache all his yong ſouldiers chiefly in the time of any great Tentation to giue them ſelues in great earneſtnes to the holy exerciſe of faſting and prayer For faſting mortifieth the
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:12856:94"/>fleſh and weakneth the too ſtrong arme of this our homebred ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: and prayer viuifieth the ſpirit and ſtrengtheneth the ſame to the foyling of the fleſhe. The faſting of the fleſh is the feeding of the ſpirit, and the ſubduing of the Body is the renewing of the mind. Well knew this the bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>S. Paul</hi> who ſayeth of himſelfe, that he was wont <hi>to beate downe his Body and to bring it in ſubiection,</hi> and that he was exerciſed <hi>in watching often,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Corr. 9.27 2. Corr. 11.27. 2. Corr. 4.10. &amp; 6.6.</note> 
                  <hi>in hunger and thirſt and faſting often. Euery where</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>we beare about in our body the dying of the Lord Ieſus, that the life of Ieſus might alſo be made manifeſt in our bodies; by watchings,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exo. 24.28 Deut. 9.9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.18. 1. King. 19.7.8 Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 4.1.2.3</note> 
                  <hi>by faſtings, by purity.</hi> And as we read in holy ſcripture of the forty day faſt of <hi>Moſes, Eliah,</hi> and of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niour <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſo we reade likewiſe of <hi>Daniels</hi> three weeks faſt; during
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:12856:95"/>the which time, he turned his face vnto the Lord God praying vnto him,<note place="margin">Dan. 9.3.4 &amp; 10.2.3. Iudg. 20.26 1 Sam. 7.6 &amp; 31.13. 2. Chron. 20.3. Ezr. 8.21. Ierem. 36.9 Ionah. 3.5.6.7.8.9.10.</note> and making his confeſſion, neither eate he any pleaſant bread nor fleſh, nor dranke any wine. There likewiſe we reade how that the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> faſted &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed their ſinnes at diuers times before the Lord: and the people of <hi>Niniute</hi> did humble themſelues by faſting, and crying myghtily vnto God, who was appeaſed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them &amp; their whole Citie. <hi>Dauid</hi> a man after Gods owne heart, and who knew well inough what thing was moſt agreeable vnto God, telleth vs how that he often humbled his ſoule with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and praying, his eyes with weeping and mourning, his knees with bowing, and his whole body with hardlying, and with fitting in ſackloth and aſhes. <hi>I was clothed
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:12856:95"/>with a ſack</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>I humbled my Soule with faſting,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 31.13.14</note> 
                  <hi>and my prayer was turned vpon my boſome, I humbled my ſelfe mourning as one that bewaileth his mother. Mine heart is ſmitten and withereth like graſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">&amp; 69.10.11</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe I forgate to eate my bread. For the voice of my groaning, my bones doe cleaue to my ſkinne. Surely I haue eaten aſhes as bread,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">&amp; 102.4.5.9. &amp; 109.24.</note> 
                  <hi>and mingled my drinke with weeping, my knees are weake through faſting, and my fleſh hath loſt all fatnes.</hi> And godly Queene <hi>Eſter</hi> who had heene trayned vp in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and feare of God from her youth, in the time of the great danger that Gods people were put in by the malitious practiſes of <hi>Haman.</hi> She together with her maydes of honour,<note place="margin">Eſt. 4.16 &amp; 14.1.2.3.4.5.6.12.14.19.</note> ſpent whole three dayes and three nights in faſting &amp; prayer. She laid away her glorious apparell, and put on the
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:12856:96"/>garments of ſighing and mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, in the ſtead of a pretious oyntment, ſhe ſcattered aſhes and dung vpon her head: and ſhe humbled her body greatly with faſting, and all the places of her ioy filled ſhe with the haire that ſhe plucked off. And ſhe prayed vnto the Lord God of Iſrael, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>O my Lord, thou art our King: helpe me deſolate moman which haue no helper but thee, for my danger is at hand. From my youth vp I haue heard in the kinred of my father, that thou, O Lord tookeſt Iſrael from among all people, and our fathers from their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors for a perpetuall inheritance, and thou haſt performed that which thou did deſt promiſe them. Now Lord, we haue ſinned before thee: therefore haſt thou giuen vs into the hands of our enemies. Think vpon vs O Lord, and ſhew thy ſelfe vnto vs in the time
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:12856:96"/>of our diſtreſſe, and ſtrengthen me O King of Gods, and Lord of all power. Deliuer vs with thine hand, and helpe me that am ſolitary, which haue no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence hut onely thee. O thou mighty God aboue all, heare the voice of them that haue none other hope, and deliuer vs out of the hand of the wicked, and deliuer me out of my feare.</hi> And as Q. <hi>Eſter</hi> and her maides faſted, ſo did <hi>Mordecai,</hi> he alſo rent his clothes, and put on ſackloth and aſhes; &amp; in euery Proumce and place whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Kings charge and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion came (towit for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the Iewes) there was great ſorow among the Iewes, &amp; faſting, and weeping, and mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,<note place="margin">Eſt. 4.15.16.17. &amp; 7.10.</note> and many lay in ſackloth &amp; in aſhes. <hi>Eſter</hi> and <hi>Mordecai</hi> by their faſting and prayer preuailed ouer <hi>Haman</hi> the great enemie of Gods people together with his cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:12856:97"/>complices,<note place="margin">Eſt 9.1.2.3.4.5.13.14.15.16 &amp; 1.11.13.</note> and diſapoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their bloody deuiſes and made him an example that had begun deſtruction againſt them, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their prayer. For <hi>Hama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> had not beene exalted before ſo high in the Kings court, but ere it was long, he was hanged as high, euen vpon a gibbet of fifty cubites height which he had prepared for godly <hi>Mordecai,</hi> and ſo were his tenne ſonnes; yea the Iewes put all their enemies to death, euen all thoſe that roſe againſt them. And in like manner the Chriſtian <hi>Eſters &amp; Mordecaies,</hi> euen Gods ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ones (for <hi>Eſter</hi> ſignifieth hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den or ſecret) and the children of bitter contrition (for <hi>Mordecai</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth bitter contrition) that is, ſuch as doe vnfainedly repent them of their ſinnes by faſting and prayer, they ſhall preuaile ouer
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:12856:97"/>their ſpirituall enemies, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appoynte all their practiſes and attempts for the compaſſing of their ſpirituall ouerthrowe. Yea and the ſpirituall <hi>Haman</hi> for all his hight, euen Sathan the profeſſed enimie of all Gods people, &amp; the great troubler and vprore maker (for ſo much doth the worde <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> ſignifie) ſhal in end be hanged vp on the ſelfe ſame gallous of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperation which he had ſet vp for Chriſtian <hi>Mordecaies,</hi> that is, for the mourning children of contrition to hang them vpon; for his drift is, to make all ſuch (by reaſon of the ſight of their ſinnes) to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire of Gods mercy; but he ſhall be diſappointed: for as I ſaid, he himſelfe ſhall hang on his owne gibbet, together with his ten chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, that is the whole multitude of the impenitent tranſgreſſors of
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:12856:98"/>Gods ten co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, which ſhall likewiſe be hanged vpon the tree of eternall conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation. And in the meane time the ſorow of Chriſts mourning <hi>Mordecaies,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſter 13.17</note> euen of all the repenting children of contrition, ſhall be turned into ioy, according to godly <hi>Mordecaies</hi> petition. <hi>O Lord</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>heere my prayer and be mercifull vnto thy portion, turne our ſorow into ioy, that we may liue O Lord and praiſe thy name: ſhut not the mouthes of them that praiſe thee.</hi> So that light, and ioy, and gladnes, and honour ſhall come vnto them (as it did befall vnto the afflicted Iewes at that time of <hi>Hamans</hi> hurtfull attempt) euen light in ſteede of darkenes,<note place="margin">Eſt. 8.15.16.17.</note> ſolace for ſorow, mirth for mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, feaſting for faſting, deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance for danger, fine linnen for ſackeloth, royall apparell for rags,
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:12856:98"/>and in a worde, for duſt and aſhes, a golden Growne and a ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yall Diademe.<note place="margin">Eſt. 2.7. &amp; 4.16. &amp; 14.1.2.3. &amp; 15.4.8</note> And as the faire and beautifull Queene <hi>Eſter</hi> for all her beautie &amp; maieſtie was not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to humble her ſelfe before the Lord by faſting and prayer &amp; ſitting in ſackloth and athes, ſo godly <hi>Iudith</hi> who was a Lady much admired for her beautie of face and wiſedome of words,<note place="margin">ſudith 8.4.5.5.6.7.8</note> was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe wont to giue her ſelfe much to faſting and prayer: ſo that for the ſpace of three yeeres and more wherin ſhe was widowe, ſhe faſted the moſt part of the weeke, &amp; put on ſackloth on her loynes, and ware her widdowes apparell. Eſpecially before her enterpriſe againſt <hi>Olofernes</hi> the cruell and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannous tormenter of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſhe humbled her ſelfe greatly before the Lord, who gaue her
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:12856:99"/>enterpriſe the deſired iſſue. And truly the confefing and praiſing chriſtian, (for <hi>Iudith</hi> ſignifieth praiſing &amp; confeſſing) that would <hi>Iudith</hi>-like ouercome and kill ſuch a ſtrong Captaine as the ſpirituall <hi>Olofernes</hi> is (for <hi>Olofernes</hi> ſignifieth a ſtrong Captaine, as he was no leſſe indeede,) the Chriſtian man or woman I ſay, that would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue and deſtroy the great decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and deſtroyer, through the ſtrength of Chriſt, muſt be much addicted to the deuout excerciſes of faſting &amp; prayer.<note place="margin">Luke 2.36 37.</note> Alſo it is ſaid of <hi>Anna</hi> the daughter of <hi>phanuel</hi> that ſhe ſerued God with faſtings and prayer, the whole ſpace of foureſcore and foure yeeres; in which doing ſhe did anſwere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her name, and proued a <hi>gratious</hi> woman and euen the godly dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghter of a father ſeeing God; for
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:12856:99"/>
                  <hi>Phanuel</hi> is aſ much as the force of God or ſeing God: and truly ſo many as would ſee God, and take reſt (for <hi>Anna</hi> ſignifieth gratious as ſaid is, or taking reſt) in Gods holy mountaine, muſt in this life harbour holines in their hearts, and giue them ſelues to ſuch holy exerciſes;<note place="margin">Heb. 12.14</note> for <hi>without holines</hi> (ſayth the holy Apoſtle) <hi>noman ſhall ſee the Lord.</hi> By prayer and faſting, <hi>Deuills</hi> are caſt out, and by prayer and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting the deuill is ouercome:<note place="margin">Mat. 17.15 18.19.20.21.</note> alſo the fleſh (which is Sathans hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maide) is effeebled by faſting, for it delighteth in feeding, and by it the worlde is weakned if not van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed, for it deliteth in feaſting.</p>
               <p>The Chriſtian that would playe the good and toward ſouldier, and preuaile ouer his ſpirituall enemie, muſt pray inſtantly; for a praying ſouldier is the beſt ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:12856:100"/>that can be, he muſt pray, and pray in the ſpirit, that is to ſay, faithfully and feruently, for God careth not for the effectles prayers of faithles people.<note place="margin">Iere. 11.14. &amp; 14.12.</note> Of ſuch it is that he ſayeth, <hi>when they crie vnto me in their trouble, I will not heare them</hi> And as the Chriſtian muſt pray, &amp; pray feruently, ſo muſt he pray co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually; for ſo doth the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle exhort almoſt in all his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles: yea and our Sauiour himſelfe ſaith,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. Ephe. 6.18. Coll. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.2. 1. Theſſ. 5.17. Luke 21.36</note> 
                  <hi>Watch and pray co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually that ye may be cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted worthy to eſcape all theſe things that ſhall come to paſſe; and that ye may ſtand before the Sonne of man.</hi> Sathan walketh about vs continually, and he roareth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually for his pray; and therfore the Chriſtian muſt pray conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually, and ſo by prayer he ſhall fruſtrate the deuill of his pray.</p>
               <p>The prayer of <hi>Moſes</hi> made the
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:12856:100"/>
                  <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to preuayle, &amp; <hi>Amalek</hi> to faile: and the feruent prayer of ſuch as Chriſt hath drawen out of the muddie water of the worlde, as <hi>Moſes</hi> was taken vp from among the bulruſhes by the riuers brink, and there vpon got his name (for <hi>Moſes</hi> ſignifieth dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen foorth or taken out) the praier of ſuch I ſay, ouerthroweth ſpirituall <hi>Amalcek</hi> (which is by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation ſtriking,<note place="margin">Ezod. 2.3.4.5.</note> ſiniting or licking) euen all the bloodie and butcherlie ſmiters and ſtrikers of mens ſoules, and the lickers of their blood.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sampſon</hi> by prayer recouered his ſtrength, ſo that he was auen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged vpon the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> which had put out his eyes, and put him in priſon with fetters on his feete, and made him a laughing ſtocke, after that they had corrupted <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilah</hi>
                  <pb n="176" facs="tcp:12856:101"/>to deceiue him. And if at any time the conſuming &amp; deceiuing <hi>Dalilah</hi> of our fleſh (for <hi>Dalilah</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificth a conſumer) conſume vs and deceiue vs ſo farre as to make vs <hi>Sampſon</hi>-like to ſleepe vpon her knees, that is to ſay, lulle vs a ſleep in the cradle of ſecurity, &amp; ſhaue off the haire of our head, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaue vs of our ſpirituall ſtrength, and ſell vs to the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> of our inordinate affections, which will not faile <hi>Philiſtim</hi>-like to put out the eies of our vnderſtanding, and to put fetters vpon our feete, ſo that we can not walke in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes of holynes: If I ſay at an time we runne into ſuch a miſerable miſhap, and yet ſpeedily there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſhall returne penitently vnto God by faſting &amp; prayer, humbly and heartily entreating him with <hi>Sampſon</hi> to reſtore vnto vs our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:12856:101"/>ſtrength, we ſhall not faile with <hi>Sampſon</hi> to kill more <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtims</hi> then euer we did before; that is, to ſlay more of our ſinnefull affections then euer we did at any other time els before our fall. And euen as at the prayer of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 7.9.10.</note> the Lord ſcattered the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtims,</hi> and put them to the flight, yea made them to fall before <hi>Iſrael:</hi> in like maner at the voice of our prayer, the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> of our fleſhly affections ſhal be ſcattered and ouercome, they ſhall flee and fall before the face of our inward man, which is the true <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which is by interpretation pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailing with God.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Dauids</hi> prayer the counſell of <hi>Achitophel</hi> was turned into foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhnes.<note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.31. 2. Kin 1.9.10.11.12.</note> At <hi>Eliahs</hi> prayer <hi>Ahaziahs</hi> meſſengers whom he had ſent to apprehend the Prophet, were
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:12856:102"/>conſumed with fire from heauen-At <hi>Eliſhas</hi> prayer,<note place="margin">2. King 6.18</note> the hoſte of <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hadad</hi> King of <hi>Aram</hi> ſent likewiſe by him to apprehend the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,<note place="margin">2. Kin. 13.14.</note> was ſtricken with blindenes. <hi>Iehoahaz</hi> by his prayer was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered out of the ſeruitude of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaal</hi> King of <hi>Aram.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. King 19.15.16.17.18.19.20.35.</note> 
                  <hi>Ezekiah</hi> by his prayer was aided of Gods mighty Angell againſt the King of <hi>Aſhur,</hi> ſo that there was killed of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies in the campe in one night, an hundreth foure ſcore and fiue thouſand.<note place="margin">2 Chron. 20.1.10.23</note> Finally <hi>Iehoſephat</hi> by his prayer moued God to confound his enemies of <hi>Moab, Ammon</hi> and mount <hi>Seir,</hi> in ſo notable and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable a manner, that he made them to kill one another, ſo that none of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſcaped. In the which and other the like examples, we ſee the great efficacie of prayer for the confuſion of corporall
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:12856:102"/>foes: and yet the vertue of it is greater that doth appeare in the repreſſing of the furie, and diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing of the policie of our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall enemies. For the prayer of the Chriſtian <hi>Dauid</hi> that is of Gods beloued one (for <hi>Dauid</hi> ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifieth beloued) or of an <hi>Eliah</hi> or of an <hi>Ezekiah,</hi> that is, of one that hath the ſtrength of the Lord, or is ſtrong in the Lord by faith (for both theſe wordes or names do import aſmuch as the Lords ſtrength) the feruent prayer of ſuch a one I ſay is able to turne our ghoſtly enemies ſubtilty into foliſhnes, their ſharp ſight into blindnes, their force into feeble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and their furie into faintnes; In one word, the faithfull mans feruent prayer confoundeth their counſells, diſapointeth their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies, turneth them to flight, and
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:12856:103"/>giueth them the foile. And what wonder though that prayer van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh the <hi>wicked one,</hi> ſeeing that it hath often ouercome euen the <hi>good one</hi> him ſelfe,<note place="margin">1. Ioh 2.13.14. Mat. 9.17. Exo. 32.10.11.12.13.14 Iudges 10.10.0.17</note> I meane God who is onely good, and hath euen changed his minde from the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing of his people?</p>
               <p>Admirable then is the force and efficacie of feruent prayer, ſeing it is able to vanquiſhe the deuill againſt his will, &amp; to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come God with his will. So that it is not without great cauſe that the Apoſtle <hi>S. Iames</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">Iame 5.16.17.</note> 
                  <hi>that the prayer of the rightcout man auaileth much, if it beferuent.</hi> And no doubt but that he doth commend vnto vs the diligent practiſe of prayer when as he exhorteth vs thus,<note place="margin">Iam. 4 7 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the deuill, and he will ſtee from you; drawe neere to God, and he will drawe neere to you.</hi> For by pray r the
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:12856:103"/>Chriſtian ſoule doth both reſiſt the deuill, &amp; drawe neere to God; yea by praying and inuoking of his name we walke with God as <hi>Enoch</hi> did.<note place="margin">Gen 5.22.24.</note> And if we walke with God, then dare not the deuill though hebe the great walker &amp; compaſſer of the worlde, be ſo bolde as to walke with vs. If God be neere vs, the deuill dare not ſtirre vs; no, he will flee away from vs, and keepe him ſelfe a farre off.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 12. Of the putting on of the ſpirituall armour, &amp; of the keeping on of it till the end, by perſeuerance in fighting againſt ſinne and inſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of God.</head>
               <p>Now as God hath framed and forged this ſpiritual armour,
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:12856:104"/>for his ſouldiers to arme them with all; ſo doth he offer it to euery one of vs; it reſteth onely that we take it and put it on. <hi>Take vnto you the whole armour of God</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that ye may be able to reſiſt in the euill da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it auaileth not that we take it, vnleſſe we put it on, therefore the ſame Apoſtle exhorteth thus, <hi>Put on the whole armour of God, that ye may be able to ſtand againſt the aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the deuill.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ephe. 6.11.13.</note> We can not reſiſt in the euill day, or perſiſt againſt the euill one without armour, and that Gods armour, ſuch as the heauenly armour-houſe doth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forde, and without we take it to vs, and put it on. And therefore we muſt not be ſo foliſh as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe it when it is offered vs, or to lay it aſide when as we ſhould put it on. It were a great follie for the
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:12856:104"/>Chriſtian to preſume to fight without it, &amp; euen a greater mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, then if a man ſhould goe to the warres without a weapon. So then it behoueth of meere neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that the ſpiritual ſoldier, whom our great capaine <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> hath preſſed out to the field to fight againſt Sathan, the world and the fleſh; that I ſay, he take to him the armour of God, if he would be able to reſiſt in the euill day; that is in the day that the euill one would bring him to an euil end by the perpetrating of an euil action; for ſuch is the deuils ayme. He muſt take the armour, and the whole armour, for a piece or part of it will not ſerue the turne. The ſeuen pieces of it are all of them equally requiſite for the extirping and quelling of the ſeuen capitall ſinnes; to the end, that the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:12856:105"/>may become a fit habitacle for the holy ghoſt, &amp; a meet recep tacle of his ſeaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> principall gifts.</p>
               <p>If Sathan eſpie any part of our ſpirituall man vnarmed, he will not miſſe to worke vs ſome miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, and to wounde vs in that part with one of his dartes, and that in a deadly manner, if he can; and therefore if we wiſh to fight without receiuing of any deadly wound, whether in the head or in the hart, at our aduerſaries hands, we muſt take heed that we be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med on al parts. And as the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt take this armor, yea this whole armour, ſo muſt he take it to himſelf, and for himſelfe: take vnto you (ſayth the Apoſtle) meaning that euery man muſt play the ſouldier for him ſelfe: Be we yong or olde, men or women, rich or poore, noble or baſe, ſtrong or
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:12856:105"/>weake, euery one of vs muſt beare armour vpon our owne backe, &amp; fight for him ſelfe as Chriſt hath foughten for vs all. Kings and great men haue their armour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearers, but Chriſtians muſt haue none. Kings haue men to fight for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but Chriſtians muſt fight for themſelues.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 17.38.39.40.</note> 
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> could not goe out againſt <hi>Goliah</hi> in <hi>Sauls</hi> armour, and therefore he put it off, and betooke him ſelfe to his owne ſtaffe, his ſling and his fiue ſtones; to ſhewe vs, that in the Chriſtian warrefare eche man muſt fight in his owne armour, with his owne faith, charity, and hope, and not with another mans.</p>
               <p>And as the Chriſtian muſt take this armour, and this whole armour, and that to himſelfe, and for himſelfe, and as he muſt put it on, and not lay it aſide, ſo muſt he
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:12856:106"/>continually keepe it on, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer put it off. For no man can ſtand ſtedfaſt in the faith, as the Apoſtle doth exhort, except hee ſtand faſt in his armour,<note place="margin">Ephe. 6.11.13</note> and be a ſtedfaſt fighter. He that perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to the end ſhall be ſaued, and he that fighteh to the end ſhall be crowned. And therefore the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.12</note> as he exhorteth <hi>Timothie</hi> to <hi>fight the good fight of faith, and to lay hold on cternall life,</hi> in ſo doing: ſo he ſpeaketh thus of him ſelfe, the time of his departing being nere, <hi>I haue fought a good fight,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.6.7.8.</note> 
                  <hi>and haue finiſhed my courſe; I haue kept the faith, henceforth is laid vp for me the crowne of righteouſneſſe, which the Lord the righteous Iudge ſhall giue me at that day, and not to me onely, but vnto all them that loue his appcoring.</hi> Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> whole life time from the firſt houre of his conuerſion
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:12856:106"/>to the laſt houre of his diſſolution was no other thing but as a day of battell; he began his fight cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſly, hee continued in fighting conſtantly, and ended triamphantly, and ſo muſt we.</p>
               <p>Sathans fighting is his temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, wherefore when the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is tempted, let this both comfort him and encourage him, that thereby he knoweth that he is not the Deuils ſubiect, but Gods ſouldier, euen the Lords warrior, and the Deuils vanquiſher: for no King warreth at any time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his owne people, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his enemies. When the Deuill tempteth thee, he maketh warre againſt thee, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently thou art none of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, but one of Gods ſeruants. Endeauour therefore to play the part of a valiant warriour, and
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:12856:107"/>pretend neither the fortitude, nor the multitude of thine enemies for excuſe. For the greater that they be for number and ſtrength, the more ſhalt thou ouercome, and the more glorious ſhall thy victorie be, and the greater thy reward. Likewiſe, this ought to encourage vs to fight; that wee haue armour forged for vs by the finger of God, and furniſhed vnto vs by the holy Spirit out of the heauenly armour houſe of the Lord of hoſtes. For it is hee that aideth and aſſiſteth vs,<note place="margin">Iſay 43.2. Pſal 50.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5. &amp; 121.1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8. 2. Theſ 3.3</note> and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth vs with ſtrength to ſtand faſt, to fight and to ouercome. And if we be weake, his fatherly wiſedome will not ouer charge vs as the Apoſtle teacheth.<note place="margin">1. Corr 13.13.</note> 
                  <hi>There hath no temptation taken you</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>but ſuch as apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth to man: and God is faithfull,
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:12856:107"/>which will not ſuffer you to be tempted aboue that you be able, but will euen giue the iſſue with the temptation that ye may be able to beare it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And not onely doth he giue vs armour and aide in our Chriſtian warfare, together with a ſpirituall ſtrength, but likewiſe he will giue vs victory ouer all our ſpirituall enemies through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, as the ſame Apoſtle doth deliuer.<note place="margin">Iohn 4.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Litle children</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Iohn</hi>) <hi>yee are of God, and haue ouercome them: for greater is hee that is in you, then he that is in the world;</hi> that is, then Sathan the Prince of the world, and the luſts of the fleſh, and of the eyes that are in the world. <hi>For all that is borne of God o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercometh the world,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Ioh 5.4.5</note> 
                  <hi>and this is the victorie that ouercometh the world, euen our faith.</hi> And therefore the Apoſtle exhorteth men aboue all
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:12856:108"/>to take vnto them the ſhield of faith, wher with they may quench al the fierie darts of the Deuil. For it is euen faith in our Lord Ieſus Chriſt that foyleth all our foes,<note place="margin">1. Iohn 2.13.14.15.16.17. &amp; 4 4. &amp; 5.4. Gen. 4 20 2. King 19.6.7. 1. Sam. 17 46 47. Iuag. 4.14.15.33.</note> &amp; winneth the field.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> faught againſt <hi>Chedar Laomer,</hi> and God gaue him victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; ſo did hee to <hi>Ezekiah</hi> againſt <hi>Senaherib</hi> &amp; to <hi>Daurd</hi> againſt <hi>Goliah</hi> and the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> and to <hi>Debora</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Siſera</hi> the Captaine of <hi>Iahin</hi> King of Canaan; and if we prooue the children of <hi>Abraham</hi> by being followers of his faith, and workers of his workes, God ſhall giue vs victorie againſt the ſpirituall <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar Laomer,</hi> which is by interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation the generation of bondage, euen againſt our fleſhſly affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which would bring vs into bondage ſpiritually and eternally.</p>
               <p>If we endeauour to be <hi>Ezekiahs</hi>
                  <pb n="191" facs="tcp:12856:108"/>that is, men endued with the ſtrength of the Lord by faith and holineſſe, then the ſpirituall <hi>Sena<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>herib</hi> which is as much as the bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of deſtruction, ſhal be brought to deſtruction, together with the ravling <hi>Rabſakehs</hi> of our raging af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, euen theſe miſerable ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-drinkers (for ſo much doth the word <hi>Rabſakeh</hi> ſignifie) which drinke in ſinne as the fiſh doe water. If we be deuote like <hi>Dauid</hi> &amp; euen of the Lords beloued ones (for <hi>Dauid</hi> ſigniſieth beloued) then the ſpirituall <hi>Galiah</hi> which is the great Captaine of captiuitie, ſhall be conquered by the meanes of the ſtone of Chriſt crucified throwen or flung againſt his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head out of the ſling of an effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all faith; &amp; the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> of our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, which are the authors of our double decay, euen in Soule
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:12856:109"/>and body (for <hi>Philiſtim</hi> as I ſaid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boueſi, gnifieth a doubledecay) ſhal be diſcomfited; Finally if we proue ſuch laborious &amp; dilligent Bees in drawing the hony of holineſſe out of the ſweet dewy floweres of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian vertues, as <hi>Deborah</hi> was (which is by interpretation a Bee) we ſhall not faile to triumph ouer the ſpirituall <hi>Iabin,</hi> the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Tyrant of wickedneſſe (for <hi>Iabin</hi> was a Tyrant, and ſignifieth building) and ouer all his <hi>Siſeras,</hi> euen ouer all our ſinnes. So that as when the Lord gaue victorie vnto the people of Iſraell ouer <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his people,<note place="margin">Exod. 15.</note> then <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Iſraelites ſung a ſong of praiſes: In like manner, when as we haue got the victorie ouer the ſpirituall <hi>Pharaoh</hi> through the ſtrength of Chriſt, then ſhall wee ſing the ſong of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:12856:109"/>ſong of the Lambe: The Lord is my ſtrength and praiſe (ſhall the victorious Chriſtian ſay) and hee is become my ſaluation, he is my God and my father, and I will exalt him. The Lord is a man of warre, his name is <hi>Iehouah,</hi> ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall <hi>Pharaos</hi> Chariot, his hoſte, and his choſen Captaines, euen all his helliſh hang-men hath hee drowned in the red ſea of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation; the depths of fire and Brimſtone haue couered them, they ſhall ſinke to the bottome as a ſtone. Thy right hand O Lord is glorious in power, thy right hand O Lord, hath bruiſed the enemie: the Lord ſhall raigne for euer and euer. O death, where is thy ſting? O graue where is thy victory? O ſinne where is thy ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraignty? O Sathan where is thy power and policie? O hell where
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:12856:110"/>is thy tyrannie?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thankes be vnto God which hath giuen vs victorie through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cori. 15.55.57.</note> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. 13. Of Gods ample rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of ſuch as fight againſt ſin valiamly, and continue in his ſeruice conſtantly vnto the end.</head>
               <p>NEuer was there any ſeruant ſo well rewarded of his maſter for his ſeruice, nor ſouldier in the field ſo largely remunerated of his Generall for his valour &amp; war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proweſſe, as ſhall be Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; ſouldier for his towardnes &amp; forwardnes in ſeruing of God, and in fighting againſt ſinne and Sathan. We reade how <hi>Caleb</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:12856:110"/>
                  <hi>Othniel</hi> for ſmiting and taking of the towne of <hi>Debir,</hi> in giuing him <hi>Achſach</hi> his daughter to wife,<note place="margin">Ioſh. 13.15.16.17.18.19.20.</note> together with fields and ſprings of water with her for an inheritance. And how <hi>Saul</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded <hi>Dauid</hi> for foyling the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtims</hi> by giuing him likewiſe his daughter <hi>Michal</hi> to wife,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 17.25. &amp; 28.27.</note> together with much riches. And if we proue valiant in the ſpirituall warrefare and in fighting Gods battels againſt the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> of our fleſhly affections, and againſt the maſter <hi>Philiſtim,</hi> the ſpirituall <hi>Goliah,</hi> the great Captaine of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall captiuitie (as the name doth beare) we ſhall not miſſe to be honoured with the mariage of the Lambe in the land of the liuing, which ſhall be our inheritance; where we ſhall be arayed with pure fine linnen and
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:12856:111"/>ſhining, for the fine linnen is the righteouſnes of ſaints ſayth <hi>S. Iohn</hi> euen he who ſaw the warriers of Chriſt following him vpon white horſes clothed with fine linnen white &amp; pure; giuing vs therby to vnderſtand that the Chriſtian then fighteth moſt valiantly againſt Sathan, when as he endeauoureth to lead and liue a pure and an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted life. And heer in true reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion doth chiefly ſtand as <hi>S. Iames</hi> teacheth <hi>Pure religion</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and vndefiled before God euen the father, is this, to viſit the fatherles, and widowes in their aduerſitie, and to keep him ſelfe vnſpotted of the world.</hi> White is the colour of puritie, of grace and of glorie; and therefore it is, that <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſawe none caried in heauen vpon white horſes, and arayed in the white ſhining robes of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, but ſuch as had heere on earth
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:12856:111"/>couered their inward man with the white linnen of an vnſpotted life, or at leaſt had waſhed out the ſpots and blots of their misbeha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, with the ſalt teares of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition. So that he that hath not worne and borne the white of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegritie and puritie, in and on his heart heere in this life, ſhall not attaine to be adorned &amp; decored with the white pearlie Diadenie of glorie vpon his head after this life The which thing the holy Pſalmiſt doth likewiſe teache in theſe words;<note place="margin">Pſalm 24.3.4.5.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Who ſhall aſeende into the mountaine of the Lord? and who ſhall ſtand in his holy place? euen he that hath innocent handes, and a pure heart: which hath not lift vp his minde vnto vanitie, nor ſworne deceitfully. He ſhall receiue a bleſſing from the Lord, and righteouſnes from the God of his ſaluation. This is the generation
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:12856:112"/>of them that ſeeke him, of them that ſeeke thy face.</hi> None ſhall ſtand in Gods holy mountaine, but ſuch as haue heere harboured holynes in their hearts;<note place="margin">Heb. 12.14</note> 
                  <hi>for without holynes no man ſhall ſee the Lord,</hi> ſayth the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle; and the man that ſeeketh not Gods face heere, ſhall not ſee his face heereafter.</p>
               <p>And as the good ſeruants of God ſhall be clothed with fine white linnen in ſigne of puritie &amp; integritie, ſo ſhall they beare pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes in their handes in ſigne of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie and felicitie. And therefore bleſſed <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſawe thoſe that ſtoode before the throne,<note place="margin">Reuel. 7.9.</note> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lambe, not only clothed with long white robes, but alſo hauing palmes in their hands.</p>
               <p>K. <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> commanded <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> to be clothed with purple,<note place="margin">Dan. 5.16.29</note> and a chaine of golde to be put about
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:12856:112"/>his necke, and made him to be proclaimed the third ruler in the kingdome for his wiſedome, in reading the writing of the Angel vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wall, &amp; in ſhewing the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thereof. And <hi>Ioſeph</hi> for his exceeding great wiſedome, ſhewed in expounding of <hi>Pharaos</hi> dreame was ſo highly honoured,<note place="margin">Gen. 41.40 41.42.43. Pſal. 105 17.18.19.20.21.22.</note> that the king tooke off his ring from his hand, and put it vpon <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephs</hi> finger, and arayed him in gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of fine linnen, and put a golden chaine about his neck, and ſet him ouer his houſe, and ouer the whole land, and made him to ſit vpon the beſt Charet he had ſaue one.</p>
               <p>And no doubt but the King of Kings wil highly honour his good ſeruants that haue honoured him in this life, according to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, ſaying,<note place="margin">1. Samu. 2.30.</note> 
                  <hi>Them that honour me
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:12856:113"/>I will honour.</hi> He will euen honour his <hi>Daniels</hi> and his <hi>Ioſephs,</hi> that is, all his vprightand perfit ones (for <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſignifieth perfit) which doe begin in their young yeares with <hi>Daniel</hi> and <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to ſerue and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him, and doe conſtantly continue in his ſeruice ſtill increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and growing in grace and in godlineſſe, and alwayes ayming at Chriſtian perfection whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our Sauior doth exhort vs, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Ye ſhall therefore be perfit as your Father which is in heauen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5.46.</note> 
                  <hi>is perfit.</hi> The King of <hi>Egypt</hi> tooke off his ring from his hand, and put it v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon <hi>Ioſephs,</hi> and arayed him in garments of fine linnen, and put a gold chaine about his necke, and the King of Kings will one day ſay vnto his ſeruants concerning ſuch a man as hath ſerued him with an vpright heart, <note place="margin">Luk 15.22.23.</note> 
                  <hi>Bring forth the beſt
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:12856:113"/>robe, and put it on him, and put a ring on his hand, and ſhoes on his feete;</hi> bring forth the white wedding garment with the reſt of the nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial ornaments, and let him be clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed, &amp; adorned therewith, &amp; let him ſit downe to feaſt at the table of God (will hee ſay) for ſuch is his promiſe.<note place="margin">Reue. 7.11 17.28. &amp; 3.5.</note> 
                  <hi>To him that ouercometh</hi> (ſaith the Lord Ieſus to St. <hi>Iohn</hi>) <hi>will I giue to eate of the tree of life, which is in the middeſt of the Paradiſe of God: he that ouercometh ſhall not be hurt of the ſecond death. To him that ouercometh will I giue to eate of the Manna that is hid, and will giue him a white ſtone, and in the ſtone a new name written, which no man knoweth ſauing he that receaueth it: Euen as I receiued of my father, ſo will I giue him the morning ſtarre. He that ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh, ſhall be clothed in white aray, and I will not put out his name out of
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:12856:114"/>the Booke of life, but I will confeſſe his name before my father, and before his Angels.</hi> King <hi>Pharao</hi> ſet <hi>Ioſeph</hi> vpon the beſt charet hee had ſaue one, but our king wil honour his good &amp; perfite ſeruant yet in an higher manner;<note place="margin">Reuel. 3.21</note> 
                  <hi>To him that ouercometh</hi> (ſayth our king <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi>) <hi>will I grant to ſit with me in my throne, euen as I ouercame, and ſit with my father in his throne</hi> Finally as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was ſet ouer <hi>Pharaohs</hi> houſe, and ouer the whole land of <hi>Egypt;</hi> ſo God will make his good and perfite ſeruant ruler of all his goods.<note place="margin">Reuel. 2.26 27. &amp; 3.12.</note> 
                  <hi>To him that ouercometh</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>will I giue po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer ouer nations, and he ſhall rult them with a rod of yron: and as the veſſels of a potter ſhall they be broken. Him that ouercometh will I make a pillar in the Temple of my God, and he ſhall go no more out: and I will write vpon him the name of my God, and the name of
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:12856:114"/>the City of my God which is the new Ieru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſalem, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth down out of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from my God, &amp; I will write vpon him my new name.</hi> Euen thus ſhall it be don vnto the man that hath ſerued Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly by holines &amp; new<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of life; for the new name &amp; the new Ieruſalem, and the new wine the ſpirit of God ſpeaketh of in the ſcripture, are ordained onely for new creatures. And therefore the Apoſtle doth exhorte thus;<note place="margin">2. Corr. 5.17</note> 
                  <hi>If any man be in Chriſt, let him be a new creature:</hi> thereby giuing vs to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande, that no man after this life ſhall ſee Chriſt in the new Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem; but he that in this life hath followed his footſteps by newnes of life. And this is that thing which is intimated vnto vs by the euangelicall Prophete <hi>S. Iohn</hi> when as he telleth vs that he ſaw all things made new.<note place="margin">Reuel. 21.1 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; 19.7.8 9 &amp; 14.3.</note> For he
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:12856:115"/>ſaw a new heauen, &amp; a new earth, and a new Ieruſalem, comming downe from God out of heauen, prepared as a bride trimmed for her husband. He ſawe the lambes wife arayed with pure fine linnen which was likewiſe new, and the ſupper which he ſaw made for the mariage of the Lambe, was in like manner new; for he that ſate vpon the throne ſaid, beholde I make all things new. And as the things which he ſaw with his eyes were new, ſo the muſicke which he heard with his eares was ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blably new; for he heard a new ſong ſung by the harpers of God vpon a ten ſtringed inſtrument. And therefore queſtionles <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſaw none inuited to that new mariage to eate of that new ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, and to drinck of that new wine with Chriſt in the new Ieruſalem,
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:12856:115"/>to weare that new wedding gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; to receiue the impreſſion of that new name, &amp; in one word, to hear the ioyful melodie of that new muſick; but ſuch as did here in this olde earth (where all things are olde) indeauoure to be new creatures by newnes of life. As for all olde creatures, that is, ſuch as doe follow the crooked footſteps of olde <hi>Adams</hi> corruption by car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalitie and ſenſualitie, and are not made new by the renouation of the holy ghoſt, after the likenes of the new Adam, when al old things ſhal paſſe away, they ſhal periſh &amp; paſſe away likewiſe with them.<note place="margin">Pſal 125.1</note> But the new creture ſhalbe as mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Si on which cannot be remoued, but remaineth for euer, &amp; ſhall enioy al the new things aboue named.<note place="margin">Reue. 21.7</note> 
                  <hi>for he that ouercometh</hi> (ſayth our great Captain <hi>Chriſt Ieſus) ſhall inherit all things, and I will be his God, and he
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:12856:116"/>ſhall be my ſonne.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſt. 6.8.9.10.11 &amp; 8.2.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Mordecaie</hi> for his fidelitie and good ſeruice, at the appoyntment of king <hi>Ahaſueroſh,</hi> was arayed in royall apparell, in white, purple and blew, and a ring of gold was put on his finger, and a crowne of golde was ſet vpon his head, and he him ſelfe was ſet to ride vpon the kings horſe through the ſtreete of the citie of <hi>Shuſhan,</hi> &amp; they proclaimed before him, <hi>Thus ſhall it be done vnto the man whome the King will honour;</hi> and the citie of <hi>Shuſhan</hi> reioyced and was glad. In like manner our great <hi>Ahaſueroſh,</hi> our great Prince and head (for <hi>Ahaſueroſh,</hi> ſignifieth a Prince or head, as he was indeed a great prince) he will exalt &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour all his good &amp; well deſeruing <hi>Mordecaies</hi> euen all the children of contrition (for <hi>Mordecaie</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth ſo much) which haue in this
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:12856:116"/>life honoured God by their holy liuing, and haue humbled them ſelues vnder his hand for their ſinnes. No, the Chriſtian that hath played the good ſeruant and ſtout ſouldier in fighting manfully vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Chriſts Banner againſt ſinne and Sathan, and hath perſeuered in his ſeruice vnto the end, and conſequently hath ouercome, he ſhall not miſſe of a far more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious rewarde by a thowſand de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees then euer king <hi>Ahaſueroſh</hi> could giue. The royall apparell that this king gaue <hi>Mordecaie</hi> was no better then a rag, if it be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the good Chriſtians glorious wedding garment: and what is a kings corruptible cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wne being compared with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible Crowne of glorie, which ſhall be ſet vpon the head of the heauenly minded man in the
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:12856:117"/>kingdome of heauen? for the crowne that we runne, and ſerue and fight for, is an vncorruptible crowne,<note place="margin">1. Corr. 9.25.</note> ſo doth bleſſed <hi>S. Paul</hi> call it, and likewiſe the great Apoſtle <hi>S. Peter</hi> who calleth it the vncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible crowne of glorie.<note place="margin">1. Pet 5.4.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Iames</hi> calleth it the crowne of life.<note place="margin">Iame 1.12</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is the man</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>that endureth Tentation, for when he is tryed, he ſhall receiue the crowne of life, which the Lord hath promiſed to them that loue him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reut. 2.10.</note> So doth bleſſed <hi>S. Iohn</hi> or rather our Sauiour him ſelf call it in the Reuelation, <hi>Be thou faithfull vnto the death</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>and I will giue thee the crowne of life.</hi> In one worde, the crowne that ſhall be ſet vpon the good Chriſtians head, is the crowne of life, immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie and glorie, which he ſhall weare in the kingdom of heauen, which is the place of life, immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:12856:117"/>and glory.</p>
               <p>Thus then wee ſee how that temptation is to the godly the high way of heauenly happineſſe and honour: Let the Chriſtian then endure temptation and he is bleſſed, and let him ouercome temptation &amp; he ſhall be Crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and that with an incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Crowne.</p>
               <p>Thus ſhall he one day, being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayed in fine white linnen, ride <hi>Mordecay</hi>-like, vpon a faire white horſe, with a Crowne of incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible Gold vpon his head;<note place="margin">Reu. 19.13 14.</note> (for Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw Chriſts warriours thus arayed, riding vpon white Horſes) he ſhall I ſay ride throgh the ſtreets of <hi>Shuſhan,</hi> which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue,<note place="margin">Eſter. 6.10.11. &amp; 8.15.16.</note> and is the true Citty of ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, more faire and ſweeter a thouſand folde then the Lilly or
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:12856:118"/>the Roſe (for <hi>Schuſhan</hi> ſignifieth a Lilly or Roſe, or ioyfulnes) and Gods Heralds ſhall proclaime be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him: Thus ſhall the perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Chriſtian be honoured in Heauen, who hath honoured God on Earth. And the Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Shuſhan</hi> which is aboue, euen the holy Citty new <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel 21.2 11. &amp;c.</note> which Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw diſcending out of heauen from God, hauing the glory of God and ſhining as a Iaſper-ſtone cleere and pretious, whoſe wall is of Iaſper, and the ſtreete of pure Gold, &amp; the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of twelue pretious ſtones, &amp; the Gates of twelue pearles, and hath no neede of Sunne or Moone to ſhine in it, for the Lambe is the light of it; and whereinto no vncleane thing can enter: euen this ſelfeſame glorious Citty ſhall be glad and reioyce in the daye
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:12856:118"/>that our great Kings well deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>Mordecaies</hi> ſhall goe through the ſtreete thereof in royall appar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell of red and white, with a great Crowne of incorruptible gold v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon their heads. Finally,<note place="margin">Eſt. 8.16.17.</note> that day ſhall bee a feaſt-day for Men and Angells, and God himſelfe ſhall be the great Maſter of the feaſt, where they ſhall eate of the fruit of the Tree of life, which is in the middes of the Paradiſe of God,<note place="margin">Reu. 27.17 &amp; 7.17. &amp; 21.6. &amp; 22.1.</note> &amp; of the hidden Manna, and drinke of the water of life, which Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw cleere as Chriſtall, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding out of the throne of God and of the Lambe: euen ſuch a wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as is ſweeter then the ſweeteſt wine, and is both water and wine, and both the beſt water and the beſt wine that euer either well or vine did yeeld, or yet any man did euer drinke. All men at the firſt ſet
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:12856:119"/>forth good wine, but God ſhall bring forth the beſt wine laſt:<note place="margin">Reue. 21.5. Mat. 26.29</note> for he that maketh all things new, ſhal alſo make a new wine for the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage feaſt of the Lamb and his Spouſe. Onely it belongeth to vs to make our ſelues new veſſels for the receiuing of this new wine, by newnes of life; for if no man put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth new wine into old veſſels,<note place="margin">Math. 9.17</note> as our Sauiour ſaith, then truly God will much leſſe put his new wine into olde veſſels. And therefore if we deſire to drinke of this newe wine, in the new Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; in the Celler of God; let vs now endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to put on the new man, (as I ſaid before) which after God is created in righteouſnes and true holynes,<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.23.24.</note> according as the Apoſtle exhorteth, and ſo in that great feaſt day, we ſhall ſit downe at his Table and his fruit ſhall be ſweet
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:12856:119"/>vnto our mouth, he ſhall bring vs into his wine-celler,<note place="margin">Cant. 2.3.4.5</note> and Loue ſhall be his Banner ouer vs, &amp; the Chriſtian Soule ſhall then ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our Spouſe, ſtay <hi>me with flag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons, and comforte me with apples; for I am ſicke of loue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus in the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the godly ſhall ſee and heare nothing but ſweetneſſe, and ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe; nothing but loue, life, and light.<note place="margin">Reuel. 21.4.5.6. &amp; 2.7.</note> Then there ſhall be no more ſorrow, for God ſhall cheere vs; no more paine, for Chriſt ſhall eaſe vs: no more weeping nor crying, for Chriſt ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vs, and wipe away all teares from our eyes; nor no more death, for God will giue vs to cate of the tree of life, and to drinke of the water of life. He will giue vs wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but yet ſuch a water as ſhall be wine, and a ſweeter water then
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:12856:120"/>the ſweeteſt wine, as I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſaid. To conclude, if earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wine hath ſuch a property to make glad the heart of man, how much more ſhall this heauenly wine reioyce the ſoule of man? and what meruaile though that ſuch new heauenly wine, make the glorified Soule ſing a new hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly ſong, euen a new Halleluiah <hi>Let vs be glad and roioyce, and giue glory to him?</hi> Chiefely when as we ſhall heare our ſweete Sauiour in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiting vs in this manner. <hi>Eate ô friends, drinke and make you merry ô welbeloued:</hi> drinke (ſhall he ſay) e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the ſpiced wine, &amp; new wine of the pomegranate: and it being the time apoynted for the conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Godlies ioy, by him who hath ſaid it: <hi>I will create Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem as a reioycing, and her people as a ioy; and I will reioyce in Ieruſalem,
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:12856:120"/>and ioy in my people.</hi> God ſhall then ioy in vs, and we ſhall ioy in him, with ioy vnſpeakeable and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: <hi>For the things which eye hath not ſeene, neither eare hath heard, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther came into mens heart, are which God hath prepared for them that loue him:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To whome alone be glory.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed by E. Alde, for Ed. White dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling nere the little north-dore of Paules, at the ſigne of the Gun. <hi>1612.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
